<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1800: Hart-leap Well</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB00-2_HART</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="HART">
                  <title>[HART]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB00-2">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB00-2.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1800</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">8 to 13</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">13</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <head>
            <emph>HART-LEAP WELL.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </emph>
            <note place="head">
               <emph>Hart-Leap Well is a small spring of
                                        water, about five miles <lb/> from Richmond in Yorkshire,
                                        and near the side of the road <lb/> which leads from
                                        Richmond to Askrigg. Its name is derived <lb/> from a
                                        remarkable chace, the memory of which is preserved <lb/> by
                                        the monuments spoken of in the second Part of the following
                                        <lb/> Poem, which monuments do now exist as I have there
                                        described <lb/> them. </emph>
            </note>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="1" type="stanza">
               <l n="1">The Knight had ridden down from Wensley moor</l>
               <l n="2">With the slow motion of a summer’s cloud;</l>
               <l n="3">He turn’d aside towards a Vassal’s door,</l>
               <l n="4">And, “ Bring another Horse!” he cried
                                        aloud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2" type="stanza">
               <l n="5">“Another Horse!”—That shout the Vassal
                                        heard,</l>
               <l n="6">And saddled his best steed, a comely Grey ;</l>
               <l n="7">Sir Walter mounted him ; he was the third</l>
               <l n="8">Which he had mounted on that glorious day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="2" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="3" type="stanza">
               <l n="9">Joy sparkled in the prancing Courser’s eyes ;</l>
               <l n="10">The horse and horsemen are a happy pair ;</l>
               <l n="11">But, though Sir Walter like a falcon flies,</l>
               <l n="12">There is a doleful silence in the air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4" type="stanza">
               <l n="13">A rout this morning left Sir Walter’s Hall,</l>
               <l n="14">That as they gallop’d made the echoes roar ;</l>
               <l n="15">But horse and man are vanish’d, one and all ;</l>
               <l n="16">Such race, I think, was never seen before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5" type="stanza">
               <l n="17">Sir Walter, restless as a veering wind,</l>
               <l n="18">Calls to the few tired dogs that yet remain :</l>
               <l n="19">Brach, Swift and Music, noblest of their kind,</l>
               <l n="20">Follow, and weary up the mountain strain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6" type="stanza">
               <l n="21">The Knight halloo’d, he chid and cheer’d
                                        them on</l>
               <l n="22">With suppliant gestures and upbraidings stern;</l>
               <l n="23">But breath and eye-sight fail, and, one by one,</l>
               <l n="24">The dogs are stretch’d among the mountain
                                        fern.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="3" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="7" type="stanza">
               <l n="25">Where is the throng, the tumult of the chace ?</l>
               <l n="26">The bugles that so joyfully were blown ?</l>
               <l n="27">—This race it looks not like an earthly race
                                        ;</l>
               <l n="28">Sir Walter and the Hart are left alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8" type="stanza">
               <l n="29">The poor Hart toils along the mountain side ;</l>
               <l n="30">I will not stop to tell how far he fled,</l>
               <l n="31">Nor will I mention by what death he died;</l>
               <l n="32">But now the Knight beholds him lying dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9" type="stanza">
               <l n="33">Dismounting then, he lean’d against a thorn ;</l>
               <l n="34">He had no follower, dog, nor man, nor boy :</l>
               <l n="35">He neither smack’d his whip, nor blew his
                                        horn,</l>
               <l n="36">But gaz’d upon the spoil with silent joy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10" type="stanza">
               <l n="37">Close to the thorn on which Sir Walter
                                        lean’d,</l>
               <l n="38">Stood his dumb partner in this glorious act ;</l>
               <l n="39">Weak as a lamb the hour that it is yean’d,</l>
               <l n="40">And foaming like a mountain cataract.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="4" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="11" type="stanza">
               <l n="41">Upon his side the Hart was lying stretch’d :</l>
               <l n="42">His nose half-touch’d a spring beneath a
                                        hill,</l>
               <l n="43">And with the last deep groan his breath had
                                        fetch’d</l>
               <l n="44">The waters of the spring were trembling still.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12" type="stanza">
               <l n="45">And now, too happy for repose or rest,</l>
               <l n="46">Was never man in such a joyful case,</l>
               <l n="47">Sir Walter walk’d all round, north, south and
                                        west,</l>
               <l n="48">And gaz’d, and gaz’d upon that darling
                                        place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13" type="stanza">
               <l n="49">And turning up the hill, it was at least</l>
               <l n="50">Nine roods of sheer ascent, Sir Walter found</l>
               <l n="51">Three several marks which with his hoofs the beast</l>
               <l n="52">Had left imprinted on the verdant ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14" type="stanza">
               <l n="53">Sir Walter wiped his face, and cried, “ Till
                                        now</l>
               <l n="54">Such sight was never seen by living eyes :</l>
               <l n="55">Three leaps have borne him from this lofty brow,</l>
               <l n="56">Down to the very fountain where he lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="5" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="15" type="stanza">
               <l n="57">I’ll build a Pleasure-house upon this spot,</l>
               <l n="58">And a small Arbour, made for rural joy ;</l>
               <l n="59">’Twill be the traveller’s shed, the
                                        pilgrim’s cot,</l>
               <l n="60">A place of love for damsels that are coy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16" type="stanza">
               <l n="61">A cunning Artist will I have to frame</l>
               <l n="62">A bason for that fountain in the dell ;</l>
               <l n="63">And they, who do make mention of the same,</l>
               <l n="64">From this day forth, shall call it Hart-leap Well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17" type="stanza">
               <l n="65">And, gallant brute ! to make thy praises known,</l>
               <l n="66">Another monument shall here be rais’d ;</l>
               <l n="67">Three several pillars, each a rough hewn stone,</l>
               <l n="68">And planted where thy hoofs the turf have
                                        graz’d.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18" type="stanza">
               <l n="69">And in the summer-time when days are long,</l>
               <l n="70">I will come hither with my paramour,</l>
               <l n="71">And with the dancers, and the minstrel’s
                                        song,</l>
               <l n="72">We will make merry in that pleasant bower.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="6" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="19" type="stanza">
               <l n="73">Till the foundations of the mountains fail</l>
               <l n="74">My mansion with its arbour shall endure,</l>
               <l n="75">—The joy of them who till the fields of
                                        Swale,</l>
               <l n="76">And them who dwell among the woods of Ure.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20" type="stanza">
               <l n="77">Then home he went, and left the Hart, stone-dead,</l>
               <l n="78">With breathless nostrils stretch’d above the
                                        spring.</l>
               <l n="79">And soon the Knight perform’d what he had
                                        said,</l>
               <l n="80">The fame whereof through many a land did ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21" type="stanza">
               <l n="81">Ere thrice the moon into her port had
                                        steer’d,</l>
               <l n="82">A cup of stone receiv’d the living well ;</l>
               <l n="83">Three pillars of rude stone Sir Walter
                                        rear’d,</l>
               <l n="84">And built a house of pleasure in the dell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22" type="stanza">
               <l n="85">And near the fountain, flowers of stature tall</l>
               <l n="86">With trailing plants and trees were
                                        intertwin’d,</l>
               <l n="87">Which soon composed a little sylvan hall,</l>
               <l n="88">A leafy shelter from the sun and wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="7" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="23" type="stanza">
               <l n="89">And thither, when the summer days were long,</l>
               <l n="90">Sir Walter journey’d with his paramour ;</l>
               <l n="91">And with the dancers and the minstrel’s song</l>
               <l n="92">Made merriment within that pleasant bower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24" type="stanza">
               <l n="93">The Knight, Sir Walter, died in course of time,</l>
               <l n="94">And his bones lie in his paternal vale.—</l>
               <l n="95">But there is matter for a second rhyme,</l>
               <l n="96">And I to this would add another tale.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <pb/>
         <milestone n="8" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <div>
            <head n="2" type="part">
               <emph>
                  <lb/>PART SECOND. </emph>
               <lb/>
            </head>
            <lg n="25" type="stanza">
               <l n="97">The moving accident is not my trade.</l>
               <l n="98">To curl the blood I have no ready arts ;</l>
               <l n="99">’Tis my delight, alone in summer shade,</l>
               <l n="100">To pipe a simple song to thinking hearts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26" type="stanza">
               <l n="101">As I from Hawes to Richmond did repair,</l>
               <l n="102">It chanc’d that I saw standing in a dell</l>
               <l n="103">Three aspins at three corners of a square,</l>
               <l n="104">And one, not four yards distant, near a well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26" type="stanza">
               <l n="105">What this imported I could ill divine,</l>
               <l n="106">And, pulling now the rein my horse to stop,</l>
               <l n="107">I saw three pillars standing in a line,</l>
               <l n="108">The last stone pillar on a dark hill-top.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="9" unit="verseParagraph"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="27" type="stanza">
               <l n="109">The trees were grey, with neither arms nor head ;</l>
               <l n="110">Half-wasted the square mound of tawny green ;</l>
               <l n="111">So that you just might say, as then I said,</l>
               <l n="112">“Here in old time the hand of man has
                                        been.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28" type="stanza">
               <l n="113">I look’d upon the hills both far and near ;</l>
               <l n="114">More doleful place did never eye survey ;</l>
               <l n="115">It seem’d as if the spring-time came not
                                        here,</l>
               <l n="116">And Nature here were willing to decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29" type="stanza">
               <l n="117">I stood in various thoughts and fancies lost,</l>
               <l n="118">When one who was in Shepherd’s garb
                                        attir’d,</l>
               <l n="119">Came up the hollow. Him did I accost,</l>
               <l n="120">And what this place might be I then
                                        inquir’d.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30" type="stanza">
               <l n="121">The Shepherd stopp’d, and that same story
                                        told</l>
               <l n="122">Which in my former rhyme I have rehears’d.</l>
               <l n="123">“A jolly place,” said he, “ in times
                                        of old,</l>
               <l n="124">But something ails it now ; the spot is
                                        curs’d.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="10" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="31" type="stanza">
               <l n="125">You see these lifeless stumps of aspin wood,</l>
               <l n="126">Some say that they are beeches, others elms,</l>
               <l n="127">These were the Bower ; and here a Mansion stood,</l>
               <l n="128">The finest palace of a hundred realms.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32" type="stanza">
               <l n="129">The arbour does its own condition tell,</l>
               <l n="130">You see the stones, the fountain, and the stream,</l>
               <l n="131">But as to the great Lodge, you might as well</l>
               <l n="132">Hunt half a day for a forgotten dream.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33" type="stanza">
               <l n="133">There’s neither dog nor heifer, horse nor
                                        sheep,</l>
               <l n="134">Will wet his lips within that cup of stone ;</l>
               <l n="135">And, oftentimes, when all are fast asleep,</l>
               <l n="136">This water doth send forth a dolorous groan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34" type="stanza">
               <l n="137">Some say that here a murder has been done,</l>
               <l n="138">And blood cries out for blood : but, for my part,</l>
               <l n="139">I’ve guess’d, when I’ve been sitting
                                        in the sun,</l>
               <l n="140">That it was all for that unhappy Hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="11" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="35" type="stanza">
               <l n="141">What thoughts must through the creature’s brain
                                        have pass’d !</l>
               <l n="142">To this place from the stone upon the steep</l>
               <l n="143">Are but three bounds, and look, Sir, at this last!</l>
               <l n="144">O Master ! it has been a cruel leap.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36" type="stanza">
               <l n="145">For thirteen hours he ran a desperate race ;</l>
               <l n="146">And in my simple mind we cannot tell</l>
               <l n="147">What cause the Hart might have to love this place,</l>
               <l n="148">And come and make his death-bed near the well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37" type="stanza">
               <l n="149">Here on the grass perhaps asleep he sank,</l>
               <l n="150">Lull’d by the fountain in the summer-tide ;</l>
               <l n="151">This water was perhaps the first he drank</l>
               <l n="152">When he had wander’d from his mother’s
                                        side.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38" type="stanza">
               <l n="153">In April here beneath the scented thorn</l>
               <l n="154">He heard the birds their morning carols sing,</l>
               <l n="155">And he, perhaps, for aught we know, was born</l>
               <l n="156">Not half a furlong from that self-same spring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="12" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="39" type="stanza">
               <l n="157">But now here’s neither grass nor pleasant
                                        shade;</l>
               <l n="158">The sun on drearier hollow never shone :</l>
               <l n="159">So will it be, as I have often said,</l>
               <l n="160">Till trees, and stones, and fountain all are
                                        gone.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40" type="stanza">
               <l n="161">“Grey-headed Shepherd, thou hast spoken well
                                        ;</l>
               <l n="162">Small difference lies between thy creed and mine ;</l>
               <l n="163">This beast not unobserv’d by Nature fell,</l>
               <l n="164">His death was mourn’d by sympathy divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41" type="stanza">
               <l n="165">The Being, that is in the clouds and air,</l>
               <l n="166">That is in the green leaves among the groves,</l>
               <l n="167">Maintains a deep and reverential care</l>
               <l n="168">For them the quiet creatures whom he loves.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42" type="stanza">
               <l n="169">The Pleasure-house is dust :—behind, before,</l>
               <l n="170">This is no common waste, no common gloom ;</l>
               <l n="171">But Nature, in due course of time, once more</l>
               <l n="172">Shall here put on her beauty and her bloom.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="13" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lg n="43" type="stanza">
               <l n="173">She leaves these objects to a slow decay</l>
               <l n="174">That what we are, and have been, may be known ;</l>
               <l n="175">But, at the coming of the milder day,</l>
               <l n="176">These monuments shall all be overgrown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44" type="stanza">
               <l n="177">One lesson, Shepherd, let us two divide,</l>
               <l n="178">Taught both by what she shews, and what conceals,</l>
               <l n="179">Never to blend our pleasure or our pride</l>
               <l n="180">With sorrow of the meanest thing that feels.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
