<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="paratext">
            <head rend="bold">Appendix 2:</head>
            <head rend="bold">Southey’s Challenge to Brougham</head>
            <p>We here reproduce for the first time Southey’s light-hearted – but
               unsent – 1818 response to an anticipated challenge to a duel from Henry Brougham.
               Southey suggests that such a challenge would be provoked by the appearance of his own
               ‘Tender Epistle’, which had been written in reaction to Brougham’s reported criticism
               of Southey during the Westmorland election of 1818. In fact, the ‘Tender Epistle’ was
               not completed and only part of it was ever published as an Appendix (without
               mentioning Brougham’s name) to the second edition of Southey’s <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>
               (London, 1821), pp. 45–53. </p>
            <lb/>
            <div type="letter">
               <head rend="bold"> Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="BroughamHenryPeter">Henry Peter
                     Brougham, Baron Brougham and Vaux</ref>, <date when="1818-07">[c. July
                     1818]</date>
                  <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: None, but a small
                     embossed stamp in the upper right corner of 1r, positioned vertically. A crown
                     in the centre. SUPERFINE / BATH POST<lb/> MS: Department of Rare Books, Special
                     Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester,
                     Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AMS; 2p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head>
               <p rend="center"> Answer to an expected Challenge.</p>
               <p rend="indent0">Sir </p>
               <p rend="indent1">I have the honour of acknowledging the receipt of your letter,
                  &amp; do myself the pleasure of replying to it without delay.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">In affairs of this kind, the parties ought to meet upon equal
                  terms. But to establish such an equality between you &amp; me, there are three
                  things which must be previously done; &amp; then a fourth also becomes necessary,
                  before I can meet you in the field.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">First, you must marry &amp; have four children. Please to be
                  particular in having them all girls.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"
                     >Southey’s only children alive at this time were <ref type="m"
                        target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m"
                        target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m"
                        target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m"
                        target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">Secondly you <del>can</del> must prove that the greater part of the
                  provision which you make for them depends upon your life: &amp; you must be under
                  a bond of 4000£ not to be hanged, not to commit suicide, &amp; not to be killed in
                  a duel, which are the conditions upon which I have effected an insurance on my own
                  life, for the benefit of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my
                     wife</ref> &amp; children.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                     life was insured for £4000 – he had invested his salary as Poet Laureate in
                     increasing the coverage to this sum.</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">Thirdly, I must tell three direct falsehoods concerning you, upon
                  the hustings, or in some other not less public assembly.<note n="3" place="foot"
                     resp="editors">A reference to the newspaper reports of what Brougham and said
                     about Southey from the hustings at Appleby on 30 June 1818.</note> And I shall
                  never be able to do this, nor to meet you afterwards in the manner you propose,
                  unless you can perform the fourth thing, which is, ––</p>
               <p rend="indent1">That you must convert me from the Christian religion.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">Till all this be accomplished, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brougham, our
                  disputes must be carried on without the use of any more iron than is necessary for
                  blackening our ink &amp; mending our pens, – or of any more lead than enters into
                  the composition of the Edinburgh Review<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"
                        ><title>Edinburgh Review</title> (1802–1929), the main Whig quarterly
                     journal, to which Brougham was a contributor.</note>
               </p>
               <closer><salute rend="indent1">I have the honour to subscribe myself</salute>
                  <salute rend="indent2">Sir,</salute>
                  <salute rend="indent1">Yours with all proper consideration</salute>
                  <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
