<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1802: Advertisement [essay]</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LBP1-campbell_ADVERT</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="ADVERT">
                  <title>[ADVERT]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LBP1-campbell">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LBP1-campbell.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <date>1802</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page"/>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">0</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
         <p>AT the same time that the Editor begs leave to offer the <lb/>following
                              as the cause of the little delay that has taken <lb/>place in the
                              Publication of these Poems, he begs also re-<lb/>spectfully to present
                              his Thanks to those who have been pleased <lb/>to favour them with
                              their encouragement by Subscription.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>So rapid appears to have been the sale of these Poems in <lb/>London
                              after the Publication of the S<hi>econd</hi> V<hi>olume</hi> the
                              <lb/>last summer, that another Edition has been already since
                              <lb/>published. This, containing the following lengthy
                                   P<hi>reface</hi>, <lb/>the beautiful O<hi>de to</hi>
                                   L<hi>ove</hi>, and some additional explana-<lb/>tory
                                   N<hi>otes</hi>, more than the former Edition, did not reach
                              <lb/>this Country till after the present one had been put to Press,
                              <lb/>and the First Volume nearly finished. Some little delay, has
                              <lb/>arisen from this circumstance, but, at the same time, it has
                              <lb/>enabled the Editor to give the Work compleat, which
                              other-<lb/>wise would not have been the case ; and though attended
                              with <lb/>considerable more expence than he calculated upon when he
                              <lb/>put it to press, it will be delivered to the Subscribers at the
                              <lb/>Price mentioned in his Proposals. The only difference that
                              <lb/>now exists between this and the last London Edition is, that
                              <lb/>the Poem entitled the C<hi>onvict</hi> is retained in this
                              Edition, <lb/>but omitted in that, and that the Arrangement of the
                              Poems <lb/>in the <emph>First Volume</emph> somewhat differs. The
                              Reader, however, <lb/>by turning to them as they follow in the
                              preceding Table of <lb/>Contents, will have them as they are arranged
                              in the last <lb/>London Edition. </p>
         <lb/>
         <signed>
            <emph> JAMES HUMPHREYS.</emph>
            <lb/>P<hi>hiladelphia</hi>,
                                   <lb/>
            <emph>January</emph>, 1802 </signed>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
