<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1800: Written in Germany</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB00-2S_GERMANY</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="GERMANY">
                  <title>[GERMANY]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB00-2S">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB00-2S.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1800</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">144 to 146</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="144"/>
         <milestone n="144" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <head>
            <emph>Written in GERMANY, <lb/>
               <lb/>On one of the coldest days of the
                                   Century. </emph>
         </head>
         <note>
            <emph>I must apprize the Reader that the stoves in North Germany
                                   <lb/>generally have the impression of a galloping Horse upon
                                   <lb/>them, this being part of the Brunswick Arms. </emph>
         </note>
         <lg n="1" type="stanza">
            <l n="1">A fig for your languages, German and Norse,</l>
            <l n="2">Let me have the song of the Kettle,</l>
            <l n="3">And the tongs and the poker, instead of that horse</l>
            <l n="4">That gallops away with such fury and force</l>
            <l n="5">On this dreary dull plate of black metal.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="2" type="stanza">
            <l n="6">Our earth is no doubt made of excellent stuff,</l>
            <l n="7">But her pulses beat slower and slower,</l>
            <l n="8">The weather in Forty was cutting and rough,</l>
            <l n="9">And then, as Heaven knows, the glass stood low enough,</l>
            <l n="10">And <emph>now</emph> it is four degrees lower.</l>
         </lg>
         <pb n="145"/>
         <milestone n="145" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg n="3" type="stanza">
            <l n="11">Here’s a Fly, a disconsolate creature perhaps,</l>
            <l n="12">A child of the field, or the grove,</l>
            <l n="13">And sorrow for him! this dull treacherous heat</l>
            <l n="14">Has seduc’d the poor fool from his winter retreat,</l>
            <l n="15">And he creeps to the edge of my stove.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="4" type="stanza">
            <l n="16">Alas! how he fumbles about the domains</l>
            <l n="17">Which this comfortless oven environ,</l>
            <l n="18">He cannot find out in what track he must crawl,</l>
            <l n="19">Now back to the tiles, and now back to the wall,</l>
            <l n="20">And now on the brink of the iron.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="5" type="stanza">
            <l n="21">Stock-still there he stands like a traveller
                                   bemaz’d,</l>
            <l n="22">The best of his skill he has tried;</l>
            <l n="23">His feelers methinks I can see him put forth</l>
            <l n="24">To the East and the West, and the South and the North,</l>
            <l n="25">But he finds neither guide-post nor guide.</l>
         </lg>
         <pb n="146"/>
         <milestone n="146" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg n="6" type="stanza">
            <l n="26">See! his spindles sink under him, foot, leg and thigh,</l>
            <l n="27">His eyesight and hearing are lost,</l>
            <l n="28">Between life and death his blood freezes and thaws,</l>
            <l n="29">And his two pretty pinions of blue dusky gauze</l>
            <l n="30">Are glued to his sides by the frost.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="7" type="stanza">
            <l n="31">No Brother, no Friend has he near him, while I</l>
            <l n="32">Can draw warmth from the cheek of my Love,</l>
            <l n="33">As blest and as glad in this desolate gloom,</l>
            <l n="34">As if green summer grass were the floor of my room,</l>
            <l n="35">And woodbines were hanging above.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="8" type="stanza">
            <l n="36">Yet, God is my witness, thou small helpless Thing,</l>
            <l n="37">Thy life I would gladly sustain</l>
            <l n="38">Till summer comes up from the South, and with crowds</l>
            <l n="39">Of thy brethren a march thou should’st sound through
                                   the clouds,</l>
            <l n="40">And back to the forests again.</l>
         </lg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
