<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1805: Appendix [essay]</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB05-2_APPENDIX</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="APPENDIX">
                  <title>[APPENDIX]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB05-2">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB05-2.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1805</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">237 to 247</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">11</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="237"/>
         <head>APPENDIX.<lb/>
            <lb/>See Preface, page xliii.—“ by what is
                              usually <lb/>called Poetic Diction.”</head>
         <p>As perhaps I have no right to expect from a Reader <lb/>of an
                              Introduction to a volume of Poems that at-<lb/>tentive perusal without
                              which it is impossible, <lb/>imperfectly as I have been compelled to
                              express <lb/>my meaning, that what I have said in the Preface
                              <lb/>should throughout be fully understood, I am the <lb/>more anxious
                              to give an exact notion of the sense <lb/>in which I use the phrase
                                   <emph>poetic diction;</emph> and for <lb/>this purpose I will
                              here add a few words concern-<lb/>ing the origin of the phraseology
                              which I have <lb/>condemned under that name.——The earliest
                              <lb/>Poets of all nations generally wrote from passion <pb n="238"/>
            <milestone n="238" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>excited by real
                              events ; they wrote naturally, and <lb/>as men: feeling powerfully as
                              they did, their lan-<lb/>guage was daring, and figurative. In
                              succeeding <lb/>times, Poets, and men ambitious of the fame of
                              <lb/>Poets, perceiving the influence of such language, <lb/>and
                              desirous of producing the same effect, without <lb/>having the same
                              animating passion, set themselves <lb/>to a mechanical adoption of
                              those figures of speech, <lb/>and made use of them, sometimes with
                              propriety, <lb/>but much more frequently applied them to feelings
                              <lb/>and ideas with which they had no natural connec-<lb/>tion
                              whatsoever. A language was thus insensibly <lb/>produced, differing
                              materially from the real lan-<lb/>guage of men in <emph>any
                                   situation.</emph> The Reader or <lb/>Hearer of this distorted
                              language found himself in <lb/>a perturbed and unusual state of mind:
                              when af-<lb/>fected by the genuine language of passion he had
                              <lb/>been in a perturbed and unusual state of mind also: <lb/>in both
                              cases he was willing that his common <lb/>judgment and understanding
                              should be laid asleep, <pb n="239"/>
            <milestone n="239" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>and he had no instinctive and infallible perception
                              <lb/>of the true to make him reject the false; the one <lb/>served as
                              a passport for the other. The agitation <lb/>and confusion of mind
                              were in both cases delight-<lb/>ful, and no wonder if he confounded
                              the one with <lb/>the other, and believed them both to be produced
                              <lb/>by the same, or similar causes. Besides, the Poet <lb/>spake to
                              him in the character of a man to be looked <lb/>up to, a man of genius
                              and authority. Thus, and <lb/>from a variety of other causes, this
                              distorted lan-<lb/>guage was received with admiration; and Poets,
                              <lb/>it is probable, who had before contented them-<lb/>selves for the
                              most part with misapplying only <lb/>expressions which at first had
                              been dictated by real <lb/>passion, carried the abuse still further,
                              and intro-<lb/>duced phrases composed apparently in the spirit of
                              <lb/>the original figurative language of passion, yet al-<lb/>together
                              of their own invention, and distinguished <lb/>by various degrees of
                              wanton deviation from good <lb/>sense and nature.</p>
         <pb n="240"/>
         <milestone n="240" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <p>It is indeed true that the language of the earliest <lb/>Poets was felt
                              to differ materially from ordinary <lb/>language, because it was the
                              language of extraor-<lb/>dinary occasions; but it was really spoken by
                              men, <lb/>language which the Poet himself had uttered when <lb/>he had
                              been affected by the events which he de-<lb/>scribed, or which he had
                              heard uttered by those <lb/>around him. To this language it is
                              probable that <lb/>metre of some sort or other was early superadded.
                              <lb/>This separated the genuine language of Poetry still <lb/>further
                              from common life, so that whoever read or <lb/>heard the poems of
                              these earliest Poets felt himself <lb/>moved in a way in which he had
                              not been accus-<lb/>tomed to be moved in real life, and by causes
                              ma-<lb/>nifestly different from those which acted upon him <lb/>in
                              real life. This was the great temptation to all <lb/>the corruptions
                              which have followed: under the <lb/>protection of this feeling
                              succeeding Poets con-<lb/>structed a phraseology which had one thing,
                              it is <lb/>true, in common with the genuine language of
                                   <pb/>
            <milestone n="241" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>poetry, namely,
                              that it was not heard in ordinary <lb/>conversation; that it was
                              unusual. But the first <lb/>Poets, as I have said, spake a language
                              which, <lb/>though unusual, was still the language of men. <lb/>This
                              circumstance, however, was disregarded by <lb/>their successors; they
                              found that they could please <lb/>by easier means: they became proud
                              of a language <lb/>which they themselves had invented, and which
                              <lb/>was uttered only by themselves; and, with the <lb/>spirit of a
                              fraternity, they arrogated it to them-<lb/>selves as their own. In
                              process of time metre <lb/>became a symbol or promise of this unusual
                              lan-<lb/>guage, and whoever took upon him to write in <lb/>metre,
                              according as he possessed more or less of <lb/>true poetic genius,
                              introduced less or more of this <lb/>adulterated phraseology into his
                              compositions, and <lb/>the true and the false became so inseparably
                              inter-<lb/>woven that the taste of men was gradually per-<lb/>verted;
                              and this language was received as a natu-<lb/>ral language; and at
                              length, by the influence of <pb n="242"/>
            <milestone n="242" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>books upon men, did to a certain degree
                              really <lb/>become so. Abuses of this kind were imported <lb/>from one
                              nation to another, and with the progress <lb/>of refinement this
                              diction became daily more and <lb/>more corrupt, thrusting out of
                              sight the plain <lb/>humanities of nature by a motley masquerade of
                              <lb/>tricks, quaintnesses, hieroglyphics, and enigmas.</p>
         <p>It would be highly interesting to point out the <lb/>causes of the
                              pleasure given by this extravagant <lb/>and absurd language: but this
                              is not the place; it <lb/>depends upon a great variety of causes, but
                              upon <lb/>none perhaps more than its influence in impressing <lb/>a
                              notion of the peculiarity and exaltation of the <lb/>Poet’s
                              character, and in flattering the Reader’s <lb/>self-love by
                              bringing him nearer to a sympathy <lb/>with that character; an effect
                              which is accom-<lb/>plished by unsettling ordinary habits of thinking,
                              <lb/>and thus assisting the Reader to approach to that <lb/>perturbed
                              and dizzy state of mind in which if he <pb n="243"/>
            <milestone n="243" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>does not find himself, he imagines that he
                              is <emph>balked</emph>
            <lb/>of a peculiar enjoyment which poetry can, and <lb/>ought to
                              bestow.</p>
         <p>The sonnet which I have quoted from Gray, in <lb/>the Preface, except
                              the lines printed in Italics, <lb/>consists of little else but this
                              diction, though not <lb/>of the worst kind; and indeed, if I may be
                              per-<lb/>mitted to say so, it is far too common in the best
                              <lb/>writers, both antient and modern. Perhaps I can <lb/>in no way,
                              by positive example, more easily give <lb/>my Reader a notion of what
                              I mean by the phrase <emph>
               <lb/>poetic diction </emph>than by
                              referring him to a comparison <lb/>between the metrical paraphrases
                              which we have <lb/>of passages in the old and new Testament, and
                              <lb/>those passages as they exist in our common Trans-<lb/>lation. See
                              Pope’s “Messiah” throughout, Prior’s
                              <lb/>“Did sweeter sounds adorn my flowing tongue,”
                              <lb/>&amp;c. &amp;c. “Though I speak with the tongues of
                              <lb/>men and of angels,” &amp;c. &amp;c. See 1st Corinthians,
                                   <pb n="244"/>
            <milestone n="244" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>chapter
                              xiiith. By way of immediate example, <lb/>take the following of Dr. Johnson:<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>“Turn on the prudent Ant thy heedless eyes,</l>
                  <l>Observe her labours, Sluggard, and be wise;</l>
                  <l>No stern command, no monitory voice,</l>
                  <l>Prescribes her duties, or directs her choice;</l>
                  <l>Yet, timely provident, she hastes away</l>
                  <l>To snatch the blessings of a plenteous day;</l>
                  <l>When fruitful Summer loads the teeming plain,</l>
                  <l>She crops the harvest and she stores the grain.</l>
                  <l>How long shall sloth usurp thy useless hours,</l>
                  <l>Unnerve thy vigour, and enchain thy powers?</l>
                  <l>While artful shades thy downy couch enclose,</l>
                  <l>And soft solicitation courts repose,</l>
                  <l>Amidst the drowsy charms of dull delight,</l>
                  <l>Year chases year with unremitted flight,</l>
                  <l>Till want now following, fraudulent and slow,</l>
                  <l>Shall spring to seize thee, like an ambushed
                                             foe.”</l>
               </lg>
            </q>From this hubbub of words pass to the original.
                              <lb/>“Go to the Ant, thou Sluggard, consider her ways, <lb/>and
                              be wise: which having no guide, overseer, <lb/>or ruler, provideth her
                              meat in the summer, and <pb n="245"/>
            <milestone n="245" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>gathereth her food in the harvest. How long wilt <lb/>thou
                              sleep, O Sluggard? when wilt thou arise out <lb/>of thy sleep? Yet a
                              little sleep, a little slumber, a <lb/>little folding of the hands to
                              sleep. So shall thy <lb/>poverty come as one that travaileth, and thy
                              want <lb/>as an armed man.” Proverbs, chap. vith.</p>
         <p>One more quotation and I have done. It is from <lb/>Cowper’s
                              verses supposed to be written by Alex-<lb/>ander Selkirk:</p>
         <q>
            <lg>
               <l>“Religion! What treasure untold</l>
               <l>Resides in that heavenly word!</l>
               <l>More precious than silver and gold,</l>
               <l>Or all that this earth can afford.</l>
               <l>But the sound of the church-going bell</l>
               <l>These valleys and rocks never heard,</l>
               <l>Ne’er sighed at the sound of a knell,</l>
               <l>Or smiled when a sabbath appeared.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye winds, that have made me your sport,</l>
               <l>Convey to this desolate shore</l>
               <l>Some cordial endearing report</l>
               <l>Of a land I must visit no more.</l>
               <pb n="246"/>
               <milestone n="246" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <l>My Friends, do they now and then send</l>
               <l>A wish or a thought after me?</l>
               <l>O tell me I yet have a friend,</l>
               <l>Though a friend I am never to see.”</l>
            </lg>
         </q>
         <p>I have quoted this passage as an instance of three <lb/>different styles
                              of composition. The first four lines <lb/>are poorly expressed; some
                              Critics would call the <lb/>language prosaic; the fact is, it would be
                              bad <lb/>prose, so bad, that it is scarcely worse in metre. <lb/>The
                              epithet “church-going” applied to a bell, <lb/>and that by
                              so chaste a writer as Cowper, is an <lb/>instance of the strange
                              abuses which Poets have <lb/>introduced into their language till they
                              and their <lb/>Readers take them as matters of course, if they do
                              <lb/>not single them out expressly as objects of admira-<lb/>tion. The
                              two lines “Ne’er sigh’d at the sound,”
                              <lb/>&amp;c. are, in my opinion, an instance of the language <lb/>of
                              passion wrested from its proper use, and, from <lb/>the mere
                              circumstance of the composition being <lb/>in metre, applied upon an
                              occasion that does not <pb n="247"/>
            <milestone n="247" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>justify such violent expressions; and I should
                              con-<lb/>demn the passage, though perhaps few Readers will <lb/>agree
                              with me, as vicious poetic diction. The last <lb/>stanza is throughout
                              admirably expressed: it would <lb/>be equally good whether in prose or
                              verse, except <lb/>that the Reader has an exquisite pleasure in seeing
                              <lb/>such natural language so naturally connected with <lb/>metre. The
                              beauty of this stanza tempts me here <lb/>to add a sentiment which
                              ought to be the perva-<lb/>ding spirit of a system, detached parts of
                              which <lb/>have been imperfectly explained in the
                              Preface,—<lb/>namely, that in proportion as ideas and feelings
                              <lb/>are valuable, whether the composition be in prose <lb/>or in
                              verse, they require and exact one and the <lb/>same language.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
