<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four: 1810-1815</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-08-15</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.new.2366.1</idno><idno type="nines">rce3637.1</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-08-15">August 15, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2366.1 Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 21
						January 1814</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Four</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-08-15">August 15, 2013</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Four/HTML/letterEEd.26.2366.1.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 5. ALS; 4p.  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change n="1" when="2017-01-30" who="#DR"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Update of TEI headers to conform to new template</item></list></change><change n="8" when="2013-05-27" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="7" when="2013-04-22" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-02-01" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2012-01-15" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="4" when="2011-12-02" who="#DR"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="3" when="2010-08-15" who="#AB"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change n="2" when="2010-07-22" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change n="1" when="2010-06-27" who="#AB"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2366.1" type="letter"><head>2366.1 Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1814-01-21">21
						January 1814</date><note resp="editors" place="foot" type="headnote">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Postmarks: 7
						o’Clock/ JA 26/ 1814 N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; [1 illegible]; Too Late for/ Morng Post <lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
						MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 5. ALS; 4p. <lb/> Unpublished. </note></head><p rend="indent1">When you are in that neighbourhood will you look in at Rodds, <note n="1" resp="editors" place="foot"> Thomas Rodd
						(1763–1822; <title>DNB</title>), bookseller and poet, with a special interest in Spanish literature. </note> the dirty
					bookseller at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2. Newport Street, the top of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Martins Lane, &amp; see whether N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2207 of his catalogue is worth five shillings – it contains a Guide to Rome, Monserrat, Compostella
					&amp; all other places of pilgrimage, 1610, – the second article in the book. <note n="2" resp="editors" place="foot">
						Unidentified. </note> A pilgrims book of the road may very likely have some curious things in it. </p><p rend="indent4"> ––––</p><p rend="indent1">Your neighbour<note n="3" resp="editors" place="foot"> William Barlow (1759–1839), merchant and neighbour of
						Herbert Hill in Streatham; he commissioned Southey to write the anonymous pamphlet, <title>An Exposure of the
							Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George Barlow’s Administration of Madras. By the
							Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813). </note> has just sent me down a number of the New Quarterly, &amp; two
					numbers of the Anti-Jacobine. <note n="4" resp="editors" place="foot"> Southey’s reference to the ‘New Quarterly’ is unclear,
						but the Barlow controversy had been continued in the second edition of Marsh’s <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the
							Late Administration of Sir George Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813). Barlow had sent Southey the review of this in
						the <title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine, or, Monthly Political and Literary Censor</title>, 45 (November–December
						1813), 451–458, 555–564, 625–643; 46 (January 1814), 119–134. This article was continued in vol. 46
						(April–May 1814), 362–378, and [417]–440. </note> I see by the direction that he paid the carriage, –
					&amp; according to the constant system of imposition which is practised in these things “carriage paid” is blotted
					with a line drawn across it, &amp; I have six shillings to pay for a cargo which is only worth its weight as waste paper. I am
					heartily sorry for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B. &amp; know not what to say to him. If he could make &amp; keep a resolution never
					again to look into any book or journal which touched upon this fatal subject, he would best consult his own peace, but in his
					present state, his feelings are at the mercy of every journalist. I wish he could be persuaded that the question is one on which
					it is utterly impossible to excite any public interest. That these articles come from persons connected with the parties
					concerned, &amp; but for this sort of personal <del>xxxx</del> influence that the subject would not find its way into the reviews.
					So well am I convinced of this that I think it very likely M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Grant<note n="5" resp="editors" place="foot"><title>A Letter Signed by C. Grant, Esq. …Containing a Minute Examination and Full Vindication of the Measures Adopted
							by Sir George Barlow, During the Dissensions at the Presidency of Madras</title> (1812). The letter was written by Sir
						Charles Grant, 1st Lord Glenelg (1778–1866; <title>DNB</title>), a politician closely connected to Indian affairs. It
						was not reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> may not be able to get it reviewed in the Quarterly: –
					certain I am that if he should, it will <del>only</del> be a sacrifice <del>both</del> on the part both of the Editor &amp;
					Publisher to oblige him. Nothing can be done but to let things take their course. Sir G. is coming home; <note n="6" resp="editors" place="foot"> Sir George Barlow (1762–1847; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Madras 1808–1813. His
						career was blighted by a mutiny of local army officers in 1809. </note> – a discussion will take place in Parliament
					which the public will regard with as much indifference as they did Paulls<note n="7" resp="editors" place="foot"> James Paull
						(1770–1808), made a fortune in trade in India, became MP for Newtown, Isle of Wight 1805–1807 and conducted a
						prolonged campaign against Wellesley’s conduct as Governor-General in India. </note> struggle against <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref>. Ministers in common decency will lay the matter at rest, &amp; when
					they have thus given Sir G. a <hi rend="ital">quietus</hi>, they will think they have done for him all that he has any reason to
					expect. He is an ill used man – but <del>when things come to</del> the worst that will befall him is that he must be content
					to live like an English Gentleman of moderate fortune instead of an Indian Governor, – &amp; the family must wait for a
					peerage till George Barlow wins one for them in the field of battle, – which if he lives he is likely enough to do some five
					&amp; twenty years hence. </p><p rend="indent1">I have wrought up the virile stanzas of the Carmen into a separate Ode, which is gone to the Courier, <note n="8" resp="editors" place="foot"> Southey had been compelled to amend his first New Year’s Ode as Poet Laureate,
							<title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814), because of its disagreement with British government policy towards France; the deleted
						sections were published as an ‘Ode’ in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February 1814. </note> – or rather to
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> to be inserted by him if he thinks it not unfit for the palate of
					this mealy-mouthed generation. If it should not appear there I will transcribe it for you. As for the printed piece of P<hi rend="ital">e</hi>e<hi rend="ital">l</hi>lery, it is, from its very nature one of those things which must disappoint every
					body, &amp; there are <del>xx xxxx</del> very few persons who can be expected to take the trouble of perusing it <del>in</del> a
					second time, &amp; asking themselves whether <del>any</del> they had any reason for expecting any thing better, or whether any
					thing better could be made of the same materials. I care not how much it may be criticised, nor how much it may be abused: for I
					shall never see what is said of it, &amp; if I were {to see} I have a constitutional indifference to praise or censure,
					which it {would be} giving myself too much credit to ascribe to philosophy. The only difference which there could be between
					my own opinion &amp; that of the severest critic would be this, that he might call the verses bad, whereas I affirm that they are
					simply good-for-nothing. </p><p rend="indent1">How is Massenas<note n="9" resp="editors" place="foot"> André Masséna (1758–1817), French Marshal
						and commander of the unsuccessful invasion of Portugal in 1810–1811. </note> name accented, Massena or Massena? I want
					to know because it must be introduced in some of my Inscriptions. <note n="10" resp="editors" place="foot"> Southey’s series
						of inscriptions on the Peninsular War, planned in 1813–14. </note> I may as well fill the remainder of the <del>x</del>
					sheet by transcribing one of them, – it is for the Battle of Coruña. <note n="11" resp="editors" place="foot">
						‘At Coruna’, commemorating the Battle of Corunna in 1809. It was not published until <title>Poetical
						Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 125–126. </note> – There is a separate one for Sir J
					Moore, <note n="12" resp="editors" place="foot"> Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the British
						forces at Corunna. Southey’s ‘Epitaph’ was published in his <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London,
						1837–1838), III, pp. 127–128. </note> whose ignominy I have taken care not to remember in his epitaph. </p><lg><l rend="indent3">When from these shores the British army first</l><l rend="indent3">Boldy advanced into the heart of Spain, </l><l rend="indent3">The admiring people who beheld its march</l><l rend="indent3">Call’d it the beautiful. And surely will</l><l rend="indent3">El hermoso exercito<note n="13" resp="editors" place="foot"> El
							… exercito: written in Southey’s hand in right hand margin; it translates as ‘the beautiful army’,
							a term used by the Spanish to describe the British forces sent to Iberia in 1808–1809. </note></l><l rend="indent3">Its proud array, its perfect discipline, </l><l rend="indent3">Its goodly furniture of war compleat, </l><l rend="indent3">Its powerful horse, its men of British mould</l><l rend="indent3">All high in heart &amp; hope, all of themselves</l><l rend="indent3">Assurd, &amp; in their leaders confident, </l><l rend="indent3">Deservd the title. Few short weeks elapsed</l><l rend="indent3">Ere that disastrous army here returnd</l><l rend="indent3">In hasty &amp; precipitate retreat, </l><l rend="indent3">A fourth of all its gallant force consumd; </l><l rend="indent3">Stores, treasures &amp; artillery in the wreck</l><l rend="indent3">Left to the fierce pursuer, horse &amp; man</l><l rend="indent3">Founder’d, &amp; stiffening on the mountain snows. </l><l rend="indent3">But when the exulting enemy approachd</l><l rend="indent3">Boasting that he would drive into the sea</l><l rend="indent3">The remnant of the wretched fugitives, </l><l rend="indent3">Here, ere they reachd their ships, they turnd at bay. </l><l rend="indent3">Then was the proof of English courage seen: </l><l rend="indent3">Against a foe whose <del>strength</del> host outnumberd theirs</l><l rend="indent3">Twice-told, – a foe rejoicing in pursuit, </l><l rend="indent3">Sure of the fruit of victory, whatsoeer</l><l rend="indent3">Might be the fate of battle, here they stood</l><l rend="indent3"><del>Xx</del> And their safe embarkation, all they sought, </l><l rend="indent3">Won manfully. That mournful day revenged</l><l rend="indent3">Their <del>xxxxxxxx</del> {sufferings} &amp; redeemed their countrys name. </l><l rend="indent3">And thus Coruña which in that retreat</l><l rend="indent3">Had seen the else indelible reproach</l><l rend="indent3">Of Britain, saw the stain effaced in blood.</l></lg><p>We are all well at present, thank God, – but it is yet too soon to be certain that the very slight attack of scarlet fever
					which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> had, has not communicated itself. For my own part I growl at
					the weather, &amp; wonder that any body will live in England who can live in a <del>better</del> southern climate. We have been
					covered with snow for three weeks, &amp; the weather belongs to England, not to Cumberland, – for it is worse in Devonshire
					than it is here. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the three Peers. <note n="14" resp="editors" place="foot"> The Hills’ three eldest sons, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol">Errol</ref>, to whom Southey affectionately gave
						aristocratic titles. </note> I rejoice to hear of the goats fecundity.</p><closer><signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed><dateline><date when="1814-01-21">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21. 1814. </date></dateline></closer></div></body></text></TEI>