<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1798: The Nightingale</title>
            <author>
               <name>Samuel Taylor Coleridge</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB98-Bbl_NTNGLstc</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="NTNGLstc">
                  <title>[NTNGLstc]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24599809">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB98-Bbl">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB98-Bbl.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>[Cottle printing, London publisher not yet found]; title page reads
                                       T. N. Longman</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1798</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">63 to 69</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">7</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="63"/>
         <head>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>THE NIGHTINGALE;<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <hi>a conversational poem, written in april,<lb/>
               <lb/>1798.</hi>
            <lb/>
         </head>
         <lg n="1" type="verseparagraph" part="I">
            <l n="1">No cloud, no relique of the sunken day </l>
            <l n="2">Distinguishes the West, no long thin slip </l>
            <l n="3">Of sullen Light, no obscure trembling hues.</l>
            <l n="4">Come, we will rest on this old mossy Bridge! </l>
            <l n="5">You see the glimmer of the stream beneath, </l>
            <l n="6">But hear no murmuring: it flows silently </l>
            <l n="7">O’er its soft bed of verdure. All is still, </l>
            <l n="8">A balmy night! and tho’ the stars be dim, </l>
            <l n="9">Yet let us think upon the vernal showers </l>
            <l n="10">That gladden the green earth, and we shall find</l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="64"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="M">
            <l n="11">A pleasure in the dimness of the stars. </l>
            <l n="12">And hark! the Nightingale begins its song, </l>
            <l n="13">“Most musical, most melancholy”*<note n="*" place="foot" resp="auth">*<emph>“Most musical, most
                                             melancholy.”</emph> This passage in
                                        Milton<lb/>possesses an excellence far superior to that of
                                        mere description:<lb/>it is spoken in the character of the
                                        melancholy Man, and has <lb/>therefore a
                                             <emph>dramatic</emph> propriety. The Author makes this
                                        remark,<lb/>to rescue himself from the charge of having
                                        alluded with levity<lb/>to a line in Milton: a charge than
                                        which none could be more<lb/>painful to him, except perhaps
                                        that of having ridiculed his<lb/>Bible.</note> Bird! </l>
            <l n="14">A melancholy Bird? O idle thought! </l>
            <l n="15">In nature there is nothing melancholy. </l>
            <l n="16">—But some night-wandering Man, whose heart was
                                   pierc’d</l>
            <l n="17">With the remembrance of a grievous wrong, </l>
            <l n="18">Or slow distemper or neglected love, </l>
            <l n="19">(And so, poor Wretch! fill’d all things with himself </l>
            <l n="20">And made all gentle sounds tell back the tale </l>
            <l n="21">Of his own sorrows) he and such as he </l>
            <l n="22">First nam’d these notes a melancholy strain; </l>
            <l n="23">And many a poet echoes the conceit,</l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="65"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="M">
            <l n="24">Poet, who hath been building up the rhyme</l>
            <l n="25">When he had better far have stretch’d his limbs</l>
            <l n="26">Beside a brook in mossy forest-dell </l>
            <l n="27">By sun or moonlight, to the influxes </l>
            <l n="28">Of shapes and sounds and shifting elements</l>
            <l n="29">Surrendering his whole spirit, of his song </l>
            <l n="30">And of his fame forgetful! so his fame </l>
            <l n="31">Should share in nature’s immortality, </l>
            <l n="32">A venerable thing! and so his song </l>
            <l n="33">Should make all nature lovelier, and itself </l>
            <l n="34">Be lov’d, like nature!—But ’twill not be
                                   so;</l>
            <l n="35">And youths and maidens most poetical </l>
            <l n="36">Who lose the deep’ning twilights of the spring</l>
            <l n="37">In ball-rooms and hot theatres, they still </l>
            <l n="38">Full of meek sympathy must heave their sighs</l>
            <l n="39">O’er Philomela’s pity-pleading strains. </l>
            <l n="40">My Friend, and my Friend’s Sister! we have learnt</l>
            <l n="41">A different lore: we may not thus profane </l>
            <l n="42">Nature’s sweet voices always full of love </l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="66"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="M">
            <l n="43">And joyance! ’Tis the merry Nightingale </l>
            <l n="44">That crowds, and hurries, and precipitates </l>
            <l n="45">With fast thick warble his delicious notes, </l>
            <l n="46">As he were fearful, that an April night </l>
            <l n="47">Would be too short for him to utter forth </l>
            <l n="48">His love-chant, and disburthen his full soul</l>
            <l n="49">Of all its music! And I know a grove </l>
            <l n="50">Of large extent, hard by a castle huge </l>
            <l n="51">Which the great lord inhabits not: and so </l>
            <l n="52">This grove is wild with tangling underwood,</l>
            <l n="53">And the trim walks are broken up, and grass, </l>
            <l n="54">Thin grass and king-cups grow within the paths. </l>
            <l n="55">But never elsewhere in one place I knew </l>
            <l n="56">So many Nightingales: and far and near </l>
            <l n="57">In wood and thicket over the wide grove </l>
            <l n="58">They answer and provoke each other’s songs— </l>
            <l n="59">With skirmish and capricious passagings, </l>
            <l n="60">And murmurs musical and swift jug jug </l>
            <l n="61">And one low piping sound more sweet than all—</l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="67"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="F">
            <l n="62">Stirring the air with such an harmony, </l>
            <l n="63">That should you close your eyes, you might almost </l>
            <l n="64">Forget it was not day! On moonlight bushes, </l>
            <l n="65">Whose dewy leafits are but half disclos’d, </l>
            <l n="66">You may perchance behold them on the twigs, </l>
            <l n="67">Their bright, bright eyes, their eyes both bright and
                                   full,</l>
            <l n="68">Glistning, while many a glow-worm in the shade </l>
            <l n="69" part="I">Lights up her love-torch. </l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="2" type="verseparagraph" part="I">
            <l part="F"> A most gentle maid </l>
            <l n="70">Who dwelleth in her hospitable home </l>
            <l n="71">Hard by the Castle, and at latest eve, </l>
            <l n="72">(Even like a Lady vow’d and dedicate </l>
            <l n="73">To something more than nature in the grove) </l>
            <l n="74">Glides thro’ the pathways; she knows all their
                                   notes,</l>
            <l n="75">That gentle Maid! and oft, a moment’s space,</l>
            <l n="76">What time the moon was lost behind a cloud,</l>
            <l n="77">Hath heard a pause of silence: till the Moon </l>
            <l n="78">Emerging, hath awaken’d earth and sky </l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="68"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="F">
            <l n="79">With one sensation, and those wakeful Birds </l>
            <l n="80">Have all burst forth in choral minstrelsy, </l>
            <l n="81">As if one quick and sudden Gale had swept </l>
            <l n="82">An hundred airy harps! And she hath watch’d </l>
            <l n="83">Many a Nightingale perch giddily </l>
            <l n="84">On blosmy twig still swinging from the breeze, </l>
            <l n="85">And to that motion tune his wanton song, </l>
            <l n="86">Like tipsy Joy that reels with tossing head. </l>
         </lg>
         <lg n="3" type="verseparagraph" part="I">
            <l n="87">Farewell, O Warbler! till to-morrow eve, </l>
            <l n="88">And you, my friends! farewell, a short farewell! </l>
            <l n="89">We have been loitering long and pleasantly, </l>
            <l n="90">And now for our dear homes.—That strain again!</l>
            <l n="91">Full fain would it delay me!—My dear Babe, </l>
            <l n="92">Who, capable of no articulate sound, </l>
            <l n="93">Mars all things with his imitative lisp, </l>
            <l n="94">How he would place his hand beside his ear,</l>
            <l n="95">His little hand, the small forefinger up, </l>
            <l n="96">And bid us listen! And I deem it wise </l>
         </lg>
         <pb/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="69"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <lg part="F">
            <l n="97">To make him Nature’s playmate. He knows well </l>
            <l n="98">The evening star: and once when he awoke </l>
            <l n="99">In most distressful mood (some inward pain </l>
            <l n="100">Had made up that strange thing, an infant’s dream) </l>
            <l n="101">I hurried with him to our orchard plot, </l>
            <l n="102">And he beholds the moon, and hush’d at once </l>
            <l n="103">Suspends his sobs, and laughs most silently, </l>
            <l n="104">While his fair eyes that swam with undropt tears </l>
            <l n="105">Did glitter in the yellow moon-beam! Well—</l>
            <l n="106">It is a father’s tale. But if that Heaven </l>
            <l n="107">Should give me life, his childhood shall grow up</l>
            <l n="108">Familiar with these songs, that with the night</l>
            <l n="109">He may associate Joy! Once more farewell, </l>
            <l n="110">Sweet Nightingale! once more, my friends! farewell.</l>
         </lg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
