<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Untitled Document</title>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2025-03-15T20:19:00</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>no publication statement available</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><name/><date>2026-06-28T02:44:00</date></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><figure/><figure/><figure/><figure/><figure/><figure/><hi rend="bold"
                    >Introduction</hi></p>
            <p>by Tristanne Connolly</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">“The</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">most</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">delicious</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi
                    rend="bold">poem</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">on</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">earth”</hi></p>
            <p>“I send you the most delicious poem on earth. If you don’t know what it is all about,
                or why, at least you will find glorious similes about everything in the world, and I
                defy you to discover three bad verses in the whole stack.”<hi rend="sup">1</hi> So
                wrote Horace Walpole, that exacting monitor of fashion, to Mary and Agnes Berry in
                1789 when the first edition of <hi rend="italic">The Loves of the Plants
                </hi>appeared (see Appendix 5.6). <hi rend="italic">The Loves of the Plants
                </hi>might be most concisely described as an educational vegetable soap opera. It is
                a poetic dramatization of the Linnaean sexual system of botanical taxonomy, in the
                form of episodic romances starring personified pistils and stamens, accompanied by
                footnotes voluminous enough to constitute a parallel text in prose. But the poem is
                not structured according to the order of Linnaeus’s classes, and the verse episodes
                and notes often freely digress. The four cantos are broken up by Interludes of
                self-consciously staged dialogues on aesthetic theory between a “Bookseller” and a
                “Poet.” The text as a whole is surrounded by ample apparatus. At the front there is
                an Advertisement and a Proem, plus a Preface with an outline, verbal and pictorial,
                of Linnaean taxonomy. At the back, there are no less than three indexes, not to
                mention Additional Notes. And there is even more text beyond the text, a whole other
                half of a larger composite work. The title page announces <hi rend="italic">The
                    Botanic Garden. Part II. Containing The Loves of the Plants</hi>, which is
                confusing, since Darwin made the oddly illogical move of publishing Part II several
                years before Part I. Altogether, from a twenty-first century point of view, this may
                seem like a rather quixotic form of popular science writing. But <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Loves</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of the Plants</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>was a hit. All of the major and minor writers of the
                Romantic period</p>
            <p>read it, and its influence can be traced in their works, from William Blake’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The Book of Thel </hi>in 1789 to the blossoming of a whole
                sub-genre of botanic poetry by women in the early nineteenth century.<hi rend="sup"
                    >2</hi> Formidable men of science also read <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, such as
                Joseph Banks (the British Library’s copy of the 1789 edition belonged to him) and
                Erasmus Darwin’s friends in the Lunar Society of industrialists, inventors and
                thinkers, including Josiah Wedgwood, James Watt, and Richard Lovell Edgeworth (who
                read it to his family, including Maria). Darwinian poetry became a thing, and <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP </hi>was its first published manifestation, in many ways its
                epitome, and the easiest to characterize and satirize. <hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>is a good place for readers to start with Darwin’s philosophical verse. Indeed,
                it is where his original audience started, and it remained the only substantial
                published example of Darwin’s poetry for several years and decided his public
                literary character.</p>
            <p>But by 1809 Byron could quip in <hi rend="italic">English Bards and Scotch
                    Reviewers</hi>, “The neglect of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Garden</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>is some proof of returning taste” (see
                Appendix 5.19).<hi rend="sup">3</hi> And in 1818, Hazlitt could more seriously but
                no less dismissively confirm, “I have myself out-lived one generation of favourite
                poets, the Darwins, the Hayleys, the Sewards. Who reads them now?”<hi rend="sup"
                    >4</hi> Through the nineteenth century, Erasmus Darwin continued (to paraphrase
                Oscar Wilde) to be talked about as not being talked about. In 1879, Darwin’s
                grandson Charles wrote, “I have myself met with old men who spoke with a degree of
                enthusiasm about his poetry, quite incomprehensible at the present day […]
                Notwithstanding the former high estimation of his poetry by men of all kinds in
                England no one of the present generation reads, it appears, a single word of
                it.”What happened? The standard explanation is the one adopted by Charles: “the
                downfall of his fame” is the result of Darwin’s verses being “quizzed” in parodies,
                most famously <hi rend="italic">The Loves of the Triangles </hi>in <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Anti-Jacobin; or, Weekly Examiner </hi>(1798; see Appendix 5.10).</p>
            <p>Furthermore, Charles explains, “No doubt public taste was at this time changing, and
                becoming more simple and natural. It was generally acknowledged, under the guidance
                of Wordsworth and Coleridge, that poetry was chiefly concerned with the feelings and
                deeper workings of the mind; whereas, Darwin maintained that poetry ought chiefly to
                confine itself to the word-painting of visible objects.”<hi rend="sup">5</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">6</hi> Now that the simple naturalness of Romanticism, and the
                guidance of Wordsworth and Coleridge, have been thoroughly questioned and
                complicated, it is no longer possible to take for granted this basic sketch of
                Erasmus Darwin as a quaint outdated curiosity.</p>
            <p>The idea that Darwinian poetry was taken down by witty mockery can mask some of the
                heavier motivations for parody (though the title of the government-supported <hi
                    rend="italic">Anti-Jacobin </hi>makes them clear enough). The
                counter-revolutionary reaction that developed over the course of the 1790s had
                repercussions not only including surveillance and censorship, but also what
                Katherine Binhammer has named the decade’s “sex panic”.<hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                Responses to the French Revolution represented political threats as sexual, and
                sexual threats as political, feeding “the ideological need to police and control the
                sexual practices of women.”<hi rend="sup">8</hi> And more broadly, Binhammer finds
                in the 1790s a “crystallization” of the cultural elements involved in the longer
                “transition from a pre-Enlightenment conception of sexuality to a bourgeois
                Victorian sexuality.”<hi rend="sup">9</hi> An additional factor that would intensify
                with the conservative backlash was the association of radicalism and science with
                atheism, a charge Charles defends his grandfather against, but still admits that
                though he “was certainly a theist in the ordinary acceptation of the term, he
                disbelieved in any revelation.”<hi rend="sup">10</hi> In a manuscript passage not
                included in the published biography, Charles asserts that after his death Erasmus
                Darwin was “grossly and often calumniated” because “he was unorthodox.”Richard
                Lovell Edgeworth’s prediction “that any clouds which have obscured Darwin’s genius
                will pass away, and that it will shine out again” has gradually come true over the
                past half century, though on a smaller scale than the widespread “admiration of
                posterity” (see Appendix 5.21).<hi rend="sup">11</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">12</hi> The revision of the canon, and the parallel rise of sexuality
                and science as preoccupations in Romanticism studies, have brought Erasmus Darwin
                back into the light. Adam Komisaruk and Allison Dushane produced the first critical
                edition of <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden </hi>in 2017, a landmark achievement
                in furthering the recognition of Darwin in his literary, historical, and especially
                scientific context.<hi rend="sup">13</hi> Martin Priestman wrote in 2013 that “the
                traditional knee-jerk sarcasms at his expense [that] used to be thought mandatory”
                have decreased and “the old perception of him as a figure of fun has now been
                largely swept away” by studies that have given him “a much more respectable place on
                the cultural map.”<hi rend="sup">14</hi> And in 2010 Julia List had questioned the
                “portrayal of Darwin’s reception in the 1790s as a pattern of liberal acceptance
                followed by conservative rejection” and argues that “the evidence suggests” a “more
                consistently positive response.”<hi rend="sup">15</hi> In light of these
                reconsiderations, the narrative of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>as highly fashionable
                then highly unfashionable becomes revealing in itself about the ways the cultural
                changes of the 1790s have been understood, both contemporaneously and
                retrospectively. The parodies, and other responses to Darwin’s poetry over the
                decades following its initial popularity, are an index of the way writers of that
                time formulated, and tried to influence as well as reflect, the transformations of
                the Romantic period as they happened. <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>functions as a
                touchstone, or a baseline measuring an earlier state, against which changing
                cultural attitudes and aesthetic tastes could be defined, through opposition but
                also through selective praise.</p>
            <p>Jerome McGann has taken <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>as an example of a kind of poetry
                we have forgotten how to read: “This happened because the twentieth-century critique
                of the sentimental tradition</p>
            <p>[…] not only disappeared a large corpus of vital and important poetry, it obscured
                the conventions that supported such poetry.”<hi rend="sup">16</hi> “The poem is not
                an organic structure,” as Romantic ideology would teach us to expect.<hi rend="sup"
                    >17</hi> It is not only the several cantos of rhyming couplets and the visuality
                of the verse that make it seem alien, but a disconnectedness of form and a strange
                pervasiveness of sensation which yet seems stilted in comparison to “the spontaneous
                overflow of powerful feelings.”<hi rend="sup">18</hi> But McGann finds in this
                devalued poetic tradition a radical “(con)fusion” of mind and body, and of the
                analytical and affective. In <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>specifically, the prose
                “ground[s] the verse with analysis and empirical observation” while “the verse
                charges the scientific project with feeling and sensation.”<hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>comes from a scientific environment that has also been “disappeared,” where
                materialism and vitalism allowed natural philosophers to entertain the possibility
                of the soul’s materiality, which has the potential to radically reconfigure the
                relationship between mind and body, thought and feeling. It also involved the
                possibility that consciousness, agency, and desire might be shared, in lesser
                degrees, by the non-human world. And <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>also tentatively
                but unmistakably puts forward theories of evolution that would become more
                pronounced in Darwin’s later works (see, for example, <hi rend="italic">LOTP
                    </hi>I:65n).<hi rend="sup">19</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">20</hi> Such trains of thought obviously had religious implications as
                well. Edward Reed argues that Erasmus Darwin is a major representative of these
                directions of thought which went underground when the territory of metaphysics was
                fearfully ceded by science to religion in the nineteenth century.<hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>is a work that represents science before it was called science: it
                went under the names of natural history and natural philosophy, while the word
                “science” was more broadly defined as “knowledge.” Priestman points out that
                literature, also, had not yet “cut itself off from other writing” or opposed itself
                to science; it “still covered the whole field of ‘letters’, as in that</p>
            <p>widespread eighteenth-century sharing of polymathic ideas known as ‘the republic of
                    letters.’”<hi rend="sup">21</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">22</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>provides a detailed snapshot of that international
                circulation of knowledge, showing Darwin, like many other citizens of the “republic
                of letters,” not merely receiving information but actively participating in
                dialogue, testing and contesting others’ conclusions, and contributing to the
                advancement of knowledge. <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>also shows the kind of
                information that was circulated. It is a compendium of current learning, and
                witnesses Darwin’s wide reading as well as his broad knowledge and curiosity. It
                attests too that involvement in science or literature was not professionally based
                or restricted by specialization. Darwin was a physician by profession, but his
                writing, information, and authority go far beyond the practice of medicine.</p>
            <p>It is because <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>is a work so much of its time, so much a
                culmination of earlier currents, that it chimed so resonantly with readers when it
                appeared, and for the same reason soon became an emblem of retro styles and
                attitudes, a target of ridicule for counter-revolutionary writers, and an other
                against which cultural changes could be defined. The points for which <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>was praised and blamed often
                indicate what makes it fascinating now, as a voice from an alternative tradition
                illuminating current concerns: interdisciplinarity and the relationship between the
                arts and the sciences; the relationship between humans and nature; what it means to
                try to think the non-human, scientifically and imaginatively; gender roles, sexual
                diversity, and the status of gender and sexuality as natural or artificial; the
                relative value of the natural and the artificial; popular access to and
                participation in science; women’s science education; the relationship of art and
                science to revolution and empire; the possibilities of hybrid texts; aesthetic
                criteria as culturally determined and changing, in revealing ways, over time.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Genre</hi></p>
            <p>Darwin’s poetry is part of a tradition that goes back to classical literature and
                enjoyed a rich flowering in the eighteenth century. Wide-ranging, various, and
                difficult to define, it is nonetheless a recognizable genre that could be labeled
                the didactic poem, the philosophical poem, or even more broadly, the long poem. It
                has its two main classical precursors in Virgil’s <hi rend="italic">Georgics</hi>,
                which gives practical instructions and advice on agricultural matters, and
                Lucretius’s <hi rend="italic">De rerum natura</hi>, which explains Epicurean
                philosophy and the workings of the universe.</p>
            <p>Major examples of the eighteenth-century “English Georgic” include John Philips’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Cyder</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1708), Christopher Smart’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Hop</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Garden</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1752),
                John Dyer’s <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Fleece</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1757), and James Grainger’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The Sugar-Cane </hi>(1764). Like <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>,
                Dyer’s poem, on the care of sheep and the wool trade, includes a poetic description
                of a spinning machine (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>II:85–104; Dyer III:291–302).<hi
                    rend="sup">23</hi> Rudolf Beck considers Dyer’s poem an example of a subgenre,
                “industrial georgic,” which tries to modify the ancient agricultural form to the
                demands of the early Industrial Revolution.<hi rend="sup">24</hi> This subgenre also
                includes Richard Jago’s <hi rend="italic">Edge-Hill</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1767), relevant to Darwin considering its Midlands location and praise of
                Birmingham’s manufactures, and also in its venturing into other branches of science
                such as geology and optics. James Venable Logan, in an overview of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Botanic Garden</hi>’s antecedents, argues that the closest resemblance is
                to Grainger’s <hi rend="italic">The Sugar-Cane</hi>, especially for its extensive
                use of footnotes, though it is not known whether Darwin read Grainger.<hi rend="sup"
                    >25</hi> A very important difference, though, is that Grainger seeks to
                contribute to knowledge of the world’s vegetation from his position as a West Indian
                plantation manager; his practical advice covers the purchase and use of slaves.<hi
                    rend="sup">26</hi> While Grainger’s poem reflects and supports his apologist
                stance on slavery, Darwin’s poem emphatically voices the abolitionist cause in an
                explicit call to British leaders (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>III:433–62; see also
                    <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden, Part I, The Economy of Vegetation
                </hi>(1791) II:311–16). Darwin definitely read William</p>
            <p>Mason’s <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >English</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Garden</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>(1772–1781), an English Georgic poem mentioned in the first
                Interlude of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>(p. 51). It turns the traditional
                agricultural focus of the genre toward the fashionable and aesthetic topic of
                landscape gardening.</p>
            <p>Lucretius’s poem never constituted a mainstream tradition in Christian Europe because
                of its challenges to religion, denial of life after death, insistence that creation
                came about because of random chance, explicitness about sex, and praise of the
                erotic power of Venus as the source of all life. It was translated into English only
                rarely and incompletely until Thomas Creech published his full, annotated
                translation, <hi rend="italic">Of The Nature of Things </hi>in 1682. The Lucretian
                poem did not form as definite a genre as the Georgic. Rather, the example of
                Lucretius provided a basis for many eighteenth-century poets to combine science or
                philosophy with poetry in diverse ways, including hybridizing Lucretian and Georgic
                traditions. Some poets modeled works on Lucretius purposely to oppose him and defend
                religion, such as Richard Blackmore in his poem <hi rend="italic">Creation
                </hi>(1712). The influence of Lucretius can be seen in attempts to explain all of
                creation and take on the universe in a didactic poem, as in Capel Lofft’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Eudosia: or, a Poem on the Universe </hi>(1781) and Henry Brooke’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Universal Beauty </hi>(1735). Though <hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>liberally strays from its ostensible botanical focus with a digressiveness
                typical of philosophical poetry, it is not as ambitiously cosmic in scope as Part I
                of <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden, The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, or Darwin’s
                other four-canto philosophical poem, <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Nature
                </hi>(1803). A reviewer of Anna Seward’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life of
                    Dr. Darwin </hi>(1804) gets close to accusing Darwin of plagiarizing <hi
                    rend="italic">Universal Beauty</hi>, except that the “obscurity and neglect” of
                the poem made the reviewer, who did not know the name of its author, believe it
                unlikely that Darwin would have read it.Blackmore, like Darwin, is among the
                significant number of writers of eighteenth-century philosophical or didactic poems
                who were physicians. Some, unlike Blackmore or Darwin, made</p>
            <p>medicine the main focus of their verse. For instance, Hugh Downman’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Infancy </hi>(1774–1776) instructs on the healthy care of babies
                and small children, including such subjects as breastfeeding and smallpox
                inoculation. John Armstrong’s <hi rend="italic">The Art of Preserving Health
                </hi>(1744) gives, in each of its four books, advice on “Air,” “Diet,” “Exercise,”
                and “The Passions” (four of the six “non-naturals” or non-innate things affecting
                health in Galenic medicine). Armstrong also wrote a controversially explicit sex
                manual in verse, <hi rend="italic">The Oeconomy of Love </hi>(1736), which, like the
                more respectable <hi rend="italic">Art of Preserving Health</hi>, was often
                reprinted. Grainger made a point in his “West-India georgic” to include “many
                indigenous remedies [...] of such amazing efficacy” which “deserve to be universally
                known”, in which recommendations, “I beg leave to be understood as a physician, and
                not as a poet” (p. vii). Mark Akenside infused medical and scientific knowledge into
                his philosophical poem, <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures of the Imagination
                </hi>(1744), especially the embryology on which he wrote his thesis. As Darwin
                mentions in <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Interlude II (p. 95), Akenside makes
                specific reference to Lucretius in a rewriting of his famous scene of viewing a
                shipwreck from afar, safely on land (Lucretius II:1–5; Akenside II:693–711,
                II:157n.).</p>
            <p>Two of the most widely-read eighteenth-century philosophical poems, which also, like
                Darwin’s verse, later became remarkably unread, are James Thomson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The Seasons </hi>(1726–1730) and Edward Young’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Night-Thoughts </hi>(short for its impressive full title, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Complaint; or, Night-Thoughts on Life, Death and Immortality</hi>) (1742–1745).
                While Thomson’s poem includes scientific and agricultural material as part of its
                rich and evocatively symbolic description of landscape and rural life, Young’s is “a
                georgic for the soul” offering spiritual advice, and is vulnerably autobiographical
                in its representation of the poet’s grief over the deaths of his wife, stepdaughter,
                and friend.<hi rend="sup">27</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">28</hi> A third long poem that passed from major to minor status is
                William Cowper’s <hi rend="italic">The Task </hi>(1785), which comes closest to the
                Georgic tradition in its third</p>
            <p>section, “The Garden,” but also partakes of genres such as mock epic, and, like
                Young, autobiography.</p>
            <p>What most sets Cowper apart from other philosophical poets is his plain language. In
                this he is the polar opposite of Darwin, whose ornate style differs also from
                Thomson’s and Young’s Miltonic inheritance. Anna Seward reports that Darwin did not
                like Cowper’s <hi rend="italic">Task </hi>very much, for its “prosaicism” and its
                “rough and slovenly style,” and also “maintained a preference of Akenside’s blank
                verse to Milton’s; declared that it was of higher polish, of more classic purity,
                and more dignified construction.” Even in his style, then, Darwin purposely chooses
                what would very soon become unfashionable. Most noticeably, the poetic form he
                chooses is the “diction-packed” and “rigorously end-stopped Popeian heroic couplet,”
                which would soon “die” from the disdain for it expressed by Cowper and by William
                    Wordsworth.<hi rend="sup">29</hi> Though the heroic couplet is such a
                characteristically eighteenth-century form, it is conspicuously absent from the
                characteristically eighteenth-century genre of the philosophical poem. Seward’s
                reviewer may be forgiven for suspecting Darwin of plagiarism considering that Brooke
                and Blackmore were of the very rare few who wrote such poems in couplets; all of the
                other examples mentioned here are in blank verse. A major exception is Alexander
                Pope, whose name is after all synonymous with the perfection of the heroic couplet,
                but the form he uses for philosophical poems such as <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man
                </hi>(1733–1734) draws on another classical model, Horace’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epistles</hi>, which tend more toward philosophical and especially ethical
                subjects, and less toward dissemination of scientific knowledge. Another poet
                mentioned by Darwin in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, William Hayley, wrote a series
                of poetical essays in heroic couplets, all on subjects in the arts and addressed to
                artists and writers, including William Mason to whom he addressed <hi rend="italic"
                    >An Essay on Epic Poetry </hi>(1781).</p>
            <p>Pope’s philosophical poems, being epistles, also have named addressees. And Lucretius
                has his</p>
            <p>Memmius and Young his Lorenzo, who are charged to learn from the poems. It is
                interesting to notice how <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>differs in its use of the
                addressee. The prose dialogue in the Interludes is between Poet and Bookseller
                (rather than philosopher and student as in Plato’s philosophical dialogues, for
                example). In the verse, the speaker of the body of each canto is the Botanic Muse,
                and the addressee is Nature itself, as the stream, wind, and leaves are exhorted to
                be quiet and insects are called to listen (I:21–38).</p>
            <p>Priestman suggests that all the “other most celebrated examples” of didactic poetry
                are in blank verse because it “giv[es] the feeling of a kindly instructor gently
                leading the reader from one idea to the next and not straying too far from the prose
                in which those ideas might normally be expressed.”<hi rend="sup">30</hi> Among the
                major differences Logan finds between Darwin and his predecessors in philosophical
                poetry is that there is simply more science in Darwin’s poems, and it is more
                detailed, accurate, and cutting-edge.<hi rend="sup">31</hi> This only makes his
                choice of couplets and ornamental language seem all the more strange. Discussing
                didactic poetry in the first Interlude of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, the “Poet”
                opines that “Science is best delivered in Prose, as its mode of reasoning is from
                stricter analogies than metaphors or similes.”<hi rend="sup">32</hi> Darwin himself
                appears to subordinate poetry to prose, as in the opening of the Advertisement to
                    <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>which states his intention to “lead” readers “from
                the looser analogies, which dress out the imagery of poetry, to the stricter ones,
                which form the ratiocination of philosophy,” and in <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Plan</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Conduct</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Female</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Education</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>where he recommends reading the notes of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>and
                considers the verses optional (see Appendix 3.2).<hi rend="sup">33</hi> Recent
                studies of Darwin, however, have found that in practice there is an essential,
                dynamic relationship between verse and notes, poetry and science, in his works.<hi
                    rend="sup">34</hi> Darwin’s choice of an extremely poetical diction and verse
                form serves what Dahlia Porter sees as his purpose in bringing poetry and prose
                together: calling attention to their difference and valuing</p>
            <p>poetry as “a science in its own right—a field of knowledge with its own style.”<hi
                    rend="sup">35</hi> For Priestman, the self-containment and speed of the
                end-stopped couplet actually make it “the perfect vehicle for moving rapidly between
                diverse fields of knowledge,”<hi rend="sup">36</hi> contributing not only to the
                multidisciplinary agility of Darwin’s poetry, but also to its aesthetic of
                multiplicitous scenes, its analogical juxtapositions, and its overwhelming
                effect.</p>
            <p>Priestman describes Darwin as having brought the didactic tradition “at once to a
                climax and an end” and observes that he was writing his last poem, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Temple of Nature </hi>(published posthumously in 1803), “just as Wordsworth
                produced the <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads </hi>Preface, with its announcement
                of the imminent divorce between the poet and the man of science.”<hi rend="sup"
                    >37</hi> The grounds for this divorce were generic as well as disciplinary. As
                Anna Barbauld puts it in the introductory essay to her 1794 edition of Mark
                Akenside’s <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures of Imagination</hi>, “Didactic, or
                preceptive Poetry, seems to include a solecism, for the end of Poetry is to please,
                and of Didactic precept the object is instruction.”<hi rend="sup">38</hi> But from
                its beginnings the didactic tradition addressed this disjunction and deliberately
                brought the two purposes together. Lucretius twice repeats the (very botanical)
                image of sweetening a cup of medicinal wormwood with honey around the rim to
                “beguile” not “betray” (“deceptaque non capiatur”) children into drinking it and
                regaining health. In just such a way, Lucretius says, he puts forward his doctrine
                touched with the sweet honey of the Muses.<hi rend="sup">39</hi> Barbauld considers
                it the “office” of the didactic poet to “throw a lustre” on those aspects of the
                topic “as are most susceptible of poetical ornament” and this “<hi rend="italic">art
                </hi>of the Poet becomes itself a source of pleasure.”<hi rend="sup">40</hi> She
                holds up as a shining example a passage from <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>: “Who does
                not admire the infinite art with which Dr. DARWIN has described the [spinning]
                machine of Sir Richard Arkwright. His verse is a piece of mechanism as complete in
                its kind as that which he describes.”<hi rend="sup">41</hi> Ironically, the very
                Romantic ideal of organic unity of form and</p>
            <p>content is applied here to “a piece of mechanism.” For Barbauld, success in didactic
                poetry seems to require overcoming didacticism itself. Counterintuitively, she
                recommends,</p>
            <p>Whoever [...] reads a Didactic Poem ought to come to it with a previous knowledge of
                his subject; and whoever writes one, ought to suppose such a knowledge in his
                readers. If he is obliged to explain technical terms, to refer continually to
                critical notes, and to follow a system step by step with the patient exactness of a
                teacher, his Poem, however laboured, will be a bad Poem.The rejection of the
                didactic has been considered synonymous with Romanticism, as David Duff observes,
                even though the major Romantics indulged often enough in “moralizing in verse.”<hi
                    rend="sup">42</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">43</hi> Darwin is at odds with this moralizing aspect that lived on
                after didacticism’s fall from fashion. He does not combine, let alone replace,
                scientific with moral instruction; Dahlia Porter finds that his verse “does not
                overtly propound an ethical system or theological position.”<hi rend="sup">44</hi>
                What he does occasionally propound is messages of liberty, such as the passages in
                    <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>on prison reform and the abolition of slavery, given
                emphatic place at the ends of cantos (<hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>II:439–72, III: 419–68). Didactic poetry incorporating radical politics,
                sexual liberation, and challenges to established religion met with adverse reactions
                in the case of Richard Payne Knight, who is sometimes paralleled with Darwin.<hi
                    rend="sup">45</hi> Knight had published his rather explicit prose work on sexual
                symbolism in religion, <hi rend="italic">An Account of the Remains of the Worship of
                    Priapus</hi>, in 1786. He later entered into, and politicized, the debates on
                the picturesque with his poem <hi rend="italic">The Landscape </hi>(1794). His
                historico-political poem <hi rend="italic">The Progress of Civil Society </hi>(1796)
                was skewered by the <hi rend="italic">Anti-Jacobin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>in
                the parody <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Progress</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Man</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1798).<hi rend="sup"
                    >46</hi> This mock didactic poem was credited to the imaginary Mr. Higgins, also
                the supposed author of <hi rend="italic">The Loves of the Triangles</hi>.<hi
                    rend="sup">47</hi> The fact that Knight (and Mr. Higgins) chose heroic verse
                supports Priestman’s point that the speed and</p>
            <p>self-containment of couplets is also advantageous for controversial content: the
                reader has “swallowed an elephant” before they know it.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Composition</hi></p>
            <p>A further reason why <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>was already retro when it came out
                in 1789 is that Darwin had been working on it since the mid-1770s. And it seems that
                Darwin was working on, or at least working towards, <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>’s
                companion poem, <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden Part I: The Economy of
                    Vegetation</hi>, as well as his prose work, <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia
                </hi>(1794–1796), over roughly the same time period.<hi rend="sup">48</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">49</hi> From its first appearance, <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>was
                presented as part of a larger whole, being labeled “The Botanic Garden Part II” even
                though it came out on its own, in three editions, before the publication of Part I,
                    <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Economy</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetation</hi>. The interim was not short: though
                dated 1791, <hi rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation </hi>was actually published
                in June 1792, just over three years after the first edition of <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>in April 1789.<hi rend="sup">50</hi> The two parts, then, have always
                been joined yet disconnected. The presence of Part I was visible in Part II from the
                start, not only in the numbering itself, but also in the Advertisement, and in
                cross-references in Part II’s notes to the not-yet-existent Part I.</p>
            <p>According to Anna Seward, the inspiration for <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>came from the real botanic garden that Darwin began to
                create “about the year 1777.”<hi rend="sup">51</hi> On her first visit to the
                garden, she wrote a poem which she says made Darwin think she should write a “great
                work” on the Linnaean system with personified plants, and he would write the notes;
                she answered that he would be better suited to fulfil the assignment himself.<hi
                    rend="sup">52</hi> Without her permission, Darwin revised and published Seward’s
                “Verses written in Dr. Darwin’s Botanical Garden near Lichfield,” and also borrowed
                and adapted it for the opening of <hi rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation
                </hi>(see Appendix 4.1).</p>
            <p>Seward dates the “commencement” of <hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden </hi>to
                    1779.<hi rend="sup">53</hi> However, going by the account of Richard Lovell
                Edgeworth, portions of it were written even earlier: “The Doctor had not at that
                time [when Seward wrote her poem] formed the scheme of the Botanic Garden; but many
                of the lines, which it contains, had been seen by his friends, several years before
                the garden, which became the theme of his poetry, was in existence” (see Appendix
                4.3).In 1781, writing to Joseph Banks, Darwin thanks him for “some remarks you made
                on a poem” which seems to have been an early version of <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP</hi>.<hi rend="sup">54</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">55</hi> Confusingly, Darwin says, “I have written several of the
                notes, and corrected some of the verse, a part of which was written by Miss Seward,
                and a part by a Mr. Sayle.”<hi rend="sup">56</hi> Either there was more
                collaboration, or plagiarism, afoot than Seward’s borrowed verses in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, or the poem’s contents changed
                between 1781 and 1789; or perhaps he was, at this early stage, concealing his
                authorship of the verse from Banks, the great man of science. Darwin remarks, “The
                history you mentioned to Mr. Boothby of the Tremella is truly curious,” and asks
                “leave to add your account of it in the note,”<hi rend="sup">57</hi> revealing that
                a draft those verses (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>I:427–466) and their accompanying
                note must have already existed in some form.</p>
            <p>A letter to Joseph Johnson dated 23 May 1784 indicates that Darwin by that time had
                enough of a manuscript of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>to show the publisher. Darwin
                refers to “the work […] which you have seen” and tells Johnson that he has “about 60
                lines more to add to it, and two or three more notes.”<hi rend="sup">58</hi> Either
                those additions took him several years, or he ended up doing more. The latter is
                quite possible since in the same letter he expects <hi rend="italic">The Economy of
                    Vegetation </hi>“will consist of but 400 lines, but […] will have 3 or 4 times
                the quantity of notes” compared to <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>. As King-Hele notes,
                it ultimately had 2448 lines.<hi rend="sup">59</hi> Darwin also tells Johnson, “I
                would not wish to part with the intire coppy-right, because that would preclude me
                from entrenching or altering,</p>
            <p>or adding to it in any future edition.”<hi rend="sup">60</hi> He also requests “<hi
                    rend="italic">general</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">or</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">particular</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">criticisms</hi>” from Johnson, which, if provided (no answer is
                extant), may have led to revisions. Soon after publication of the first edition,
                though, Darwin did sell the copyright of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>to Johnson
                for</p>
            <p>£300, according to a contract dated 20 February 1790.<hi rend="sup">61</hi> In the
                same contract, Darwin received</p>
            <p>£400 for the copyright of <hi rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>. In a
                letter to Edgeworth a couple of months later (24 April 1790), Darwin reports these
                sums and adds that he “got 100£ by the first edition” of <hi rend="italic"
                >LOTP</hi>, presumably through the equal sharing of expenses and profits he had
                initially proposed to Johnson.Darwin did in fact do most of his revision to <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP </hi>before selling the copyright: by far the majority of
                significant changes, additions, and rearrangements occur between the 1789 and 1790
                editions. In the Advertisement to <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>1790, Darwin lists
                what he considers to be the major revisions: the addition of verses and notes on
                Amaryllis (I:151–160), Orchis (III:259–326, including the episode of Eliza dying on
                the battlefield of Minden), Cannabis (IV:103–32), and Ocymum (IV:217–79). He also
                indicates that the lines on Gloriosa (I:117–38) and Tulipa (I:205–12) have been
                altered. The revision to the Gloriosa passage involved changing and lengthening the
                lines on Ninon de l’Enclos, in response to Anna Seward’s negative reaction to
                Darwin’s representation of Ninon in 1789 (see Appendix 4.1), while in the Tulipa
                passage only one couplet is rewritten and another added. The other major change
                Darwin lists is that “the description of the Saltmines in Poland”: eighteen lines of
                poetry and an accompanying note that had appeared in Canto IV of <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>1789, “is removed to the first poem on the Economy of Vegetation.” A
                portion of that note is kept in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, repurposed in the note
                on the added plant Ocymum salinum. Plus, Darwin mentions the addition of two plates
                (Amaryllis and Hedysarum).<hi rend="sup">62</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">63</hi> Other changes from 1789 to 1790 include some medium-sized
                insertions, such as</p>
            <p>a verse passage on Joseph Wright’s painting of Vesuvius (I:175–82), a response to
                criticism of the first edition in the <hi rend="italic">English Review </hi>in
                Interlude II (pp. 95–6), and the addition of several sentences to various notes.
                There was also the structural change of relocating the notes in the Supplement
                section of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>1789 to the main text or the Additional
                Notes. The rest of the changes between 1789 and 1790 are on the small scale: the
                scattered addition of couplets or sentences and some rewordings. From 1790 on,
                occasional small-scale alterations continued, though fewer in number. The most
                sizeable insertions in later editions include those to the Additional Notes (in
                1791, the “Fairy-scene” passage from <hi rend="italic">Needwood Forest</hi>, and in
                1794, the extra account of the Upas by Aejmelæus and Thunberg). Most importantly,
                Darwin composed verses and notes on two more plants: Nelumbo (Canto IV) in 1794, and
                Epidendrum (Canto I) in 1799.</p>
            <p>None of the editions of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(or indeed
                of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Botanic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Garden</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>as a whole) published in Darwin’s lifetime gave the author’s
                name. And yet, from the start, the works were not exactly anonymous. In February
                1789, sending the book to his friend Josiah Wedgwood, Darwin calls himself “the <hi
                    rend="underline">supposed</hi>, not the <hi rend="underline">avow’d</hi>
                    author.”<hi rend="sup">64</hi> Walpole, in his effusions about <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>to the Berry sisters, in the very month of its publication, names
                Darwin as the author (see Appendix 5.6). When the first volume of Darwin’s medical
                treatise <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia </hi>came out in 1794, its title page gave his
                name and indicated he was the “AUTHOR OF THE BOTANIC GARDEN,” as did his later prose
                works, <hi rend="italic">A Plan for the Conduct of Female Education in Boarding
                    Schools </hi>(1797) and <hi rend="italic">Phytologia; or the Philosophy of
                    Agriculture and Gardening </hi>(1800).</p>
            <p rend="justify">In the 1784 letter to Johnson, Darwin confides, “I would not have my
                name affix’d to this work on any account, as I think it would be injurious to me in
                my medical practise, as it has been to all other physicians who have published
                    poetry.”<hi rend="sup">65</hi> Seward says that Darwin responded with</p>
            <p>the same misgivings when she suggested he write the poem himself (see Appendix
                    4.1).<hi rend="sup">66</hi> Indeed, near the beginning of her biographical
                account, she paints a picture of Darwin bravely resisting poetry: “with the wisdom
                of Ulysses” he “bound himself to the medical mast, that he might not follow those
                delusive syrens, the muses” because he “remembered how fatal” the “gift of a highly
                poetic imagination” became to two other eighteenth-century poet physicians, Mark
                Akenside and John Armstrong.<hi rend="sup">67</hi> This appears to have been more of
                an apprehension than a fact: there is no basis for the claim that Akenside or
                Armstrong was disadvantaged in their later medical careers by publishing poetry in
                their twenties (see Appendix 4.1, editor’s note). And besides, Darwin was 57 when
                    <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>was published.</p>
            <p>Darwin had written poetry from a young age. The earliest poem we have of his was
                probably written when he was around twelve years old, to his sister:</p>
            <p>My dearest Sue Of lovely hue</p>
            <p>No sugar can be sweeter; You do as far Excel Su-gar</p>
            <p>As sugar does saltpetre.</p>
            <p>Darwin was already mixing verse with chemistry and agriculture (saltpetre, or
                potassium nitrate, is used both in gunpowder and fertilizers). But before <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP </hi>he published few poems. In 1751, his tribute verses on
                Thomas Gurney’s system of shorthand appeared anonymously in <hi rend="italic">The
                    London </hi><hi rend="italic">Magazine</hi>,<hi rend="sup">68</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">69</hi> and were reprinted in Gurney’s <hi rend="italic">Brachygraphy
                </hi>(1752), with the initials “E.D.” and the place and date of writing, “<hi
                    rend="italic">Cambridge, St. Johns. </hi>May 14, 1751.” Also in 1751, his verses
                on the death of Prince Frederick were published in a University of Cambridge</p>
            <p>collection of tributes. An elegy in tribute to his son Charles was published as a
                book in 1778, but the authorship of that work is debated.<hi rend="sup">70</hi> He
                probably collaborated on Anna Seward’s first publication, <hi rend="italic">Elegy on
                    Captain Cook </hi>(1780).<hi rend="sup">71</hi> “Address to Swilcar Oak” was
                printed in F.N.C. Mundy’s <hi rend="italic">Needwood Forest </hi>(1776), with the
                initials “E.D.” (see <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Additional Notes, editor’s note)
                and “Ode to the River Derwent” was published in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s
                    Magazine </hi>in 1785,<hi rend="sup">72</hi> credited to “<hi rend="italic">Dr.
                    D———, of Derby.</hi>” The lines from <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>describing
                Fuseli’s <hi rend="italic">The Nightmare </hi>were published in an earlier version
                in 1783, but without Darwin’s name (see <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>III:51–78 and
                editor’s note, and Appendix 1.3). In the attributions of these earlier publications
                there is a dance between remaining anonymous and leaving clues of identity; between
                being a “<hi rend="underline">supposed</hi>” and an “<hi rend="underline"
                    >avow’d</hi> author.” There is a hint of what this meant to Darwin in a 1788
                letter in which he tells his son Robert, “I shall not put my name to [<hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP</hi>], tho’ it will be known to many: but the addition of my
                name would seem as if I thought it a work of consequence.”<hi rend="sup">73</hi> It
                seems to have been important to Darwin to make light of his poetry—whether he in
                fact took it lightly or not.</p>
            <p>Another letter of Darwin’s indicates that sacrificing poetry to medicine was not only
                a matter of reputation, but also of time and concentration amid the demands of
                establishing his practice and pursuing his research. In 1775, when gifted by his
                patient Joseph Cradock with a copy of his <hi rend="italic">Village</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1774), Darwin writes back in a confessional mode: “what shall I send you in
                return for these? I who have for twenty years neglected the Muses, and cultivated
                medicine alone with all my industry!”<hi rend="sup">74</hi> This would mean he
                hadn’t composed verses since he was in university. He seems to have felt a deep,
                significant lack from having to channel his efforts of cultivation toward medicine
                and away from poetry. But the same letter reveals that, though he already had some
                articles in <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal
                    Society</hi>,<hi rend="sup">75</hi> Darwin’s apprehensions about publication
                extended to his medical writing: “Medical</p>
            <p>Dissertations I have several finished for the press, but dare not publish them, well
                knowing the reception a living writer in medicine is sure to meet with from those
                who wish to raise their own reputation on the ruin of their antagonists. Faults may
                be found or invented; or at least ridicule may cast blots on a book were it written
                with a pen from the wings of the angel Gabriel”<hi rend="sup">76</hi>—a delightful
                image, suggesting that scientific discourse could be divinely inspired, while also
                representing the vulnerability that comes with “a work of consequence”.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Elizabeth</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Pole:</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Poetry,</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi
                    rend="bold">Fertility,</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">and</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">the</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                    >Real</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Botanic</hi><hi rend="bold"
                    > </hi><hi rend="bold">Gardens</hi></p>
            <p>Darwin, however, did send Cradock the return gift of a poem: “I lately interceded
                with a Derbyshire lady to desist from lopping a grove of trees, which has occasioned
                me […] to try again the long neglected art of verse-making, which I shall inclose to
                amuse you, promising, at the same time, never to write another verse as long as I
                    live.”<hi rend="sup">77</hi> He claims it is the preservation and celebration of
                plant life that cause him to resume versifying after two decades. It was also
                budding love, as the “Derbyshire lady” was Elizabeth Pole who would eventually
                become his second wife. (She was married at the time to Colonel Edward Sacheverel
                Pole, thirty years her senior. Darwin, sixteen years older than Elizabeth, met her
                through medically treating her and her children.) Having recommenced, Darwin did not
                keep his droll promise to stop, but composed a series of poems to Elizabeth which
                share some elements with <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>.<hi rend="sup">78</hi> This
                first in the series sets the tone, with Darwin taking on the female voice of a
                “Wood-Nymph” (though transforming in the final stanza into a “love-struck swain”)
                and asking his reader to cross the line between kingdoms and identify with
                plants:</p>
            <p>Hear, bright Eliza! ere thy dread commands Lop my green arms, my leafy tresses
                tear</p>
            <p>[…]</p>
            <p>Know, in this Grove there sleeps in every tree A Nymph, embalm’d by some poetic
                spell, Who once had beauty, wit and life like thee.</p>
            <p>Oh, spare the mansions where thy sisters dwell!The “poetic spell” recalls, in the
                Proem of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, the “art poetic” by which Ovid “did transmute
                Men, Women, and even Gods and Goddesses, into Trees and Flowers,” and the “similar
                art” by which Darwin will “restore some of them to their original animality, after
                having remained prisoners so long in their respective vegetable mansions.” He mixes
                human and vegetable loves as the nymphs amorously promise (with reference to flowers
                and fruits, that is, to plant sexuality and reproduction): “For thee, sweet Belle,
                our earliest fruits shall grow, / For thee our sweetest blossoms scent the wind.”<hi
                    rend="sup">79</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">80</hi> Many of the poems involve personification of landscape; they
                depict a responsive environment charged with adoration for Elizabeth; they call her
                children “Loves” and express enchantment with her maternal affection (and,
                implicitly, her fertility).<hi rend="sup">81</hi> While they play with the
                conventions of pastoral and Petrarchan romance, the poems also mix in Lunar Society
                industry (in his versified commission of Matthew Boulton to craft a “tea-vase” for
                her) and medicine (alluding to her and her children’s illnesses and cures).<hi
                    rend="sup">82</hi> The fact that Elizabeth was married not only causes these
                poems to resonate with the platonic love, and the painful yearning, that mark some
                of the botanic romances in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>; it also reflects the
                non-monogamous arrangements pervasive in the poem. Indeed, Darwin’s platonic
                protestations are quite impassioned:</p>
            <p>Say! should I gaze o’er thy fair form with bliss, Or ask the balmy rapture of a
                kiss,</p>
            <p>Pure as the vestal meets her sister-guest, Or holy lips on sainted marble
                press’d,</p>
            <p>Could truth, could innocence or virtue blame? And frowns Eliza on my guiltless
                flame?Even though he knows a virtuous married woman cannot “bestow” any more than “A
                cold esteem,” he does not hide or deny his attraction to her.<hi rend="sup"
                >83</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">84</hi> His insistence that his love is pure hardly seems a
                declaration of sexless friendship, but spills over into vindication of sexual desire
                itself as pure, as in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>’s non-judgmental depiction of
                erotic multiplicity.</p>
            <p>After five years of this poetic courtship, Elizabeth’s husband died, and Darwin was
                “more fortunate than Petrarch” in his ideal romance becoming real.<hi rend="sup"
                    >85</hi> They married in March 1781. Between 1782 and 1790, Darwin and Elizabeth
                had seven children together (all but one surviving infancy). Elizabeth already had
                three living children (of four) from her first marriage to Colonel Pole, while
                Darwin had two living from his first marriage to Mary “Polly” Howard (out of five:
                two had died in infancy, and his eldest, Charles, had died at age 19 in 1778, due to
                accidentally cutting his finger while dissecting a corpse during his medical
                studies). Colonel Pole had an illegitimate son previous to his marriage to
                Elizabeth; Elizabeth had been pregnant when she married Colonel Pole; and Elizabeth
                herself was an illegitimate child of the Earl of Portmore. Darwin also had two
                illegitimate daughters by Mary Parker, who, after his first wife died, came into the
                household to look after his son Robert. Darwin did not marry Mary Parker, but they
                seem to have stayed on good terms: he visited her after she married Joseph Day in
                1782 and found her “very happy I believe.”<hi rend="sup">86</hi> Susan and Mary
                Parker (born in 1772 and 1774) continued to live with the cumulative Darwin family,
                and Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">A Plan for the Conduct of Female Education in
                    Boarding Schools </hi>(1797) arises from his role in setting up a school to be
                run by</p>
            <p>Susan and Mary. Darwin’s household, then, rather like <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>itself, combined unconventional, non-monogamous love and
                fertility with legitimate and loyal domestic joys.</p>
            <p>Real as well as poetic plants, gardens, and landscapes played a part in Darwin’s
                relationship with Elizabeth. In King-Hele’s view, when Darwin began the botanic
                garden that inspired Seward’s verses, he “was obviously inspired by Elizabeth Pole.
                She was an almost obsessive gardener: fifty years later, when she was eighty, she
                would spend all day outside working, and supervising improvements to her extensive
                    gardens.”<hi rend="sup">87</hi> The only contemporary account of what Darwin’s
                Lichfield botanic garden was like is Seward’s poem and Darwin’s adaptation of it for
                the opening of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Economy</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetation</hi>. Seward would later give a general
                description of it in her memoirs of Darwin (see Appendix 4.1).<hi rend="sup">88</hi>
                In <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi>, Darwin would retrospectively describe the
                grotto he had excavated, and its strata, as an example of “a situation where the
                manner of the production of springs is most agreeably visible.”<hi rend="sup"
                    >89</hi> Paul Elliott has gathered available evidence to try to envision the
                garden, and emphasizes that it would have combined the functions of a physic garden
                or botanic garden (with organized specimens of classes of plants for both medical
                and botanical purposes) and a landscape garden (with plants chosen and arranged for
                aesthetic effect).<hi rend="sup">90</hi> The garden itself, then, resembles <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, in its combination of beauty and pleasure with science
                and utility; even more so if Darwin created the garden both for his courtship of
                Elizabeth and his Linnaean studies. Ironically, however, on their marriage,
                Elizabeth did not come to live in Lichfield, but Darwin left his real botanic garden
                to live with her at Radburn Hall, over twenty miles away, near Derby.<hi rend="sup"
                    >91</hi> He made another botanic garden when they moved to their house in Full
                Street, Derby, in 1783, and for this there is an extant notebook cataloging plants
                (begun in 1796). Elliott observes that, while many “were not conventional garden
                cultivars” and could easily be mistaken for weeds, Darwin also “marked</p>
            <p>some plants in the notebook with a ‘B,’ indicating those regarded as especially
                beautiful, most of which produced particularly large or colourful flowers.” Elliott
                determines, by the catalog’s account of how many Darwin planted, that irises were
                “unquestionably one of his favourite flowers.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">The</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Lunar</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Society</hi></p>
            <p>In the 1770s and 1780s, when Darwin was composing <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, the
                Lunar Society of Birmingham was at its height. Darwin was a founder when it had its
                beginnings in the late 1750s, and it remained active until around 1800. It was in
                December 1775 that they began to have planned, though irregular, meetings at each
                other’s houses on the Monday nearest a full moon (to have light for traveling in the
                evening). Though Darwin moved in 1781, and other members came and went as well, he
                kept in touch with several of his fellow “Lunaticks” by letter. Indeed, even before
                the move, much of their philosophical communication took the form of correspondence.
                On one occasion when Darwin, having to attend to patients, sent his regrets for a
                meeting of the “troop of philosophers,” he described what he would be missing:
                “Lord! what inventions, what wit, what rhetoric, metaphysical, mechanical and
                pyrotechnical, will be on the wing.”<hi rend="sup">92</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">93</hi> Their topics of discussion had a remarkable range: as Jenny
                Uglow summarizes, “from optics and astronomy, chemistry and mechanics, hydraulics
                and minerals, to meteorology and magnetism, ballooning and ballistics.”<hi
                    rend="sup">94</hi> What particularly characterized the Society was its equal
                interest in theoretical, experimental, and applied science. They shared a strong
                belief that knowledge and invention, activity and industry were improving forces,
                for individual advancement, but above all for the common good and the material,
                intellectual and political progress of humanity. The Society was known for the
                radicalism of several of its members who</p>
            <p>were, for instance, enthusiastic supporters of the French Revolution, advocates for
                the repeal of the Test Acts (laws which seriously disadvantaged those not of the
                Church of England), and active abolitionists.</p>
            <p>Darwin’s close friends Richard Lovell Edgeworth, author, educator, experimenter and
                inventor, and Josiah Wedgwood, innovative pottery manufacturer and patron of the
                arts, were members. Other members included Matthew Boulton, the founder of the first
                “manufactory” in England (Soho, founded 1761), James Watt, the pioneer of steam
                power who partnered with Boulton in industry, and James Kier, who was a chemist and
                a manufacturer of glass and of soap. There was also Thomas Day, co-author with John
                Bicknell of the antislavery poem <hi rend="italic">The Dying Negro </hi>(1773), and
                author of the influential three-volume children’s book <hi rend="italic">Sandford
                    and Merton </hi>(1783–1789), which inserts a broad range of scientific
                information into its moral narrative.</p>
            <p>Notoriously, Day attempted a Rousseauvian project of educating two young girls in
                hope that he could create the perfect wife. Maria Edgeworth, connected with the
                Lunar Society through her father, applied this irresistibly novelistic plot to
                Clarence Hervey’s relationship with Virginia in <hi rend="italic">Belinda
                </hi>(1801).</p>
            <p>The great author, Unitarian minister, scientist, and radical Joseph Priestley joined
                the society around the time Darwin left for Derby; thus, they did not get the chance
                to know each other well, but it is evident from his references that Darwin was
                familiar with Priestley’s work. Priestley is the prime example of the way the Lunar
                Society combined science and radicalism. He also symbolizes the popular assumption
                that the innovative, experimental and polymathic must be politically dangerous. In
                1791, a reactionary mob burned the New Meeting House where Priestley was minister,
                along with his home and laboratory, after he had held a dinner commemorating the
                fall of the Bastille.</p>
            <p>Another Lunar Society member was William Withering, a physician and botanist like
                Darwin. There was a heated controversy when Darwin published research on the medical
                use of digitalis before Withering did.<hi rend="sup">95</hi> Other rivalries in the
                group were more friendly; for example, Darwin had invented a copying machine he
                called a “bigrapher” (an apparatus with which writing with one pen would be
                reproduced by another attached pen). This captured the imagination of Watt who was
                spurred to make his own invention: he wrote to Darwin, “I have fallen on a way of
                copying writing <hi rend="italic">chemically </hi>which beats your bigrapher
                hollow.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                    >Commonplace</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Book</hi><hi rend="bold"
                    > </hi><hi rend="bold">and</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                    >Inventions</hi></p>
            <p>Darwin’s bigrapher is one of the inventions found in the commonplace book that he
                kept from 1776–1787, coinciding with the period of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>’s
                    composition.<hi rend="sup">96</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">97</hi> Along with the inventions, which often include sketches or
                diagrams, there are medical notes consisting both of case studies and theoretical
                ideas; there are also records of experiments, and ideas and observations on topics
                such as meteorology and chemistry, as well as on botany and horticulture. The
                inventions themselves span several scientific and mechanical categories: an
                electrical doubler for use in medical electrical therapy; spinning and weaving
                machines; a weathercock attached to a pointer in Darwin’s study so that he could see
                the direction of the wind from inside; a rocket motor propelled by inflammable air
                (hydrogen) and dephlogisticated air (oxygen). Even his playful invention of an
                artificial goose involved replicating the movement of wings based on close, detailed
                observation; and Darwin explored three different ways to power the goose: a
                watch-spring, gunpowder, or compressed air.<hi rend="sup">98</hi> Inventions
                specifically for the garden include an improved plough that could “make two small
                furrows at once, one on one side of a horse &amp; the other on the other side of
                him”; a “melonometer,” or “brazen gardener,” a copper or glass vessel</p>
            <p>containing spirit of wine in a vacuum, which would open a hotbed when the sun shone;
                and an “ananometer,” a tube with a globe of hydrogen on one end and of mercury on
                the other, which would move in response to temperature and could be used “to admit
                air in to hothouses, or to stop up a fire-flew.”Many of Darwin’s inventions for
                public improvements show his dynamic development of shared interests with his fellow
                Lunaticks. Wedgwood was interested in canals for transportation of his pottery and
                had advocated for the construction of the Grand Trunk Canal (later called the Trent
                and Mersey Canal), finished in 1777. In 1765, Darwin wrote an initial draft for a
                pamphlet defending the canal plans.<hi rend="sup">99</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">100</hi> In 1771, he shared his own canal design ideas for Lichfield
                in letters to Wedgwood, and in a 1777 entry in the commonplace book, designed a
                canal lift for situations where boats would have to pass from one level to
                    another.<hi rend="sup">101</hi> Another idea Darwin returned to was the
                horizontal windmill, which would have more power and fewer parts than a regular
                windmill. He conceived of it for Wedgwood’s use in grinding pigments for his pottery
                factory. In 1779, he recorded experiments with the horizontal windmill in his
                commonplace book; Edgeworth helped with the project by doing experiments and making
                a model; and after the invention was workshopped at a Lunar Society meeting, James
                Watt wrote to Darwin with ample technical advice (incidentally, he copied the letter
                to demonstrate his chemical copying process). The invention was successfully
                constructed, and was in use at Wedgwood’s pottery works for thirteen years before
                being replaced by a steam engine.<hi rend="sup">102</hi> But that was not the end of
                it: Darwin repurposed the horizontal windmill years later in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phytologia</hi>, suggesting it could power a pump to drain morasses.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">The</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Derby</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Philosophical</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi
                    rend="bold">Society</hi></p>
            <p>When Darwin moved to Derby in 1783, he founded the Derby Philosophical Society, a
                more formal society than the Lunar. Its main purposes were to provide a forum for
                philosophical discussion and to build a library. Darwin thought of the Derby and
                Lunar societies fraternally, suggesting to Matthew Boulton that they might
                occasionally have joint meetings, and marking the inception of the Derby society
                with the launch of a hydrogen balloon meant to greet the Lunaticks by landing in
                Boulton’s garden, though, to Darwin’s amusement, it blew several miles off
                course.Both societies were exemplary of the Midlands Enlightenment and its
                definitively local intellectual energy which was also confidently connected to the
                bigger ideas and broader movements of the wider world. Darwin was born near
                Nottingham and lived all his life in the Midlands except during his university
                studies at Cambridge and Edinburgh. Though he covered a lot of ground travelling
                locally to see patients, he rarely ventured even as far as London. He lived there
                briefly when he took a term off from Cambridge in 1753 to attend William Hunter’s
                anatomy lectures in Covent Garden; he later visited once with Elizabeth after their
                marriage, when he met Joseph Banks and Henry Fuseli, and twice in 1785 to act as a
                witness for Richard Arkwright’s defence of the patent of his cotton-spinning
                    machine.<hi rend="sup">103</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">104</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">105</hi> But Darwin’s rousing address to the first regular meeting of
                the Derby Philosophical Society is geographically and temporally vast in its scope.
                Transforming the Biblical image of “the tree of knowledge, whose fruit, forbidden to
                the brute creation, has been plucked by the daring hand of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Experimental Philosophy,</hi>” Darwin declares that its “seed” was “sowed in
                Egypt” and “put forth buds and branches afterwards in Arabia”; and “in our times
                has, by the abundance of its flowers, and the exuberance of its fruit, enriched the
                whole terraqueous globe.”<hi rend="sup">106</hi> Societies, like the Derby Society,
                have been established “for the laudable purpose of collecting the scattered facts
                which</p>
            <p>belong to these various subjects [of natural and experimental philosophy], and
                converging them, as it were, into one luminous point, or focus, to exhibit the
                distinct and beautiful images of science,”<hi rend="sup">107</hi> rather like the
                    <hi rend="italic">camera obscura </hi>in the Proem to <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP</hi>. Darwin envisions both a concentrating and a projecting effect:
                knowledge is gathered by local societies, displayed publicly in “beautiful images”
                for pleasure as well as edification, and in turn the knowledge produced by such
                societies is “circulated in every corner of the world.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">The</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Botanical</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Society</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi
                    rend="bold">at</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Lichfield</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">and</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                    >Translations</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">of</hi><hi rend="bold"
                    > </hi><hi rend="bold">Linnaeus</hi></p>
            <p>Darwin founded yet another learned society, the Botanical Society at Lichfield, in
                the late 1770s, during the time he was composing <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>. It
                would produce two translations of Linnaeus’s works. <hi rend="italic">A System of
                    Vegetables </hi>(1783) is a translation of <hi rend="italic">Systema
                    Vegetabilium </hi>and <hi rend="italic">The Families of Plants </hi>(1787) is a
                translation of <hi rend="italic">Genera Plantarum</hi>. Both are based on updated
                and expanded editions of their respective texts, and also draw on additional sources
                by Linnaeus, his son and his followers, and other botanists (see <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>Preface vi–viii and editor’s note).</p>
            <p>The Society consisted of Darwin, Brooke Boothby, and William Jackson. Seward joked,
                “it was amusing to hear scientific travellers, on their transit over Lichfield,
                inquiring after the state of the botanical society there,” when it only had three
                    members.<hi rend="sup">108</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">109</hi> Boothby, a writer and traveler, was part of the Lichfield
                literary circle with Seward and Darwin, and had an enthusiasm for collecting exotic
                    plants.<hi rend="sup">110</hi> He was also a friend of Rousseau: they first met
                when Rousseau stayed at Wootton Hall in Staffordshire in 1766–1767. Darwin met
                Rousseau too at this time, apparently not through Boothby but through his medical
                services to the Davenport family of Wootton Hall.<hi rend="sup">111</hi> Charles
                Darwin recounts that when Rousseau visited a cave under the Hall’s terrace (one of
                his favourite places for “melancholy contemplation”), Erasmus, knowing Jean-</p>
            <p>Jacques “disliked being interrupted, [...] sauntered by the cave, and minutely
                examined a plant growing in front of it. This drew forth Rousseau, who was
                interested in botany, and they conversed together, and afterwards corresponded
                during several years,” but the correspondence does not survive.<hi rend="sup"
                    >112</hi> Boothby, on a continental tour in 1775, visited Rousseau, who
                entrusted him with the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Rousseau, Juge de
                    Jean-Jacques: Premier Dialogue</hi>, which Boothby published in 1780 after
                Rousseau’s death. Boothby is best known for the 1781 portrait Joseph Wright of Derby
                painted of him, in which he appears as the quintessential man of sensibility,
                reclining in a woodland scene, dandily dressed, and holding a volume of Rousseau.<hi
                    rend="sup">113</hi> Janet Browne has suggested that the background might be
                Darwin’s botanic garden, while Jacques Zonneveld argues that it is a particular spot
                in Twenty Oak Wood that was another favorite Staffordshire haunt of Rousseau.<hi
                    rend="sup">114</hi> Years later, Boothby would suffer greatly from the death of
                his only child Penelope in 1791 at age six. His collection of poems, <hi
                    rend="italic">Sorrows Sacred to the Memory of Penelope </hi>(1796), includes a
                sonnet to Darwin in gratitude for his medical care and sympathetic consolation, as
                well as an imitation of Horace dedicated to Darwin.The William Jackson of the
                Botanical Society might be “W. Jackson, of <hi rend="italic">Lichfield</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Close</hi>” who wrote <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Beauties of Nature </hi>(1769).<hi rend="sup">115</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">116</hi> The book consists mainly of a series of essays on the animal,
                vegetable, and mineral kingdoms, and the planets, comets, and stars, along with
                philosophical, moral, and theological themes, followed by a series of “Maxims of
                Truth” and an unconnected selection of poems, some moral, many rude. The chapter,
                “Of the vegetable World, or God’s Glory displayed in a short Description thereof,”
                includes some florid passages that call for comparison to <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP</hi>, such as a description of tempting fruits that “now wanton in my Eye
                […] enamelled and tinged with burnished Gold, vermillioned over with maiden Blushes,
                wooing me to pull and taste their enchanting Sweets.”<hi rend="sup">117</hi> But
                Jackson goes so far as to assert, quite</p>
            <p>contrary to his future efforts with the Botanical Society, that “the infinite Variety
                of Plants […] is a Labyrinth too intricate for the Tread of mortal Man.”<hi
                    rend="sup">118</hi> Linnaeus would make that “Labyrinth” navigable, but here
                Jackson unstintingly emphasizes the ultimate ineffability of God’s creation and the
                limitations of undeserving Man. The kinds of inquiries he targets as hubristic, such
                as “to conceive, much less demonstrate, how [a] Seed, is by the Earth, formed into a
                Fœtus; or how it acquires Strength and is assisted and nourished in its several
                Gradations to Maturity,” or to analyze “how, and by what concealed Power or
                Instinct, a vegetable can feel, be sensible of, and retire from, the Human Touch,
                fainty and terrified” and then revive,<hi rend="sup">119</hi> are just such
                questions as Darwin would dare to answer in <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>and
                throughout his writings.</p>
            <p>It is not known for certain how the Botanical Society divided its work on the
                translations of Linnaeus. Seward’s account is so negative about Jackson as to seem
                obviously biased: she sums him up as “a would-be philosopher, a turgid and solemn
                coxcomb” who “worshipped and <hi rend="italic">aped</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>Dr.
                Darwin” and was merely “a useful drudge” to Darwin and Boothby “in their joint work
                […] His illustrious coadjutors exacted of him fidelity to the sense of their author,
                and they corrected Jackson’s inelegant English.”<hi rend="sup">120</hi> Elliott
                finds that his brief obituary in the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>called him a “man of literature, and an useful assistant to
                Dr. Darwin, in his ingenious publication of the System of Vegetables.”<hi rend="sup"
                    >121</hi> King-Hele believes Boothby and Jackson helped with checking and
                proofreading, while Darwin did the actual translating.Darwin’s letters certainly
                suggest he devoted much careful attention to the translation of Linnaean
                    terminology.<hi rend="sup">122</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">123</hi> In 1781, he sent “a specimen of a translation of the genera
                and species plantarum” to “about forty botanists,” among them Linnaeus the Younger
                and Joseph Banks, asking for comments and advice, consistently inquiring “<hi
                    rend="underline">if you think it can be translated on a</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">better</hi><hi rend="underline"> </hi><hi rend="underline"
                    >plan.</hi>”<hi rend="sup">124</hi> He also consulted “that great Master of the
                english tongue Dr. SAMUEL JOHNSON”</p>
            <p>(despite their rivalrous mutual dislike, according to Seward) “for his advice in the
                formation of the botanic language.”<hi rend="sup">125</hi> In his letters to Banks
                in 1781–1782, Darwin gets quite specific in asking help with obtaining books for
                research, debating questions of translation, and reporting the comments of other
                correspondents.A central principle of Darwin’s translation is to retain specifically
                Linnaean terms but give them English terminations: for instance, he renders
                “pistillum” as “pistil,” “anthera” as “anther,” and the plural “stamina” as
                “stamens.” In this he deliberately follows the lead of Rousseau who adapted Linnaean
                terms to French by the same method.<hi rend="sup">126</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">127</hi> For other descriptive terms, Darwin translated the root word
                into English but took pains to find English terminations that would be accurate,
                idiomatic, and euphonious, thinking through many examples (e.g., “egg-shape” versus
                “egg-shaped” or “egg’d”; “toothlike” versus “toothed”).<hi rend="sup">128</hi> The
                current forms of several English botanical terms can be traced back to Darwin’s
                decisions, such as “bract” and “floret.”Darwin’s principles contrast with those of
                William Withering who translated portions of Linnaeus’s <hi rend="italic">Genera
                    Plantarum </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Species Plantarum </hi>as part of <hi
                    rend="italic">A Botanical Arrangement of all the Vegetables Naturally Growing in
                    Great Britain </hi>(1776). Withering purposely anglicized and desexualized
                Linnaean terms, for instance translating “stamen” and “pistillum” as “chive” and
                “pointal.” Darwin insists that the “sexual distinctions […] are essential to the
                philosophy of the system,” and that many of Withering’s English terms “bear no
                analogy to those of LINNEUS.”<hi rend="sup">129</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">130</hi> And Darwin observes that Linnaeus “may be said <hi
                    rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">have</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">formed</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">language</hi>,
                rather than to have found one, suitable to his purpose.”<hi rend="sup">131</hi> If
                new words have to be learned anyway, one might as well learn the Linnaean terms. He
                purposely avoids inventing a special English terminology for English readers because
                it “would be so unintelligible to the latin Botanist, <hi rend="italic">that they
                    could not</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">converse together.</hi>”<hi rend="sup">132</hi> For Darwin, it is
                crucial that students of botany who do not know Greek and Latin can “<hi
                    rend="italic">converse</hi>” with those who do, encouraging mutual understanding
                and mutual contribution to the development of the science. It is also important to
                him that retaining the terminology will “assist the young Botanist in his study of
                the original.”<hi rend="sup">133</hi> In the “Botanic Terms and Definitions” section
                of <hi rend="italic">A System of Vegetables</hi>, he gives the Latin alongside every
                English term, and in the “Genera of Classes” section, as well as in the headings
                throughout, he provides the Greek names of the classes, as he does, too, in the
                “Preface” to <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>.An entry in Darwin’s commonplace book from
                1778 seems to presage <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>as well as the translations:
                “Linneus might certainly be translated into English without losing his sexual terms,
                or other metaphors, &amp; yet avoiding any indecent idea.” Tantalizingly, there are
                a couple of crossed-out letters before Darwin settles on the word “indecent.” He
                then tries out possible terms: for classes, “1. one male” with another possibility,
                “beau” written above; “2 two males &amp;</p>
            <p>c. 13 many males. 14 two masters,” with “lords” written above; “15. four masters. 16
                one brotherhood 17 two brotherhoods. 18 many brotherhoods. 19 Cotemporaries.” For
                class 20, he tries three alternatives: it appears that he first writes “viragoes,”
                then “male-ladies” above, crosses them both out, and squeezes “male-coquetts” in the
                space between. Then, “21 one house.</p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
                <item>two houses.” with “seperate <hi rend="strikethrough">one</hi> beds” and
                    “seperate <hi rend="strikethrough">beds</hi> houses” written above. For
                    Class</item>
            </list>
            <list rend="bulleted">
                <item>there are three tries: “many marriages” and “cuckoldoms” crossed out, and
                    “polygamies” written into the space. Class 24 is “clandestine marriages.” For
                    the orders, he writes, “1 one lady, two ladies &amp; c.” and above writes other
                    possibilities: “wife,” “belle,” and “wives.”<hi rend="sup">134</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p><hi rend="sup">135</hi> On the same page and facing page are theoretical and
                practical notes on constructing a device to make “luminous music,” as would be
                discussed in <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Interlude III.<hi rend="sup">136</hi> That
                Darwin was thinking of the Linnaeus translations and the composition of <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>very much in tandem is confirmed
                by his</p>
            <p>1781 letter to Banks where the thanks for his comments on the poem come up in the
                midst of updating Banks on the progress of the translation work. The letter also
                explains, “the design of the poem was to induce ladies and other unemploy’d scholars
                to study Botany, by putting many of the agreable botanical facts into the
                notes”.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Popular</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Botany</hi></p>
            <p>Darwin’s translations of Linnaeus, and <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, were part of an
                eighteenth-century trend of popular botany. Ann B. Shteir dates this era of
                participation by non-scientists, including women, in the sciences generally, and
                botany in particular, to a period lasting from the 1760s to the 1830s.<hi rend="sup"
                    >137</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">138</hi> Shteir observes that in the nineteenth century there was “a
                deepening divide between the general and the specialist, the popular and the
                academic, between the ‘high’ science of gentlemen in metropolitan learned societies
                and the ‘low’ science of practitioners who diffused scientific knowledge for
                practical use” and who rejected “activities within scientific culture that were
                associated with politeness and gentility,” leading to the professionalization of
                    science.<hi rend="sup">139</hi> Shteir emphasizes that with the
                professionalization of botany came the defeminization of botany.Darwin was not alone
                in recognizing and writing for the many women and men who did not have the privilege
                of a classical education but wanted to participate in botanical science, whether for
                amusement or for serious study. Thomas Martyn (who was Professor of Botany at
                Cambridge) hopes that his translation of Rousseau’s <hi rend="italic">Letters on the
                    Elements of Botany </hi>(1785) “might be of use to such of my fair countrywomen
                and unlearned countrymen as wished to amuse themselves with Natural History.”<hi
                    rend="sup">140</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">141</hi> William Withering, in “The Design” of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Botanical Arrangement</hi>, explains that his decision to “drop the sexual
                distinctions” of the Linnaean system</p>
            <p>was motivated by “an apprehension that Botany in an English dress would become a
                favourite amusement with the Ladies, many of whom are very considerable proficients
                in the study, in spite of every difficulty.”<hi rend="sup">142</hi> Darwin, in the
                preface to <hi rend="italic">A System of Vegetables</hi>, emphasizes the potential
                of popular participation to expand scientific knowledge: he calls attention to “the
                gardiner, the herb-gatherer, the druggist, the farmer, and all who are concerned in
                cultivating the various tribes of vegetation, in detecting their native habitations,
                or in vending or consuming their products” who “wished to attain, and were capable
                of enlarging” scientific knowledge of plants, but were prevented from doing so as
                long as Linnaeus’s system, “like the Bible in catholic countries, has been locked up
                in a foreign language, accessible only to the learned few, the Priests of Flora.”<hi
                    rend="sup">143</hi> In his acknowledgements, he recognizes the assistance of a
                range of professors, authors, and amateurs, including certain “learned and ingenious
                Ladies,” such as Anna Blackburne, a natural historian with a significant collection
                of flora and fauna (with many rare specimens sent to her by her brother in America),
                who corresponded with Linnaeus himself, and had loaned Darwin a copy of the updated
                thirteenth edition of <hi rend="italic">Systema Vegetabilium</hi>.It was the system
                of Linnaeus that enabled the popular flowering of botany. His binomial nomenclature
                reduced the lengthy descriptive names previously used to two names, genus and
                species. His system was intended to facilitate international communication by
                determining standardized names for plants (while their common names were potentially
                various even within a country, let alone across the world) and a standardized system
                of classification. Such streamlining and international co-ordination was
                particularly necessary for handling the great influx of newly discovered species
                from exploration and colonization.<hi rend="sup">144</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">145</hi> Since classification was based on one feature of the plant,
                its reproductive organs, to identify a plant’s place in the taxonomy one need only
                observe the number, shape, situation, and proportion of pistils and</p>
            <p>stamens (except for species whose reproductive organs were not discernible with the
                eye, classified under Cryptogamia). Linnaeus claimed his system could be learned in
                a year without a teacher.<hi rend="sup">146</hi> However, the benefit of simplicity
                is counterbalanced by the system’s artificiality.</p>
            <p>Because the system focuses on one aspect of the plant only and does not take into
                account the larger picture of plant morphology, it does not necessarily group plants
                according to their natural families.</p>
            <p>Linnaeus freely admitted that his system was artificial, but made the distinction
                that “Natural Orders enable us to judge of the nature of plants; artificial ones
                enable us to distinguish them.”<hi rend="sup">147</hi> Linnaeus himself expected his
                system to be superseded,<hi rend="sup">148</hi> but argued for the usefulness of the
                sexual system in the meantime because of the challenges inherent to constructing a
                natural methodology: “He, who instead of a natural method disposes the plants
                according to the fragments of it, and rejects the artificial method, seems to me to
                resemble a man, who should demolish a commodious house built upon pillars, and in
                its place endeavour to erect another, unable to construct a pedestal, or to turn an
                    arch.”<hi rend="sup">149</hi> Darwin, as enthusiastic as he was in popularizing
                Linnaeus’s artificial sexual system, took a similar view. In <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phytologia</hi>, he observes, “some of [Linnaeus’s] classes have appeared to me
                to be more excellent than others, as they seemed to approach nearer to natural
                    ones.”<hi rend="sup">150</hi> Darwin endorses the benefits of a natural system,
                both for “more readily distinguishing [plants] from each other” and “detecting their
                virtues or uses.”<hi rend="sup">151</hi> But he sticks to the focus on sexual
                organs, suggesting that those Linnaean classes that are more natural are deduced
                “from the situations, proportions, or forms of the sexual organs rather than from
                their number.” He also recognizes that “great time, labour, opportunity, and
                ingenuity, would be required to establish […] the most invariable and most natural
                classes of vegetation.”Linnaeus’s sexual system was embraced across Europe in the
                latter part of the eighteenth century, except in France where it was criticized for
                its artificiality by George Louis Leclerc, comte de Buffon, and by Antoine Laurent
                de Jussieu who, along with his uncle Bernard de Jussieu, and Michel Adanson, was
                instrumental in developing the natural system that would replace it in the
                nineteenth century. In Britain, John Lindley would declare the sexual system dead in
                    1836.<hi rend="sup">152</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">153</hi> Shteir connects this development with the professionalization
                and defeminization of botany: “teachers continued to explicate Linnaean botany for
                students” but it was increasingly “associated with children, beginners, and
                women.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Botany,</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Sex,</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">and</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                    >Gender</hi></p>
            <p>Among the sciences, botany was particularly suitable as an acceptable feminine
                activity.</p>
            <p>It could provide amusement on walks and subjects for drawing, and it did not require
                much special equipment, nor, thanks to Linnaeus and his translators and mediators,
                much previous grounding in scientific knowledge. It could be regarded as a morally
                improving pastime, an antidote to idleness or an alternative to more frivolous
                activities or preoccupations, and a way to know and admire the Creator through His
                works. Yet, simultaneously, botany could also be regarded as highly improper since
                the Linnaean system was based on sex. It implicitly confirmed that plants reproduce
                sexually, a concept that only arose in the late 1600s and continued to be contested
                through Darwin’s time and into the nineteenth century.<hi rend="sup">154</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">155</hi> Linnaeus was attacked by opponents who did not accept the
                very idea of plant sexuality. A quotable example is the article on Botany in the
                first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Britannica </hi>(1771),
                compiled by William Smellie, which asserts that “it is a certain fact, that
                obscenity is the very basis of the Linnæan system” and his writing exhibits “such a
                degree of indelicacy in the expression as cannot be</p>
            <p>exceeded by the most obscene romance-writer.”<hi rend="sup">156</hi> He quotes
                Linnaeus’s <hi rend="italic">Sponsalia Plantarum </hi>[The Betrothal of Plants]
                (1746) with incredulity, giving a full list of analogies between the sexual parts of
                humans and plants in Latin, for example, “<hi rend="italic">Antheræ </hi>sunt
                TESTICULI” and “Stigma est <hi rend="italic">vulva</hi>,” and taking issue with some
                of them in English: “The calix is made to represent no less than three things of
                very opposite natures; first, it is analogous to the <hi rend="italic">chamber of
                    the bride</hi>, then to the <hi rend="italic">female organ</hi>, and last of all
                to the LABIA.”<hi rend="sup">157</hi> He remarks that “Men or philosophers can smile
                at the nonsense and absurdity of such obscene gibberish; but it is easy to guess
                what effects it may have upon the young and thoughtless”: a “bad tendency upon
                morals.”According to Sam George, it was only in “the turbulent revolutionary climate
                of the 1790s” that “the stereotype of the forward, sexually precocious female
                botanist made its first appearance in literature,” and it appeared specifically in
                parodies targeting <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>.<hi rend="sup">158</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">159</hi> For instance, Richard Polwhele “shudder[s]” to see girls
                “With bliss botanic […] point the prostitution of a plant; / Dissect its organ of
                unhallow’d lust, / And fondly gaze the titillating dust,” and he confides, “I have,
                several times, seen boys and girls botanizing together” (see Appendix 5.10).<hi
                    rend="sup">160</hi> Here, botanizing becomes a euphemism for illicit and
                promiscuous sexual activity. His shock is quite humorous and reveals a combined
                horror at female sexuality and female science education. This scandalized response
                was not universal, as Julia List shows.<hi rend="sup">161</hi> The fact that the
                conservative writer Thomas James Mathias, called “frightful” and “a <hi
                    rend="italic">literary </hi>alarmist” by <hi rend="italic">The Monthly
                    Review</hi>,<hi rend="sup">162</hi> was the first to attack <hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>for its treatment of gender and sexuality (see Appendix 5.9) seems a
                definite clue that it was liberating. Yet, interestingly, recent scholarship has
                taken differing views on this point: for some, <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>is a
                celebration of sexuality unconstrained by the double standard or monogamy,<hi
                    rend="sup">163</hi> while for others it reinforces gender stereotypes and
                conventions of heterosexuality and marriage.Ann Shteir and Londa Schiebinger have
                argued that the Linnaean system imposed eighteenth-century assumptions about sex and
                gender on the vegetable kingdom, assuming they were natural and insinuating them
                into scientific knowledge.<hi rend="sup">164</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">165</hi> Calling stamens and pistils male and female in the first
                place is a construction based on analogy with human reproductive organs. The
                Linnaean system inherently projects human sexuality onto plants, whether it fits or
                not. If Linnaeus is ready to say anthers <hi rend="italic">are </hi>testicles and
                the stigma <hi rend="italic">is </hi>the vulva, Darwin’s romances of personified
                pistils and stamens go yet further in projection. That Linnaeus uses such metaphors
                in science writing makes it seem accidental how amusing they are. By extending them
                into poetry, Darwin spotlights their fantastical aspect. Darwin’s dramatizations
                vividly show where analogies between human and plant sex break down, biologically,
                culturally, and morally. One obvious instance is the numbers, italicized ostensibly
                to indicate the Linnean classification but also with a sensationalist effect,
                showing off how rare monogamy is among vegetables: for instance,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Two </hi>knights before thy fragrant altar bend, Adored MELISSA!
                and <hi rend="italic">two </hi>squires attend. Meadia’s soft chains <hi
                    rend="italic">five</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>suppliant beaux confess,</p>
            <p>And hand in hand the laughing belle address (<hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>I:59–62)</p>
            <p>Furthermore, as Walpole noticed, the males consistently outnumber the females so that
                it is “the botanic <hi rend="italic">ladies </hi>who keep harems and not the <hi
                    rend="italic">gentlemen</hi>” (see Appendix 5.6).The sexual daring is more
                suggestive than explicit. Darwin’s episodes do not tend to include sexual acts as
                much as anticipatory, respectful, or unrequited desire. It could be called very soft
                erotica, as in Darwin’s penchant for feminine garments being blown aside by the
                wind. The relationships are generally placed in the framework of marriage and
                courtship, even when</p>
            <p>they involve multiples: “The freckled IRIS owns a fiercer flame, / And <hi
                    rend="italic">three </hi>unjealous husbands wed the dame” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP </hi>I:71–2). This simultaneously subjects the eroticism to social
                regulation and redefines the parameters of marriage. Darwin rarely pronounces
                judgment on such alternative arrangements. For instance, in the poem’s big finish
                describing Adonis where “A <hi rend="italic">hundred </hi>virgins join a <hi
                    rend="italic">hundred </hi>swains,” a couple of negative adjectives
                arise—“Licentious Hymen [...] loosely twines the meretricious bands”—but both are
                paradoxically yoked to marriage. And this describes the flower; when the verses turn
                to human mass marriage in Tahiti, “pleased Venus [...] smiles [...] / And the loves
                laugh at all, but Nature’s laws” (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>IV:467, 481–82,
                483–86).</p>
            <p>Because of being figuratively grounded in male-female marriage, and literally based
                on reproduction, the poem’s sexual freedoms seem limited to the heteronormative.<hi
                    rend="sup">166</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">167</hi> However, it doesn’t take a big stretch of imagination to
                start wondering about the relationship the “<hi rend="italic">three </hi>unjealous
                husbands” have with each other. Ditto, of course, where there are multiple females,
                such as “<hi rend="italic">Five </hi>sister-nymphs to join Diana’s train” (I:107).
                Gender roles and identities in <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>are often stereotypical,
                or perhaps it would be more accurate to call them archetypal, but they are also
                diverse, if only due to the constantly changing scenes. And the Linnaean system
                comes complete with a class, Gynandria, which Darwin translates alternately as
                “feminine males” and “masculine ladies” (cf. <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Preface, p.
                v, and IV:281n). Maja Bondestam argues that, for all the wives and husbands and
                marriage beds that scholars such as Schiebinger have seized upon, Linnaeus “far more
                often” represented plant reproduction as “hermaphroditic, same-sex and polygamous
                connections.” He did not “have any difficulty in imagining plants as
                hermaphroditic.” Indeed, the combination of sexes in one individual was central for
                Linnaeus”</p>
            <p>and his “botany actually legitimated a multitude of sexual anatomies and
                unconventional sexual associations in nature, making them natural and
                conceivable.”Besides, it is too easy to forget that, as M.M. Mahood points out,
                there are many “scenarios” in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>“in
                which sex has no role.”<hi rend="sup">168</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">169</hi> The epic similes often allow departures from the main theme,
                but even the plant tableaux begin to stray quite early. About halfway through Canto
                I, Helianthus is depicted as a “gaudy band” of sun worshippers with no mention of
                courtship, marriage, or reproduction (<hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>I:223–30). By the time Darwin gets to Canto III, the majority of tableaux
                have nothing to do with romance, sex, or fertility. Only in the final canto does he
                finally return to the supposed main focus of the poem. This could merely be a
                failure to stay on topic, but Mahood sees it as a way for Darwin to ease up on the
                pervasive multiple suitors for the sake of propriety.<hi rend="sup">170</hi> It
                could also be a way of suggesting that “Loves” can take many forms and have many
                objects. Over the course of the poem, they range from love between parent and child
                to love of learning, invention, and inspiration. And if <hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>makes rarity of monogamy natural, it makes these alternative passions natural
                as well.</p>
            <p>Even while its plant romances can be seen alternately as absurdly fanciful or
                narrowly conventional, <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>has great potential to call into
                question biological and moral assumptions about human gender and sexuality, not only
                through its dissonant analogies between plant and human, but also through the
                artificiality with which it treats the natural. In light of the pageantry of
                Darwin’s vignettes, all gender roles can come to seem performative, and all sexual
                tendencies seem like role play. There is something very camp about them, equally in
                the ornately sensational and the sweetly domestic. Readers like Horace Walpole and
                Mary Berry picked up on the campiness from the start, while others, such as Hannah
                More, simply couldn’t relate (see Appendix 5.6).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Humans</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">and</hi><hi
                    rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold">Nature</hi></p>
            <p>The most striking artificiality of Darwin’s verse is his use of personification. In
                this, as well as his retro heroic couplets and heightened poetical style, Darwin is
                rather far from Wordsworth’s “language really used by men.”<hi rend="sup">171</hi>
                But, as Catherine Packham observes, Darwin did not indulge in “personifications of
                abstract ideas” as many eighteenth-century poets did and Wordsworth tried to avoid
                doing; instead, Darwin personified visible, living things.<hi rend="sup">172</hi>
                Personification seems key to understanding the kinds of relationship between humans
                and nature envisioned in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>. On the one hand, it reinforces
                the projection of the human on to nature already inherent in Linnaean taxonomy. As a
                form of anthropomorphization, it overrides the otherness of the non-human and
                reduces other living things to human terms. In this way it takes human perception
                and experience as the universal norm and assumes that nature exists only in relation
                to humans and for human use. Like his Lunar Society industrialist companions, Darwin
                certainly believed that nature exists for manipulation and improvement by humans,
                and for human benefit. Examples abound in <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, especially in
                Canto II, of his interest in the medicinal and practical uses of plants, depicted in
                both verse and notes as offered willingly by nature, such as in the fortuitous
                discovery of the febrifugal properties of cinchona (a.k.a. Peruvian bark) due to
                felling trees into a lake providing drinking water (<hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>II:347–404). In <hi rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, Darwin’s
                ingenious idea of evening out the world climate by dragging icebergs to the Equator
                is horrifying in our age of global warming, but for him was a co-operative pairing
                of nature’s potential with human ingenuity for the general good.<hi rend="sup"
                    >173</hi> As Donna Coffey puts it, it seems ironic that “the very technologies
                which Darwin was engaged in developing would contribute to the degradation of the
                natural world which he loved. In essence, the first half of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Botanic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Garden</hi>”
                    (<hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Economy</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetation</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>with its
                celebration of industry and invention) “would lead to the destruction of the second
                    half.”<hi rend="sup">174</hi> But critics have recently been giving increasing
                attention to this paradox in Darwin’s writing and discovering its ecological
                possibilities.Personification also has the potential to endow non-human forms of
                life with human-like faculties, giving them agency and value commensurate to humans.
                This apparently opposite function of personification also accords with Darwin’s
                thought. He theorized that plants had volition, could sleep and dream, and could
                form ideas. Depicting the romances of personified stamens and pistils, then, is not
                a mere gimmick, or a preposterous fancy, if plants can actually experience the
                passion of love, as Darwin liked to believe (See <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia
                </hi>XIII, Of Vegetable Animation, Appendix 3.1). He was fascinated by analogies
                between plant and animal systems, organizing the first part of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>around the “Physiology of Vegetation,”
                with chapters such as “Their Pulmonary Arteries and Veins,” “Their Organs of
                Reproduction,” and “Their Muscles, Nerves, and Brain,” all of which in their
                contents consistently turn to animal-vegetable comparisons. Similarly, in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, the Additional Notes on vegetable
                physiology include “‘Perspiration,’ ‘Placentation,’ ‘Circulation,’ ‘Respiration,’
                ‘Impregnation’ and ‘Glandulation’ on a strict analogy, even homology, with the
                animal,” as Komisaruk and Dushane observe.<hi rend="sup">175</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">176</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>attests to his fascination with the grey areas in the
                hierarchy of life forms, such as plants that resemble insects (e.g., <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP </hi>I:243n), and mushrooms as “a kind of isthmus connecting
                the two mighty kingdoms of animal and of vegetable nature” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>I:427n). His view of organic life becomes less
                a hierarchy than a continuum, with all forms of life in some ways being on a level,
                and in other ways having different degrees of complexity in their systems, which yet
                remain fundamentally analogous.</p>
            <p>Many of Darwin’s readers and critics felt differently. Hannah More wished that Darwin
                had devoted his poetic abilities “to subjects more congenial to human feelings, than
                the intrigues of a flower garden”: she can “feel” for the “beauty” of flowers, but
                is “indifferent […] to their amours, their pleasures, or their unhappiness.” Indeed,
                it upsets her that reading <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>could
                take away that indifference: “I should lose one of my greatest pleasures, and […] be
                filled with alarm lest every rose and pink I gathered might make a multitude of
                widows and orphans” (see Appendix 5.6).<hi rend="sup">177</hi> She anticipates the
                objections of later commentators. For example, in 1800, Polwhele would ask, “How is
                it possible to enter into the feelings of plants? Are we not, in a manner insulted,
                when seriously called upon, to sympathize with herbs and flowers in their secret
                sighs? […] What a burlesque on love, the most charming, the most poetical, of our
                passions!” (see Appendix 5.16).<hi rend="sup">178</hi> Apparently it is insulting to
                humans to suggest that other forms of life may have feelings. Such a response seems
                to cling to a superior position separate from a firmly subordinated nature, while
                Darwin’s delightful fancies once again threaten the supposed natural order of
                things. In this light, Wordsworth’s rejection of personification, which closes with
                the statement, “I have wished to keep my Reader in the company of flesh and
                blood”—not plant tissue—“persuaded that by so doing I shall interest him”, seems to
                be a stark refusal to “enter into the feelings” of the natural world.<hi rend="sup"
                    >179</hi> This might seem impossible to impute to such a devotee of nature as
                Wordsworth, but his relation to nature is very different from Darwin’s, for whom
                nature is out there, to be observed and employed by humans, rather than an extension
                of human interiority. The perception of nature as reflecting or inspiring the inner
                life of humans is another kind of projection of the human on nature. Ironically, the
                artificiality of Darwin’s verse defers more to nature, as it prevents nature from
                being reduced to a reflection of the human psyche. It foregrounds its own artfulness
                and admits that nature is being perceived and</p>
            <p>understood from a specifically human point of view that is not universal but one
                particular part of nature, one species among others.</p>
            <p>A passage in <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>shows Darwin
                (in the voice of an anonymous “Philosopher”) attempting to see humans as one species
                among many:</p>
            <p>I well remember to have heard an ingenious agricultor boast, that he had drained two
                hundred acres of morassy land, on which he now was able to feed a hundred oxen; and
                added, “is not that a meritorious thing?” “True,” replied one of the company, “but
                you forget, that you have destroyed a thousand free republics of ants, and ten
                thousand rational frogs, besides innumerable aquatic insects, and aquatic
                vegetables.”Here Darwin flips the script from humans mastering the natural
                environment to being part of an interdependent ecosystem. And nature is not an
                abstraction but a myriad particular beings who have intellectual and political
                capabilities equal (or superior) to the human improver. That artfulness, invention,
                and civilization may not be exclusively human is asserted in several <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP </hi>figures, perhaps most strikingly Papyra, the female
                personification of papyrus who is credited with inventing and teaching writing, that
                most human accomplishment. (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>II;105–54).</p>
            <p>Humans may be set apart from nature in being able to observe it, and to do science
                and poetry as a result, but the immersive experience of the <hi rend="italic">camera
                    obscura </hi>Darwin leads his audience into (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Proem)
                is a curious combination of reflecting nature artfully and observing it from within.
                The very idea of a dichotomy between humans and nature is radically undermined when
                Darwin says, in <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Nature</hi>, that “when a Monarch or
                a mushroom dies,” they are equally “organic matter” that will come back to life in
                another form.<hi rend="sup">180</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">181</hi> Personification of plants in <hi rend="italic">LOTP
                </hi>challenges the human/nature distinction all the while its disjunctions call
                attention to essential difference between life forms. The poem expresses a boundless
                eagerness to understand</p>
            <p>the natural world all the while calling into question the superiority of human
                comprehension. The limitations of the human capacity to understand non-human life
                forms are displayed in the very absurdity of rendering stamens and pistils as swains
                and nymphs. Yet the basis of analogy allows human and non-human beings to be
                comparable but not the same, thus allowing for a sympathetic relation to nature<hi
                    rend="sup">182</hi> that preserves otherness without having to base it on human
                separateness or superiority. As Denise Gigante puts it, for late eighteenth-century
                vitalist writers such as Darwin, analogy “provided a way to keep two entities in
                play without collapsing them into each other.”<hi rend="sup">183</hi> Humans may be
                different, but all entities are different, and <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>glories
                in the immense variety of species and the correspondences between them.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Conclusion:</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="bold"
                >Pleasure</hi></p>
            <p>Walpole wrote of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, “I can read this over and over again
                forever, for though it is so excellent, it is impossible to remember anything so
                disjointed” (see Appendix 5.6).<hi rend="sup">184</hi> So what is the point of
                reading a didactic poem that you immediately forget? The point, with <hi
                    rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, might be different from the traditional purpose to
                delight and instruct. For Darwin, the pleasure is not merely a sugar-coating to
                entice reluctant readers into learning, but an integral element, of value in itself.
                Indeed, studying plant life convinced Darwin that sugar is the basis of all
                nourishment: “as the digested food of vegetables consists principally of sugar, and
                from that is produced again their mucilage, starch, and oil, and since animals are
                sustained by these vegetable productions, it would seem that the sugar-making
                process carried on in vegetable vessels was the great source of life to all
                organized beings.”<hi rend="sup">185</hi> And in <hi rend="italic">Phytologia
                </hi>he represents the earth itself as formed wondrously of pleasure. It is made of
                the decomposed organic matter of living things that had pleasure in the processes
                that formed and maintained their material being, such as digestion and</p>
            <p>secretion; thus, “all the calcareous mountains in the world, and all the strata of
                clay, coal, marl, sand, and iron, which are incumbent on them, are MONUMENTS OF THE
                PAST FELICITY OF ORGANIZED NATURE!” (see Appendix 3.3).<hi rend="sup">186</hi> The
                idea re-echoes near the end of the last canto of <hi rend="italic">The Temple of
                    Nature </hi>in a memorable poetic rendition:</p>
            <p>Thus the tall mountains, that emboss the lands, Huge isles of rock, and continents of
                sands,</p>
            <p>Whose dim extent eludes the inquiring sight, ARE MIGHTY MONUMENTS OF PAST DELIGHT.The
                structure of <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>seems to invite different kinds of
                pleasure. Walpole reassures us that it is all right to enjoy the poem as eye-candy.
                In fact, he may be an ideal reader in this way, given that Darwin introduces the
                poem as a picture show giving “trivial amusement” by beautiful persons, graceful
                attitudes, and brilliant dress (<hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>Proem ix, xi). This may
                be a modest understatement, or it may be a vindication of such pleasures,
                considering how strenuously Darwin defends visual poetry in the Interludes—and how
                strenuously some critics disapproved of such supposed shallowness (see for instance
                Moir and Southey, Appendices 5.17 and 5.19). If the poem were more deep, serious,
                and unified, it would require a different kind of reading. And, as Walpole finds,
                its episodic forgettability offers the potential for ongoing re-reading. Its
                glittery, fleeting tableaux allowed Darwin to compose the poem by returning to it
                periodically over more than a decade, in moments of pleasurable fancy amid the very
                serious responsibility of caring for the sick and dying. As Edgeworth attests,
                “Doctor Darwin composed and wrote the detached pictures in his poem, as he travelled
                in his carriage among his patients” (see Appendix 4.3).<hi rend="sup">187</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">188</hi> The form equally allows readers to dip in amid the demands of
                work and life. Donald M. Hassler argues that “comic irony is indispensable for
                Darwin in the fact of the uncertainties and</p>
            <p>self-contradictions that his sceptical analytic thought reveals”; it is a “defense
                against the puzzles of the infinite universe.”<hi rend="sup">189</hi> In effect,
                both the practical and theoretical work that Darwin did might not have been
                endurable or possible without the poetic lightness he came to be known for.</p>
            <p>In its hybrid form, <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>apparently
                balances frivolity in the verse with seriousness in the notes. But the notes offer
                another kind of pleasure, as they let the reader share the nerdy enjoyment Darwin
                clearly felt in scientific knowledge: in its detail, its facts stranger than
                fiction, and its speculative fictions that he sometimes pursues into the
                delightfully impossible, and sometimes into the intuitions that would break the
                ground for future discoveries. Science, like poetry, offers the benefit of salutary
                diversion. In the catalog of diseases and remedies in the second volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi>, Darwin recommends, as a treatment for “<hi
                    rend="italic">Tædium vitæ,</hi>” “the cultivation of science, as of chemistry,
                natural philosophy, natural history, which supplies an inexhaustible source of
                pleasurable novelty, and relieves ennui by the exertions it occasions.”<hi
                    rend="sup">190</hi> The notes to <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, in their
                overwhelming detail and variety, may be as easily forgettable as the poetry (or, as
                they were for Walpole, “scarce intelligible” (see Appendix 5.6)).<hi rend="sup"
                    >191</hi> But their effect similarly enables selective attention and repeated
                return. Darwin himself often repeats information across his writings, sometimes
                almost verbatim, reseating it in different contexts, which can have fertile results,
                as in his work on <hi rend="italic">Phytologia </hi>leading him to revise his
                theories of generation in the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia </hi>(see
                Appendices 3.2 and 3.4).</p>
            <p>Reseating Darwin’s writing in our twenty-first century context can potentially be as
                fertile. But though I have argued that <hi rend="italic">LOTP </hi>offers a window
                into a time before momentous changes in poetry, science, and culture, and offers
                rich material for thinking through current concerns, perhaps the best reason to keep
                on reading this famously unread book is pleasure. The ostensible didactic purpose
                may be for a reader to learn botany, the delight of the verse leading to</p>
            <p>study of the notes. But even if, like Walpole, we forget what we have just read, we
                might learn something different: regain a lost liberty of wide-ranging thought, of
                imagining impossibilities; realize the fundamental value of pleasure; and rediscover
                the continuity that links all forms of life.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> Walpole to Mary and Agnes Berry, 28 April 1789, in <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Yale</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Edition</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Horace</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Walpole’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>, ed.</p>
            <p>W. S. Lewis (Yale University Press, 1937–1983), Vol. 11, p. 10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">2</hi> King-Hele in <hi rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic
                    Poets </hi>(Macmillan, 1986), and Priestman in <hi rend="italic">The Poetry of
                    Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin:</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Enlightened</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Spaces,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Times</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>(Ashgate, 2013), pp. 217–56, thoroughly track Romantic
                writers’ knowledge of, opinions of, and influence by Darwin. On women’s botanical
                poetry, see Sam George, <hi rend="italic">Botany, Sexuality and Women’s Writing
                    1760–1830 </hi>(Manchester University Press, 2007).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">3</hi> George Gordon, Lord Byron, <hi rend="italic">English</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Bards,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Scotch</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Reviewers.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Satire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>(1809), p. 48n.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">4</hi> William Hazlitt, “Lecture VIII: On the Living Poets,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Lectures</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">on</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">English</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poets</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1818), pp. 287–88.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">5</hi> Charles Darwin, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1879), ed. Desmond
                King-Hele (Cambridge University Press, 2003), pp. 32–3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">6</hi> C. Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 34.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">7</hi> Katherine Binhammer, “The Sex Panic of the 1790s,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">History</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sexuality</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>6.3
                (1996): pp. 409–34.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">8</hi> Binhammer, “The Sex Panic of the 1790s,” p. 417.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">9</hi> Binhammer, “The Sex Panic of the 1790s,” p. 412.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">10</hi> C. Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 63. For
                discussions from different perspectives on Erasmus Darwin and atheism, see Martin
                Priestman, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Atheism: Poetry and Freethought, 1780–1830
                </hi>(Cambridge University Press, 1999), pp. 44–79, and Ashley Marshall, “Erasmus
                Darwin contra David Hume,” <hi rend="italic">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century
                    Studies </hi>30 (2007): pp. 89–111.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">11</hi> C. Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 89.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">12</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Richard</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lovell</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Edgeworth,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Esq.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Begun</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">by</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Himself</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Concluded</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">by</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">his</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Daughter,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Maria</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Edgeworth</hi></p>
            <p>(1820), Vol. 2, p. 137.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">13</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanic</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Garden</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">by</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>ed.
                Adam Komisaruk and Allison Dushane (Routledge, 2017).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">14</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">15</hi> Julia List, “Sometimes a Stamen is Only a Stamen: Sexuality,
                Women and Darwin’s Loves of the Plants,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nineteenth-Century</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Contexts</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>32.3 (2010): p. 207. See also List’s
                “Erasmus Darwin and the Poetry of Science” (PhD diss., University of Melbourne,
                2010) for her broader re-evaluation of the reception of Darwin’s poetry.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">16</hi> Jerome McGann, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sensibility:</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Revolution</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Literary</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Style</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Clarendon, 1996), p.
                1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">17</hi> McGann, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Poetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sensibility</hi>, p. 128.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">18</hi> William Wordsworth, Preface to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lyrical</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ballads</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>(1802), in <hi rend="italic">William</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Wordsworth:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Major</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, ed. Stephen Gill (Oxford
                University Press, 2011), p. 598.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">19</hi> McGann, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Poetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sensibility</hi>, p. 133.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">20</hi> Articles on Erasmus Darwin’s evolutionary theories and their
                relation to Charles’s work include James Harrison, “Erasmus Darwin’s View of
                Evolution,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas </hi>32.2 (1971): pp.
                247–64; Roy Porter, “Erasmus Darwin: Doctor of Evolution?,” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >History,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Humanity,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Evolution:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">for</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">John</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >C.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Greene</hi>, ed. J. R. Moore
                (Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 39–69, and Patricia Fara, “Questions of
                Inheritance: Erasmus and Charles Darwin,” in <hi rend="italic">The Two Darwins</hi>,
                ed. Martin Priestman and Louise Lee, <hi rend="italic">Romanticism on the Net
                </hi>66–7 (2016). Also see Appendix 3.1 and 3.3 which include some instances of
                evolutionary thought in ED’s prose works <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia </hi>(1794–1796;
                1801) and <hi rend="italic">Phytologia </hi>(1800).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">21</hi> Edward Reed, <hi rend="italic">From</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Soul</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Mind:</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Emergence</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Psychology</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">from</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">William</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">James</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Yale
                University Press, 1997), pp. 13–14.</p>
            <p rend="justify"><hi rend="sup">22</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 6.</p>
            <p rend="justify"><hi rend="sup">23</hi> Dyer describes Lewis Paul’s wool-spinning
                machine while Darwin describes Richard Arkwright’s cotton spinning machine. The
                lines from Dyer are as follows:</p>
            <p rend="justify">We next are shown</p>
            <p rend="justify">A circular machine, of new design,</p>
            <p rend="justify">In conic shape: it draws and spins a thread Without the tedious toil
                of needless hands. A wheel, invisible, beneath the floor,</p>
            <p>To ev’ry member of th’ harmonious frame Gives necessary motion. One, intent,
                O’erlooks the work: the carded wool, he says, Is smoothly lapp’d around those
                cylinders, Which, gently turning, yield it to yon cinque Of upright spindles, which,
                with rapid whirl, Spin out, in long extent, an even twine.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">24</hi> Rudolf Beck, “From Industrial Georgic to Industrial Sublime:
                English Poetry and the Early Stages of the Industrial Revolution,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >British</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">for</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Studies</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>27 (2004): pp. 17–36. On industrial georgic
                see also Tobias Menely, “Mine, Factory, and Plantation: The Industrial Georgic and
                the Crisis of Description,” <hi rend="italic">Climate</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Making</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Worlds:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Toward</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Geohistorical</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(University of Chicago Press, 2021), pp.
                127–</p>
            <p>64. For a classic Marxist reading of Darwin’s poetry in the historical context of
                industrialization, see Maureen McNeil, <hi rend="italic">Under the Banner of
                    Science: Erasmus Darwin and his Age </hi>(Manchester University Press,
                1987).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">25</hi> James Venable Logan, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Aesthetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Darwin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1936; repr., Octagon, 1972),
                p. 126.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">26</hi> For insightful and accessible commentary on this and many
                other aspects of Grainger’s text, see <hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic"
                    >Digital</hi><hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic">Grainger:</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#0000ff)italic"> </hi><hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic">An
                    Online Edition of The Sugar-Cane (1764)</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">27</hi> Review of Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Dr.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Review</hi>, Vol. 4, no. 7 (April 1804): pp. 230–41; see pp. 238–39.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">28</hi> This perfect epithet comes from Shaun Irlam’s entry for Young
                in <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Oxford</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">British</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Literature</hi>, ed. David Scott Kastan (Oxford University Press, 2006).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">29</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 37.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">30</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 36.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">31</hi> Logan, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Aesthetics</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 130.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">32</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, Interlude, p. 51.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">33</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi>, Advertisement; ED, <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Plan</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Conduct</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Female</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Education,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Boarding</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Schools</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1797), p. 41.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">34</hi> See, for example, Noel Jackson, “Rhyme and Reason: Erasmus
                Darwin’s Romanticism,” <hi rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly:</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Literary</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">History</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>70.2 (2009): pp. 171–94, and
                Dahlia Porter, “Erasmus Darwin’s Prose of the World: Induction and the Philosophical
                Poem,” in <hi rend="italic">Science, Form, and the Problem of Induction in British
                    Romanticism </hi>(Cambridge University Press, 2018), pp. 73–112.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">35</hi> Porter, “Erasmus Darwin’s Prose of the World,” pp. 74–5,
                92.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">36</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 37.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">37</hi> Priestman, “Didactic and Scientific Poetry,” pp. 402, 419.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">38</hi> Anna Letitia Barbauld, “Essay on Akenside’s Poem on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pleasures of Imagination</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures
                    of Imagination</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">by</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Mark</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Akenside,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">M.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">D.,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">which</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">prefixed</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Critical</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Essay</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">on</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Poem,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">by</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Mrs.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Barbauld</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1794), p. 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">39</hi> Lucretius, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">rerum</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >natura</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>1.936–50, 4.1–25, trans. W.H.D. Rouse, Loeb
                Classical Library.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">40</hi> Barbauld, “Essay on Akenside’s Poem,” p. 3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">41</hi> Barbauld, “Essay on Akenside’s Poem,” pp. 3–4.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">42</hi> Barbauld, “Essay on Akenside’s Poem,” pp. 2–3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">43</hi> Joseph Warton, qtd. in David Duff, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romanticism</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Uses</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Genre</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Oxford
                University Press, 2009), p. 96. In the Advertisement to <hi rend="italic">Odes on
                    Various Subjects </hi>(1746), Warton objects that “the fashion of moralizing in
                verse has been carried too far” and fears that his poems will be found “too fanciful
                and descriptive.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">44</hi> Porter, “Erasmus Darwin’s Prose of the World,” p. 78.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">45</hi> Studies that put Darwin and Knight together include McNeil,
                    <hi rend="italic">Under the Banner of Science</hi>, pp. 39, 54, 116; Priestman,
                    <hi rend="italic">Romantic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Atheism</hi>, pp. 44–79; and Patricia Fara, <hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sex,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Science,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Serendipity</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(Oxford University Press, 2012), pp. 43–63.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">46</hi> “Extracts” from <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Progress</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Man</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>appeared in three issues of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Anti-Jacobin;</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">or,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Weekly</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Examiner</hi>: No. 15, 19 February 1798;
                No. 16, 26 February 1798; and No. 21, 2 April 1798.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">47</hi> Luisa Calè argues that “reactionary propaganda” such as <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Anti-Jacobin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>and Richard Polwhele’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Unsex’d Females
                </hi>(1798) tended to lump ED and Knight together with other figures such as Mary
                Wollstonecraft, William Godwin, and Angelica Kaufmann, as if they were a single
                hydra-headed author. “‘A Female Band despising Nature’s Law’: Botany, Gender and
                Revolution in the 1790s,” <hi rend="italic">Romanticism on the Net </hi>17
                (2000).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">48</hi> Priestman, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 37.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">49</hi> In a letter to his son Robert, dated 17 June 1788, Darwin
                writes, “I intend next year to revise and correct, and enlarge, and perhaps print my
                Zoonomia,” which suggests a full initial draft had already been completed. Darwin
                adds, “At present I am writing notes to the first part of the botanic garden”
                (King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters </hi>88-14).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">50</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, pp. 232, 253.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">51</hi> Anna Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dr.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Chiefly</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >During</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">his</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Residence</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >at</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Lichfield,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">with</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Anecdotes</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">his Friends, and Criticisms on his
                    Writings </hi>(1804), p. 125.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">52</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, pp. 130–31.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">53</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 166.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">54</hi> Edgeworth, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, Vol. 2, p. 267.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">55</hi> King-Hele, ed., Letters 81-11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">56</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>81-11. William Sayle was a college friend of Darwin’s, to
                whom he wrote a poem in 1753, included in <hi rend="italic">Poems of School and
                    University</hi>, ed. Desmond King-Hele and Stuart Harris (Stuart Harris, 2012),
                pp.</p>
            <p>48–50. Sayle published no poetry and does not appear in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oxford</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">National</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Biography</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">57</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>81-11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">58</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>84-10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">59</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>84-10n.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">60</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>84-10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">61</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>84-10n.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">62</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>90-6, 84-10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">63</hi> These are the only additions, but not the only alterations, to
                the illustrations between 1789 and 1790. For full details on changes to the
                illustrations, and to the front matter, from edition to edition, see Appendices 1.1,
                1.2, and 1.5.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">64</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>89-2.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">65</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>84-10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">66</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 131.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">67</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 7.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">68</hi> King-Hele and Harris, eds., <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">School</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">University</hi>, p. 7.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">69</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">London</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                >Magazine</hi>, Vol. 20 (1751): p. 325.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">70</hi> No author name is given in the book. It is sometimes
                attributed to Charles’s teacher, Dr. Andrew Duncan of Edinburgh, but the style
                resembles Darwin’s (King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 143).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">71</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, pp. 165–66; Teresa
                Barnard, <hi rend="italic">Anna</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Seward:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Constructed</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Ashgate, 2009), pp. 118,
                122–23.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">72</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Magazine</hi>, Vol. 55 (1785): p. 641.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">73</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>88-6.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">74</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>75-6.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">75</hi> See King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 401.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">76</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>75-6.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">77</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>75-6.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">78</hi> These poems have been collected in <hi rend="italic"
                    >To</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Elizabeth,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">with</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">love</hi>, ed. Desmond King-Hele (Stuart Harris, 2008).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">79</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>75-7, lines 1–2, 5–8.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">80</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>75-7, lines 11–12.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">81</hi> “Idyllium. The Mother, Radburn Grove,” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >To</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Elizabeth</hi>, ed. King-Hele,
                p. 32.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">82</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>77-7, 78-12.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">83</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>78-12, lines 13-18.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">84</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>78-12, line 76.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">85</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 147.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">86</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 208.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">87</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 136.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">88</hi> There is also a brief description of the garden in C. E.
                Stringer, <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Short</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Account</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ancient</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Modern</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">State of the
                    City and Close of Lichfield </hi>(1819). King-Hele says that Stringer saw the
                garden in person, but does not explain, or say when (<hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p.
                150).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">89</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Part II, Sect. XI.1.3, p. 260.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">90</hi> Paul A. Elliott, <hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gardens:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Medicine,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Agriculture</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sciences</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Eighteenth</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Century</hi></p>
            <p>(Boydell, 2021), pp. 19–32.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">91</hi> He did, however, keep the garden until 1800. It was managed by
                William Jackson, fellow member of the Botanical Society at Lichfield (Elliott, <hi
                    rend="italic">Erasmus Darwin’s Gardens</hi>, pp. 19–20, 30).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">92</hi> Elliott, <hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gardens</hi>, pp. 41, 43, 44.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">93</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>78-3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">94</hi> Jenny Uglow, “Lunar Society of Birmingham,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Oxford</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionary</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">National</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Biography</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(2007; rev. 2017). For a
                full account of the Lunar Society, see Uglow, <hi rend="italic">The Lunar Men
                </hi>(Faber and Faber, 2002).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">95</hi> See Uglow, <hi rend="italic">Lunar</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Men</hi>, pp. 275–79.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">96</hi> Watt to Darwin, 12 May 1779, qtd. in King-Hele, <hi
                    rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 155.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">97</hi> Darwin’s commonplace book is featured online, with selected
                page images, in the British Museum’s <hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic"
                    >Teaching</hi><hi rend="color(#0000ff)italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic">History with 100 Objects</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#0000ff)italic"> </hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">and West Midlands
                    History’s </hi><hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline italic">Revolutionary Players:
                    Making the Modern World</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">. The original is held, on
                    loan from English Heritage, at the Erasmus Darwin House Museum in
                    Lichfield.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">98</hi> Clive Hart, “Erasmus Darwin’s Model Goose,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Aeronautical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>89.881
                (1985): pp. 17–20.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">99</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 187; Erasmus
                Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Commonplace</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Book</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Microform Academic Publishers, 1970), pp.
                109, 112.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">100</hi> For an entertaining account of the revision of the pamphlet
                by Wedgwood’s close friend and business partner Thomas Bentley, and the resulting
                heated contestation over flat versus florid style, see Uglow, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Lunar</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Men</hi>, pp. 112–14.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">101</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 136.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">102</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, pp. 158–59.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">103</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Part II, XI.2.4, p. 271; Plate VII.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">104</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters </hi>83-1;
                King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 197. On the Derby Philosophical Society,
                and for more information about the balloon, see Paul A. Elliott, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Derby</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophers:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Science</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Culture</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">British</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Urban Society, 1700-1850 </hi>(Manchester
                University Press, 2009), pp. 69–85.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">105</hi> See King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, pp. 14, 172–73,
                206.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">106</hi> Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Address</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Society,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Delivered</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">at</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">their</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">first</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Regular</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >meeting,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">held</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">July</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">18, 1784</hi>, pp. xii–xiii. Digitized at Derby Local Studies and
                Family History Library, <ref
                    target="https://emlib.ent.sirsidynix.net.uk/client/en_GB/search/asset/242/0"><hi
                        rend="color(#0000ff)underline"
                        >https://emlib.ent.sirsidynix.net.uk/client/en_GB/search/asset/242/0</hi><hi
                        rend="color(#000000)">.</hi></ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">107</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Address</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Society</hi>, p. xiii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">108</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Address</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Society</hi>, p. xiii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">109</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 98.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">110</hi> Elliott, <hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gardens</hi>, p. 25.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">111</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 61.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">112</hi> C. Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, p. 47.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">113</hi> Joseph Wright of Derby, <hi rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Brooke</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Boothby</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1781), Tate, <ptr
                    target="https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/wright-sir-"/><hi
                    rend="color(#0000ff)underline">brooke-boothby-n04132</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)">.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">114</hi> Janet Browne, “Botany in the Boudoir and Garden: The Banksian
                Context,” <hi rend="italic">Visions</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Empire:</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Voyages,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Botany and Representations of Nature</hi>, ed. David Philip Miller and Peter
                Hanns Reill (Cambridge University Press, 1996),</p>
            <p>p. 165; Jacques Zonneveld, <hi rend="italic">Sir Brooke Boothby: Rousseau’s Roving
                    Baronet Friend </hi>(Voorburg 2004), p. 126, quoted in Stephen Leach, “Good
                Monsieur Melancholy: Joseph Wright’s <hi rend="italic">Portrait</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sir</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Brooke</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Boothby,</hi>” <hi rend="italic">British
                    Art Journal </hi>15.1 (2014): p. 111.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">115</hi> Brooke Boothby, “Sonnet IV,” p. 10; “The First Satire of the
                First Book of Horace Imitated. To Erasmus Darwin,</p>
            <p>M. D.,” in <hi rend="italic">Sorrows.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sacred</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Memory</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Penelope</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(1796), pp.
                66–72.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">116</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 151; Fara, <hi
                    rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin</hi>,
                p. 73.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">117</hi> W. Jackson, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Beauties</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1769), p. 41.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">118</hi> Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Beauties</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nature</hi>, pp. 37–9.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">119</hi> Jackson, <hi rend="italic">Beauties</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nature</hi>, pp. 39–40.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">120</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, pp. 98–9.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">121</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Magazine</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>68 (1798): p. 730, qtd. in Elliott, <hi
                    rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Gardens</hi>, p. 26.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">122</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 179.</p>
            <p rend="justify"><hi rend="sup">123</hi> For a full discussion of Darwin’s translation
                principles, see Tristanne Connolly, “‘Mistaken for Natives of the Soil’: Translation
                and Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Loves</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Plants,</hi>” <hi rend="italic"
                    >British</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Romanticism</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">European</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Perspective</hi>, ed. Steve Clark and Tristanne Connolly (Palgrave, 2015), pp.
                133–54.</p>
            <p rend="justify"><hi rend="sup">124</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>81-8, 81-13, 81-6, cf. 81-5, 81-10.</p>
            <p rend="justify"><hi rend="sup">125</hi> Seward, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, pp.
                76–77; <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >System</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. xi; see also King-Hele,
                ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>81-8.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">126</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>81-5, 81-8, 81-11, 81-12, 82-2, and 82-3.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">127</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. iv.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">128</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>81-8, 81-9; <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, pp.
                vi–x.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">129</hi> King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, pp. 181–82.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">130</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. ii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">131</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. v.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">132</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. iii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">133</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. iii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">134</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, pp. xiv–xl, 26–49.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">135</hi> Transcribed from Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commonplace</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, p. 72. Cf.
                quotation in King-Hele, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 150.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">136</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Commonplace</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, pp. 72–3; see also p. 116.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">137</hi> King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>81-11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">138</hi> Ann B. Shteir, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Women</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Cultivating</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Science</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Johns Hopkins, 1996), pp. 2, 4.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">139</hi> Shteir, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Women</hi>, p. 151.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">140</hi> Shteir, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Women</hi>, p. 157.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">141</hi> Thomas Martyn, <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Botany.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Addressed</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lady.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">By</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Celebrated</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >J.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">J.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Rousseau.</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Translated</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">into English, with
                    Notes, and Twenty-Four Additional Letters, Fully Explaining the System of
                    Linnæus </hi>(1785), p. v.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">142</hi> William Withering, <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanical</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Arrangement</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vegetables</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Naturally</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Growing</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Great</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Britain</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1776), Vol. 1, p. v.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">143</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vegetables</hi>, Vol. 1, p. xi.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">144</hi> See King-Hele, ed., <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>82-3. For more information on Blackburne, see V. P.
                Wystrach, “Anna Blackburne (1726–1793) – a neglected patroness of natural history,”
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society for the Bibliography of Natural
                    History</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>8.2 (1977): pp. 148–68. James Bolton,
                naturalist and illustrator, created a series of drawings of specimens from her
                natural history cabinet in 1768, now held at the Yale Center for British Art, and
                digitized at <hi rend="color(#0000ff)underline"
                    >https://collections.britishart.yale.edu/catalog/orbis:11411486</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)">.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">145</hi> An important study of ED’s relationship to the capitalist and
                imperialist uses of plants is Alan Bewell, “Erasmus Darwin’s Cosmopolitan Nature,”
                    <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>76 (2009): pp. 19–48. See also
                the thoughtful rebuttal in Lisa Ann Robertson, “‘Kindred Forms’: Erasmus Darwin’s
                Posthuman Ethics of Relationality,” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review
                </hi>32.5–6 (2021): pp. 551–66.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">146</hi> Linnaeus, <hi rend="italic">Philosophia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanica</hi>, section 151, referenced in Alexandra
                Cook, <hi rend="italic">Jean-Jacques</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Rousseau</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and Botany: The Salutary
                    Science </hi>(Voltaire Foundation, 2012), p. 163.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">147</hi> Linnaeus, “Ordines Naturales (Natural Orders),” translated by
                Darwin as part of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Families</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Plants</hi>, Vol. 2,</p>
            <p>p. 770.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">148</hi> For this point, and an excellent overview of the relationship
                and history of the artificial sexual system and the natural method, see Cook, <hi
                    rend="italic">Rousseau and Botany</hi>, pp. 158–67, 173–82.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">149</hi> Linnaeus, “Ordines Naturales (Natural Orders),” <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Families</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Plants</hi>, Vol. 2, p. 770.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">150</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Part III, XX.1, p. 565.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">151</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Part III, XX.1, p. 566.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">152</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>XX.3, p. 670. For discussion of <hi rend="italic">LOTP</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>in the context of the Linnaean and natural systems, see Sophie
                Laniel-Musitelli, “<hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Loves</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Plants</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>d’Erasmus Darwin: enjeux
                d’écriture et de traduction,” <hi rend="italic">Littérature française et savoirs
                    biologiques au XIXe siècle: Traduction, transmission, transposition, </hi>ed.
                Thomas Klinkert and Gisèle Séginger (DeGruyter, 2020), pp. 17–30.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">153</hi> John Lindley, <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Natural</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >System</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Botany</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(2nd ed., 1836),
                referenced in Cook, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Botany</hi>, p.
                158.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">154</hi> Shteir, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Women</hi>, p. 31.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">155</hi> For a full history of sex in plants, see Lincoln Taiz and Lee
                Taiz, <hi rend="italic">Flora</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Unveiled</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Oxford University Press, 2017).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">156</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannica;</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">or,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Dictionary</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Arts</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Sciences</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>(1771), Vol. 1, p. 653.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">157</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannica</hi>, Vol. 1, p. 653.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">158</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannica</hi>, Vol. 1, p. 653.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">159</hi> George, <hi rend="italic">Botany,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Sexuality</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Women’s</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Writing</hi>, p. 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">160</hi> Richard Polwhele, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Unsex’d</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Females:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poem,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Addressed</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Author</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pursuits</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Literature</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1798),</p>
            <p>pp. 8–9.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">161</hi> List, “Sometimes a Stamen is Only a Stamen.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">162</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Monthly</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Review</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>24 (1797): p. 219, qtd. in List, “Sometimes
                a Stamen is Only a Stamen,” p. 207.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">163</hi> For instance, Alan Bewell, “‘Jacobin Plants’: Botany as
                Social Theory in the 1790s,” <hi rend="italic">Wordsworth</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Circle</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>20.3 (1989): pp.
                132–39, and Fredrika J. Teute, “The Loves of the Plants; or, the Cross-Fertilization
                of Science and Desire at the End of the Eighteenth Century,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Huntington Library Quarterly </hi>63.3 (2000): pp. 319–45.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">164</hi> For instance, Janet Browne, “Botany for Gentlemen: Erasmus
                Darwin and ‘The Loves of the Plants,’” <hi rend="italic">Isis </hi>80.4 (1989): pp.
                593–621, and Elizabeth Heckendorn Cook, “‘Perfect’ Flowers, Monstrous Women:
                Eighteenth-Century Botany and the Modern Gendered Subject,” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Defects: Engendering the Modern Body</hi>, ed. Helen Deutsch and Felicity
                Nussbaum (University of Michigan Press, 2000), pp. 253–79.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">165</hi> Shteir, <hi rend="italic">Cultivating Women, </hi>p. 16;
                Londa L. Schiebinger, <hi rend="italic">Nature’s Body: Gender in the Making of
                    Modern Science</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Beacon, 1993), p. 17. On the
                limitations of this argument, see Cook, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Botany</hi>, pp. 166–67.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">166</hi> Walpole, To Mary and Agnes Berry, 28 April 1789, p. 11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">167</hi> For a persuasive queer reading of <hi rend="italic"
                >LOTP</hi>, see Elizabeth Bernath, “‘Seeking Flowers to Comfort Her’: Queer Botany
                in Blake’s <hi rend="italic">Visions</hi>, Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Loves</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>and Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="italic">Rights</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Woman,</hi>” in <hi rend="italic">Blake,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Gender</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Culture</hi>, ed. Helen P.
                Bruder and Tristanne Connolly (Pickering &amp; Chatto, 2012), pp. 111–22.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">168</hi> Maja Bondestam, “When The Plant Kingdom Became Queer: On
                Hermaphrodites and the Linnaean Language of Nonnormative Sex,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Illdisciplined Nature, </hi>ed. Jacob Bull and Margaretha Fahlgren (Springer,
                2016), pp. 7, 121, 124.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">169</hi> M.M. Mahood, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Poet</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >as</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanist</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(Cambridge University Press, 2008), pp. 59–60.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">170</hi> Mahood, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Poet</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">as</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanist</hi>, p. 59.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">171</hi> Wordsworth, Preface to <hi rend="italic">Lyrical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ballads</hi>, p. 597.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">172</hi> Wordsworth, Preface to <hi rend="italic">Lyrical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ballads</hi>, p. 600; Catherine Packham,
                “The Science and Poetry of Animation: Personification, Analogy, and Erasmus Darwin’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Loves of the Plants,</hi>” <hi rend="italic">Romanticism
                </hi>10.2 (2004): p. 197.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">173</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Economy</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetation</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(1791) I:529n. For commentary on this passage in relation to climate change
                and ED’s reception, see Siobhan Carrol, “On Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">The
                    Botanic Garden, 1791–1792,</hi>” <hi rend="italic">BRANCH: Britain,
                    Representation, and Nineteenth-Century History</hi>, ed. Dino Franco Felluga
                (April 2016).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">174</hi> Donna Coffey, “Protecting the Botanic Garden: Seward, Darwin,
                and Coalbrookdale,” <hi rend="italic">Women’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Studies:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">An
                    Interdisciplinary Journal </hi>31.2 (2002): p. 147.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">175</hi> Examples include Seth T. Reno, “Rethinking the Romantics’
                Love of Nature,” in <hi rend="italic">Wordsworth and the Green Romantics:</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Affect</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ecology</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nineteenth</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Century</hi>, ed. Lisa
                Ottum, Seth T. Reno, and James C. McCusick (University of New Hampshire Press,
                2016), pp. 28–58; Robertson, “‘Kindred Forms’: Erasmus Darwin’s Posthuman Ethics of
                Relationality”; and Amanda Jo Goldstein, “Utopian Pastoral and the Inhuman Trade,”
                    <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Political Ecology, </hi>ed. Kir Kuiken, <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis Series </hi>(February 2004).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">176</hi> Komisaruk and Dushane, eds., <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Botanic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Garden</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">by</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Darwin</hi>, Vol. 1, p. 16.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">177</hi> Hannah More, Letter to Horace Walpole, April 1789, in <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Yale</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Edition</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Horace</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Walpole’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>, Vol. 31, p. 295.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">178</hi> Richard Polwhele, review of Gilbert Wakefield’s translation
                of Lucretius, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Anti-Jacobin</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Review</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">and Magazine</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>(March 1800), p. 255. D. M. Moir would express a similar opinion in 1818 (see
                Appendix 5.20).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">179</hi> Wordsworth, Preface to <hi rend="italic">Lyrical</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Ballads</hi>, 600.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">180</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Section XIX.7, p. 558 (see Appendix 3.4).</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">181</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Temple</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Nature</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>IV:83–8.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">182</hi> Robertson emphasizes sympathy as part of her argument that
                Darwin advocates humans “seeing themselves as part of, rather than apart from,
                nature”. She finds that, in <hi rend="italic">The Temple of Nature</hi>, Darwin
                “connects the lack of sympathy in human society to speciesism.” Robertson, “‘Kindred
                Forms’: Erasmus Darwin’s Posthuman Ethics of Relationality,” pp. 552, 562.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">183</hi> Denise Gigante, <hi rend="italic">Life: Organic Form and
                    Romanticism </hi>(Yale University Press, 2009), p. 45. Gigante draws on Peter
                Hanns Reill who considers “analogical reasoning and comparative analysis” to be the
                two methods that answered the call of “Enlightenment vitalists” for “a harmonic
                conjunction that recognized both nature’s unity and diversity”. Reill, <hi
                    rend="italic">Vitalizing Nature in the Enlightenment </hi>(University of
                California Press, 2005), p. 8.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">184</hi> Walpole, Letter to Mary and Agnes Berry, 28 April 1789, p.
                11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">185</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Economy</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Vegetation</hi>, Additional Note XXXIX, p.
                111.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">186</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Phytologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>Part III, XIX.7.3, pp. 559–60.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">187</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Temple</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi><hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>IV:447–50.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">188</hi> Richard Lovell Edgeworth, Letter to Walter Scott (1812), in
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Richard</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi><hi rend="italic">Lovell</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Edgeworth,</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Esq.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Begun by Himself and Concluded by his
                    Daughter, Maria Edgeworth </hi>(1820), Vol. 2, p. 267.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">189</hi> Donald M. Hassler, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Comedian</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">as</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Letter</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">D:</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Erasmus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Darwin’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Comic</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Materialism</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Martinus Nijhoff, 1973), p. 22.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">190</hi> Darwin, <hi rend="italic">Zoonomia</hi>, III.1.2.11, pp. 372,
                374.</p>
            <p><hi rend="sup">191</hi> Walpole, Letter to Mary and Agnes Berry, 28 April 1789, p.
                11.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
