<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3833" type="letter">
            <head>3833. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-05-07">7 May
                  1822</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: Miss Southey/ Hatterleys Hotel/ Harrowgate<lb/>Stamped: WETHERBY/ 194<lb/>MS: Private collection. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                     from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 305–306.</note></head>


            <opener><dateline><address>
                     <placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName>
                  </address>, <date when="1822-05-07">May 7. 1822.</date></dateline>
               <salute>My dear E. May,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Fortune I think has fitted you with a Physician<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Jacques (d. 1832), a
                  doctor based in Harrogate.</note> to your taste. He has <hi rend="ital">tabooed</hi> ham, vinegar, red–herring &#38; all fruits. But
               if the melancholy Jaques<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Melancholy Jaques’, a character in <title>As You Like It</title>
                  (1599).</note> were not a heretic he would <del>not</del> &#60;never&#62; have put you to a trial so far beyond the strength of woman. If Eve when she had
               the choice of the whole garden besides (a garden too as rich in fruits as William Herbert’s,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >William Herbert (1778–1847; <title>DNB</title>). He abandoned a career in politics and the law for the Church of England, serving
                  as Rector of Spofforth, near Wetherby, 1814–1840, and Dean of Manchester 1840–1847. Herbert was also a poet and a noted writer on
                  botany. His garden at the Old Rectory, Spofforth, was well known and the site of Herbert’s development of the Spofforth
                  crocus.</note> which you have been visiting, is in flowers), could not refrain from the forbidden apple,<note n="4" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title> 3, Eve, the first woman, was tempted to eat the forbidden fruit of the Tree of the
                  Knowledge of Good and Evil. The fruit was usually identified as an apple.</note> how does he suppose that a daughter of Eve can
               resist strawberries, cherries &#38; currants, to say nothing of green gooseberries &#38; hard pears?</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Your second letter arrived to day, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> has it at
               M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Calvert’s,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (c. 1775–1834), née Mitchinson, the wife of William Calvert.</note>
               whither she is gone for the remainder of the week. I have not much to tell you, – the boat is in the water, &#38; looks very well; – the
                  pew<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southey family’s pew at St Kentigern’s church, Crosthwaite.</note> was painted
               yesterday; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">your uncle Tom</ref> has lost a cow, in calf–bed, sundry rats have been taken,
               I expect a parcel by the next carrier, &#38; your plant is as well as can be expected, whereby you will understand that there is an
               addition to its leaves. But this new <del>xxxx</del> leaf has been produced in a curious manner, – the stem proceeding from the base of the youngest &#38;
               largest of its three ancestors, &#38; all the folded part from the mother, or middle one, so that its genealogy is more puzzling than the
               relationship between Dick &#38; John.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Dick and John’ were commonly used for fictional characters,
                  including by Southey himself in his Botany Bay Eclogue, ‘John, Samuel, &#38; Richard’, <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp.
                  92–98.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am glad you take so kindly to the waters, &#38; that they seem to agree with you so well. What a happy quarter of an
               hour you must pass between the two draughts!</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I had forgotten to tell you, as part of the domestic news, that I have laid hands, since
                  your departure, upon a larger &#38; richer picture of Muckens<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Cuthbert Southey’s pronunciation of
                  ‘monkeys’.</note> than any which <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> had ever seen before. Having
               told you all that has happened, I believe I must now tell you what has not. <hi rend="ital">Pone</hi><note n="9" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> is not gone; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Midgeley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Midgeley (first name and dates
                  unknown) was renting Greta Lodge, next door to Greta Hall.</note> is not come. Miss Wilbraham<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799–1874), Tom Southey’s lodger.</note> is not married, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friar<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777–1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. A surveyor, geologist and mining engineer, Fryer spent part of
                  each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick. He married
                  Mary Laetitia Wilbraham in June 1822.</note> is not false, &#38; a she–Friar will not be the same thing as a Nun. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Potts<note n="13"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> has made no proposals to Mary Calvert, (by the by, if he has ever any children, they will
                  all be pipkins);<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (1804–1890) was the daughter of William Calvert. She married Joshua Stanger (1801–1854) in 1824. A ‘pipkin’ is a small cooking pot. Southey is joking that if Mr Potts was ever to marry his children would be small Potts.</note> Sara has had no letter from Wiffin;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"
                     >Jeremiah Holmes Wiffen (1792–1836; <hi rend="ital">DNB</hi>), poet and writer. He had met Southey and Wordsworth in the Lake District in summer 1819. In 1821 he was appointed librarian to John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766–1839; <hi rend="ital">DNB</hi>). At the time of Southey's letter, Wiffen was engaged in translating Torquato Tasso (1544–1595), <hi rend="ital">Gerusalemme Liberata</hi> (1591). His translation was published as <hi rend="ital">The Jerusalem Delivered of Torquato Tasso, translated in English Spenserian verse, with a Life of the Author</hi> (1824).</note> <del>&#38;</del> I have not yet heard from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford.</note> <del>&#38;</del> <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your mother</ref>, notwithstanding her persevering search has not found anything under
                  the bed at night, – &#38; I am neither younger, nor fatter, nor quieter, nor graver, than when you departed for Harrogate. O ye immortal
                  Powers!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Addison (1672–1719; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Cato, a Tragedy</title>
                  (1712), Act 5, scene 3, line 9.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I would send you a noise, but I cannot tell how to inclose it: – but you may imagine one at breakfast time.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My movements will be determined by yours. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref>
               goes with me, we shall travel in a jaunting car, which will bring us all back. If I go alone, I shall follow your course to Skipton &#38;
               chaise it solo from thence, which will be better than taking the Penrith road, &#38; sleeping the second night at Borough Bridge. I
               do not wish to be more than three days at Harrogate at the most.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss H.</ref> &#38; <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HutchinsonJoanna">her sister</ref>,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Joanna Hutchinson
                     (1780–1841).</note> &#38; so</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you,</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3"> Very magnificent daughter,</salute>
               <signed rend="indent4">Yo el Pa.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
