<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4206" type="letter">
            <head>4206. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">[John May]</ref>], <date when="1824-06-27">[c. 27 June
                  1824] </date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: <hi rend="ital">No</hi> 238/ Copied [Michigan State MS, see below]; N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 238 [1824/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 27<hi
                     rend="sup">th</hi> June/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Jule/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Oct. [Harry Ransom MS, see below].<lb/> MS: At some point in its history the letter was separated into two parts, which are now split between two archives. The first part (everything from ‘Keswick. 27 June. 1824’ to the closing signature) is tipped into the first volume of a copy of Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824) that once belonged to John Coleridge Frampton May (1837-1902) and is now in Stephen O. Murray and Keelung Hong Special Collections, Michigan State University Libraries, XX BX5055.S7 1824. ALS; 4p. The second part (everything after the signature) is in the Robert Southey Collection, Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin. AL; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: The section of the manuscript now in Michigan State has never been published. The section of manuscript in the Harry Ransom Center appeared in John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 429–430.</note></head>

            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-06-27">27 June. 1824</date></dateline>
               
               <salute>My dear friend</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I was truly glad to hear from you once more, after so long a silence. You must be much better informed than I can possibly be, with the state of affairs in Brazil; as far as I can judge, the aspects are more favourable than they were, both there &#38; in Portugal. Both the Emp. of Brazil<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter I (1798–1834; Emperor of Brazil 1822–1831 and King of Portugal March–May 1826). He had put himself at the head of the movement for Brazilian independence from Portugal and had defeated Portuguese forces in Brazil in 1822–1824.</note> &#38; his brother D Miguel<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael I (1802–1866; King of Portugal 1828–1834), younger brother of Peter I. In May 1824 he had been exiled to Vienna after attempting to seize power in Portugal.</note> appear to be great brutes &#38; blackguards, – &#38; yet to possess a certain strength of character which may work off the bad matter.  Of the former I have heard that one of his royal recreations was to ride a negro with spurs.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">He has however acted with vigour, &#38; if he can content himself with Brazil, giving up all hope of uniting the two countries under one government, I think he may hold it, by help of his fleet, &#38; by making it the interest of the Representatives<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter I had summoned a Constituent Assembly in May 1823 to draft a new constitution for Brazil, but dissolved this body in November 1823 and produced his own constitution in March 1824.</note> to support him, – I mean bestowing an hundredth part of the money in buying them, which it would cost to suppress a revolt. He must govern by iron or by gold, till the people are in a state to be ruled by reason. The golden system is the cheapest &#38; the best.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">This ought to be his policy. The K of Portugal<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826), father of Peter I and Michael I. In 1823 he had abolished the liberal Constitution and Cortes in Portugal created by the revolution of 1820 and promised to restore the form of the old Cortes, which had last met in 1698 and consisted of the three orders of nobility, Church and representatives of the towns.</note> is now pursuing what is his true course. Reviving the old Cortes, &#38; with the old forms, preparing I trust to bring back the realities of justice. I have long been clearly of opinion that in Sp. &#38; P. the true mode of reforming government, is to do this: &#38; to pass a Habeas Corpus act.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Habeas Corpus Act (1679) prevented detention without trial.</note> They are not ripe for any thing farther.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">In my judgement your concerns as far as they depend upon political movements ought to be more promising than they were. How heartily should I rejoice to hear that you were freed from this long &#38; painful anxiety <del>axxxxt</del> &#60;but&#62; I never can forgive your brother<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William May (1785–1849), John May’s younger brother, was in charge of the family’s business interests in Brazil, which were in dire trouble.</note> for having involved you in it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Toms</ref> subscription<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was collecting subscriptions for his brother’s proposed <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> is coming on prosperously. He has very nearly half the number required, &#38; good hope from other quarters which have not yet sent in their returns</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Poor M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Tonkin<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Tonkin, nee Windsor (d. 1824), widow of the Lisbon merchant William Tonkin (dates unknown). Southey had first met Mrs Tonkin on his trip to Portugal in 1796 and had become a close friend of her and her children.</note> – but why should I say <hi rend="ital">poor</hi>? – when I verily believe that if suicide were held allowable by Christian principles not half so many persons would reach threescore &#38; ten, as now drag about the burthen of old age. The worst of all calamities is that of living too long.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I send you herewith the fruits of a good resolution which if I can keep up to it, will bring my task to an end within a reasonable time.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John May, 27 May–26 June 1824, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Seven</title>, Letter 4191.</note> – It will be a good post–obit, &#38; ought to be worth 2000£, – 1500 would readily be offered for it.  You are aware that I make a transcript which will be found in a state fit for the press.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Before I left London <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offered me 700£ for the B of the Church,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> which I refused, telling him he must well know that of &#60;all&#62; the authors with whom he was concerned, I was the one whom, all circumstances considered, he had hitherto paid the worst, – a fact too palpable for him to deny. – When I tell you that he had originally offered me &#60;500£&#62; for this very book in one small volume – that is – not more than one third of its present extent, – you will see that I had reason to refuse his proposal, &#38; to feel more resentment than I expressed.</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">He promised to write to me concerning some plans which we had long talked of – but I have only had two lines from him since my return, – &#38; those to say he had sent a second edition to press.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to [John Murray], 24 April 1824, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Seven</title>, Letter 4176.</note> – I have drawn upon him meantime to the amount of 310£, –  my half profits upon the first edition ought to be more than this – but I do not yet know what number he printed. For Wesley<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> (an edition of 1500) I had 400£. But of the after editions of the B C. I <del>x</del> am to have <hi rend="ital">two thirds</hi>.</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">Thus the matter stands at present.</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">The first sheet of my second vol. of the P. War<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> is lying before me. It will be published in the winter, – &#38; the payment as soon as I receive it shall be forthwith transferred to you. And I shall have no need to make any drawbacks from it.</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">God bless you –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">Yrs affectionately</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>

  <postscript>
     <p rend="indent1"> I had nearly forgotten to answer your question concerning the books which elucidate our Eccl. History.<note n="14"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">Southey goes on to list his sources for <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> The two
               works which profess <del>that</del> to embrace that subject exclusively are Fullers,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                  Fuller (1607/8–1661; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Church-History of Britain: from the Birth of Jesus Christ until the Year
                     MDCXLVIII, with the History of the University of Cambridge and of Waltham-abby in Essex, Founded by King Harold</title> (1655),
                  no. 1190 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Oxford University Press did publish a new edition, edited by John Sherren
                  Brewer (1810–1879; <title>DNB</title>), but not until 1845.</note> &#38; Jeremy Collier’s.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Jeremy Collier (1650–1726; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ecclesiastical History of Great Britain, Chiefly of England: from the
                     First Planting of Christianity, to the End of the Reign of Charles the Second</title> (1708–1714). Collier was a High Churchman
                  and refused to accept the Revolution of 1688, eventually becoming a non-juring bishop in 1713.</note> The first will I hope be
               reprinted at the Clarendon Press, for with all its manifold imperfections it contains much matter for which no other authority can now
               be found the record of the Convocation<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The Convocations of Canterbury and York were the
                  assemblies of bishops and clergy of the two Provinces of the Church of England. They approved revisions to canon law and agreed to
                  taxes on the clergy, but their meetings had been formalities since 1717. Their proceedings can be gleaned from medieval archbishops’
                  registers and Southey could have consulted David Wilkins (1685–1745; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Concilia Magnae Britanniae et
                     Hiberniae a Synodo Verolamiensi A.D. 446 ad Londinensam A.D. 1717</title> (1737).</note> having been destroyed. &#38; it has
               moreover all the inimitable charm of Fullers manner. – Collier is coarse &#38; clumsy – - a bigot – on the right side. – It was
               necessary that I should have both at hand, but you would find upon investigation that I have drawn my materials from other sources,
               Collier’s never lay open before me, – &#38; Fuller’s I believe only in the reign of James I.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >James VI and I (1567–1625; King of Great Britain 1603–1625; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> For facts relating to the history of the Church the most common books are Kennetts Parochial Antiquities, &#38; his
               Case of Impropriations.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">White Kennett (1660–1728; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Parochial
                     Antiquities Attempted in the History of Ambrosden, Burcester and Other Adjacent Parts in the Counties of Oxford and Bucks, with a
                     Glossary of Obsolete Terms</title> (1695) and <title>The Case of Impropriations, and of the Augmentations of Vicarages and Other
                     Insufficient Cures, Stated by History and Law</title> (1704), no. 1553 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> H
               Wharton Defence of Pluralities.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Wharton (1664–1695; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Defence
                     of Pluralities, or Holding Two Benefices with Cure of Souls as now Practised in the Church of England</title> (1692).</note>
               Stavelys History of Churches.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Staveley (1626–1684; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     History of Churches in England</title> (1712), no. 2737 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Bede<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Bede (672/673–735; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Historia Ecclesiastica
                     Gentis Anglorum</title> (c. 731).</note> &#38; the Acta Sanctorum<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The massive, 53-volume,
                  compendium of hagiographies, entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note> were my resources for the early history – with W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> of Malmesbury.<note n="24" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">William of Malmesbury (c. 1095–c. 1143; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gesta Pontificum Anglorum</title>
               (1125).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> To my sorrow I had no original authorities for the life of Becket,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">St Thomas
                  Becket (1119/1120–1170; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1162–1170.</note> except such as were in the App. to Ld
               Lyttletons history.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">George Lyttelton, 1st Baron Lyttelton (1709–1773; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>The History of the Life of King Henry the Second, and of the Age in Which he Lived</title>, 5 vols (London, 1769–1771),
                  IV, pp. 413–521, no. 1771 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Berrington<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Joseph Berington (1743–1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Reign of Henry the Second, and of Richard and John, his
                     Sons; With the Events of the Period, from 1154 to 1216. In which the Character of Thomas a Becket is Vindicated from the Attacks
                     of George Lord Lyttelton </title>(1790).</note> is the best historian of those times, – indeed much the fairest of all the
               English Romanists in his writings</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> We come now to Lewis’s <del>Life</del> Lives of Wicliffe &#38; of Bp Pecock<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >John Lewis (1675–1747; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Life and Sufferings of the Reverend and Learned John Wiclif,
                     D.D. Together with a Collection of Papers Relating to the Said History</title> (1720) and <title>The Life of the Learned and
                     Right Reverend Reynold Pecock S.T.P. Lord Bishop of St Asaph and Chichester, in the Reign of King Henry VI. Faithfully Collected
                     from Records and MSS. Being a Sequel of the Life of Dr. John Wiclif, In order to An Introduction to the History of the English
                     Reformation</title> (1744), no. 1719 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – I had also Baber’s Life of Wiclif
               prefixed to his New Testament<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hervey Baber (1775–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     New Testament, Translated from the Latin in the Year 1380 by John Wiclif: to which are Prefixed, Memoirs of the Life, Opinions,
                     and Writings of Dr Wiclif, and an Historical Account of the Saxon and English Versions of the Scriptures, Previous to the Opening
                     of the Fifteenth Century</title> (1810), no. 2849 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – &#38; Fox’s Martyrs.<note
                  n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">John Foxe (c. 1516–1587; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Acts and Monuments most Special and
                     Memorable happening to the Church</title>, 9th edition (1684), no. 975 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Then came the whole series of Strypes laborious compilations,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">John Strype
                  (1643–1737; <title>DNB</title>), whose lives of sixteenth-century divines were important sources for church history. Southey
                  acquired the twenty-three-volume Clarendon Press edition of Strype’s <title>Works</title> (1816–1824), no. 2753 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – in which I believe nothing has escaped me, tho in this work I have not made use of the 50th
               part of my references to them. – Fox. Burnett.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>History of the Reformation of the Church of England</title> (1679–1714), no. 477 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note>
               <del>th</del>
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworths</ref> Ecc. Biography.<note n="33"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Wordsworth, <title>Ecclesiastical Biography; or, Lives of Eminent Men, Connected with the
                     History of the Church of England; from the Commencement of the Reformation to the Revolution; Selected and Illustrated with
                     Notes</title> (1810), no. 3041 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Rushworth &#38; Nalson<note n="34" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">John Rushworth (1612–1690; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Historical Collections of Private Passages of State
                  </title>(1659–1721) and John Nalson (1637–1686; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Impartial Collection of the Great Affairs of State,
                     from the Beginnings of the Scotch Rebellion in the Year MDCXXXIX to the Murther of King Charles I</title> (1682–1683), no. 1924
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – (the former I must observe is <hi rend="ital">not</hi> known as he deserves to
               be for a great rogue, – but he has perfectly convinced me that a writer may deserve to be punished as severely for his sins of
               omission, as for direct falsehood.) All the lives of Laud<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">William Laud (1573–1645;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1633–1645. Southey possessed Peter Heylin (1599–1662; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Cypriana Anglicus; or, the History of the Life and Death of William Laud</title> (1671), no. 1224 in the sale catalogue of
                  his library, and Henry Wharton (1664–1695; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Troubles and Tryal of the Most Reverend
                     Father in God and Blessed Martyr, William Laud, Lord Arch-Bishop of Canterbury</title> (1695–1700), no. 1673 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library.</note> – Hackets Life of Ab Williams<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hacket (1592–1670;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Scrinia Reserata: a Memorial Offer’d to the Great Deservings of John Williams, D.D.</title> (1693),
                  no. 1211 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was a biography of John Williams (1582–1650; <title>DNB</title>),
                  Archbishop of York 1641–1650.</note> – a much more important book (in spite of its odd, but very amusing stile) than it is generally
               known to be. A great deal has been drawn from Tracts published during the Civil Wars, – of which I found a rich collection at <ref
                  type="m" target="places.html#Lowtherestate">Lowther</ref>. – In short from all histories, <del>biograph</del> memoirs, &#38;c of all
               parties on which I could lay hands. And I need <del>x</del> not tell you that my previous knowledge of monastic history was of ‘great
               use.’</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Every body has cried out for references. I will give them as I find leisure for doing it, in some future edition: &#38;
               I will do for this reason, that when the references are given, the reader who <del>xxx</del> is diligent enough to refer to them, may
               see how faithfully I have f<del>ollowed</del> &#60;represented&#62; the facts &#38; how completely the composition is my own. </p>
  </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
