<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="892.1" type="letter"><head>892.1 Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1804-02-01">1 February 1804</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: held in the autograph album of Matilda Blanche Gibbs at Tyntesfield, N. Somerset (National Trust), described in the NT CMS as item 27411.143<lb/>
                  Unpublished</note></head>
            
            <opener><dateline><date when="1804-02-01">Wednesday Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1. 1804.</date></dateline>
               
               <salute>My dear friend</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am harrassed &#38; distressed by letters from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &#38; have none to apply to in my turn but to you. the ten pounds which you were to have sent on the 17 (by your last letter) he has not received. – you know I believe that he borrowed the money for admission to the various lectures, &#38; he is also a fortnight in arrears for lodging &#38; board.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey was studying medicine at the University of Edinburgh.</note> if therefore you have not sent the ten will it not be better to double the sum? I will write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> by the next mail pressingly upon this subject. in the summer Harry will be at no expence<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey spent much of the summer as Southey’s guest at Greta Hall. See Robert Southey to John May, 19 July 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 967.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I would have sent him an immediate supply if I had had money in the house. desire him when he acknowledges your letter to send you a statement of what monies he has received since at Edinburgh, &#38; from whom, &#38; what debts he has to pay out of the sum you send. this will be satisfactory, &#38; may operate as a check. not &#60;that&#62; there is any reason to suspect him of present extravagance, but it is well to multiply checks, knowing his disposition.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">There is nothing in this world which I covet except that of having happy <del>connec</del> family connections – mine have been to me one unceasing source of uneasiness. I have now no time for more – else I have some speculations designed for you – <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to the literary plans set out in Robert Southey to John May, 23 February 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 901. This letter outlined Southey’s intentions for <title>Madoc</title> (1805), <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807) and his unfinished ‘History of Portugal.’</note> God bless you.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">yrs very affectionately</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2">R Southey.</signed></closer></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
