<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1805: Preface</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB05-1_PREF</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="PREF">
                  <title>[PREF]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB05-1">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB05-1.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1805</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">v to lxiv</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">64</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <head>PREFACE. </head>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <p>T<hi>he</hi> first Volume of these Poems has already <lb/>been submitted
                              to general perusal. It was pub-<lb/>lished, as an experiment, which, I
                              hoped, might <lb/>be of some use to ascertain, how far, by fitting
                              <lb/>to metrical arrangement a selection of the real <lb/>language of
                              men in a state of vivid sensation, <lb/>that sort of pleasure and that
                              quantity of pleasure <lb/>may be imparted, which a Poet may rationally
                              <lb/>endeavour to impart.</p>
         <p>I had formed no very inaccurate estimate of the <lb/>probable effect of
                              those Poems : I flattered myself<pb n="ii"/>
            <milestone n="ii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>that they who should be pleased with them
                              would <lb/>read them with more than common pleasure : <lb/>and, on the
                              other hand, I was well aware, that by <lb/>those who should dislike
                              them they would be read <lb/>with more than common dislike. The result
                              has <lb/>differed from my expectation in this only, that I <lb/>have
                              pleased a greater number, than I ventured to <lb/>hope I should
                              please.</p>
         <p>For the sake of variety, and from a consciousness <lb/>of my own
                              weakness, I was induced to request <lb/>the assistance of a Friend,
                              who furnished me <lb/>with the Poems of the A<hi rend="small">ncient</hi> M<hi rend="small">ariner</hi>, the <lb/>F<hi rend="small">oster</hi>-M<hi rend="small">other’s</hi> T<hi rend="small">ale</hi>, the N<hi rend="small">ightingale</hi>,and
                              <lb/>the Poem entitled L<hi rend="small">ove</hi>. I should not,
                              however, <lb/>have requested this assistance, had I not believed
                              <lb/>that the Poems of my Friend would in a great <lb/>measure have
                              the same tendency as my own, and <lb/>that, though there would be
                              found a difference,<pb n="iii"/>
            <milestone unit="page" n="iii"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>there would be found no discordance in the co-<lb/>lours
                              of our style; as our opinions on the subject <lb/>of poetry do almost
                              entirely coincide.</p>
         <p>Several of my Friends are anxious for the success <lb/>of these Poems
                              from a belief, that, if the views <lb/>with which they were composed
                              were indeed <lb/>realized, a class of Poetry would be produced,
                              <lb/>well adapted to interest mankind permanently, <lb/>and not
                              unimportant in the multiplicity, and in the <lb/>quality of its moral
                              relations : and on this account <lb/>they have advised me to prefix a
                              systematic defence <lb/>of the theory upon which the poems were
                              written. <lb/>But I was unwilling to undertake the task, because
                              <lb/>I knew that on this occasion the Reader would <lb/>look coldly
                              upon my arguments, since I might be <lb/>suspected of having been
                              principally influenced <lb/>by the selfish and foolish hope of
                                   <emph>reasoning</emph> him <lb/>into an approbation of these
                              particular Poems : <lb/>and I was still more unwilling to undertake
                                   the<pb n="iv"/>
            <milestone unit="page" n="iv"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>task,
                              because, adequately to display my opinions, <lb/>and fully to enforce
                              my arguments, would require <lb/>a space wholly disproportionate to
                              the nature of <lb/>a preface. For to treat the subject with the
                              clear-<lb/>ness and coherence, of which I believe it
                              suscep-<lb/>tible, it would be necessary to give a full account
                              <lb/>of the present state of the public taste in this <lb/>country,
                              and to determine how far this taste is <lb/>healthy or depraved;
                              which, again, could not be <lb/>determined, without pointing out, in
                              what man-<lb/>ner language and the human mind act and re-act <lb/>on
                              each other, and without retracing the revolu-<lb/>tions, not of
                              literature alone, but likewise of so-<lb/>ciety itself. I have
                              therefore altogether declined <lb/>to enter regularly upon this
                              defence ; yet I am <lb/>sensible, that there would be some impropriety
                              in <lb/>abruptly obtruding upon the Public, without a <lb/>few words
                              of introduction, Poems so materially <lb/>different from those, upon
                              which general appro-<lb/>bation is at present bestowed.</p>
         <pb n="v"/>
         <milestone n="v" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <p>It is supposed, that by the act of writing in verse <lb/>an Author makes
                              a formal engagement that he <lb/>will gratify certain known habits of
                              association ; <lb/>that he not only thus apprizes the Reader that
                              <lb/>certain classes of ideas and expressions will be <lb/>found in
                              his book, but that others will be <lb/>carefully excluded. This
                              exponent or symbol held <lb/>forth by metrical language must in
                              different æras <lb/>of literature have excited very different
                              expecta-<lb/>tions: for example, in the age of Catullus, Te-<lb/>rence
                              and Lucretius, and that of Statius or Clau-<lb/>dian; and in our own
                              country, in the age of <lb/>Shakespeare and Beaumont and Fletcher, and
                              that <lb/>of Donne and Cowley, or Dryden, or Pope. I <lb/>will not
                              take upon me to determine the exact im-<lb/>port of the promise which
                              by the act of writing <lb/>in verse an Author, in the present day,
                              makes to <lb/>his Reader ; but I am certain, it will appear to
                              <lb/>many persons that I have not fulfilled the terms of <lb/>an
                              engagement thus voluntarily contracted. They<pb n="vi"/>
            <milestone n="vi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>who have been accustomed to the
                              gaudiness and <lb/>inane phraseology of many modern writers, if
                              <lb/>they persist in reading this book to its conclu-<lb/>sion, will,
                              no doubt, frequently have to struggle <lb/>with feelings of
                              strangeness and aukwardness : <lb/>they will look round for poetry,
                              and will be in-<lb/>duced to inquire by what species of courtesy
                              <lb/>these attempts can be permitted to assume that <lb/>title. I hope
                              therefore the Reader will not cen-<lb/>sure me, if I attempt to state
                              what I have pro-<lb/>posed to myself to perform ; and also, (as far as
                              <lb/>the limits of a preface will permit) to explain <lb/>some of the
                              chief reasons which have determined <lb/>me in the choice of my
                              purpose : that at least <lb/>he may be spared any unpleasant feeling
                              of <lb/>disappointment, and that I myself may be pro-<lb/>tected from
                              the most dishonourable accusation <lb/>which can be brought against an
                              Author, namely, <lb/>that of an indolence which prevents him from
                              <lb/>endeavouring to ascertain what is his duty, or<pb n="vii"/>
            <milestone n="vii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>when his duty is
                              ascertained, prevents him from <lb/>performing it.</p>
         <p>The principal object, then, which I proposed to <lb/>myself in these
                              Poems was to choose incidents and <lb/>situations from common life,
                              and to relate or <lb/>describe them, throughout, as far as was
                              possible, <lb/>in a selection of language really used by men ;
                              <lb/>and, at the same time, to throw over them a cer-<lb/>tain
                              colouring of imagination, whereby ordinary <lb/>things should be
                              presented to the mind in an <lb/>unusual way; and, further, and above
                              all, to <lb/>make these incidents and situations interesting <lb/>by
                              tracing in them, truly though not osten-<lb/>tatiously, the primary
                              laws of our nature : chiefly, <lb/>as far as regards the manner in
                              which we associate <lb/>ideas in a state of excitement. Low and rustic
                              <lb/>life was generally chosen, because in that condi-<lb/>tion, the
                              essential passions of the heart find a bet-<lb/>ter soil in which they
                              can attain their maturity,<pb n="viii"/>
            <milestone n="viii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>are less under restraint, and speak a
                              plainer and <lb/>more emphatic language; because in that
                              con-<lb/>dition of life our elementary feelings co-exist in a
                              <lb/>state of greater simplicity, and, consequently, <lb/>may be more
                              accurately contemplated, and more <lb/>forcibly communicated; because
                              the manners of <lb/>rural life germinate from those elementary
                              feel-<lb/>ings; and, from the necessary character of rural
                              <lb/>occupations, are more easily comprehended ; and <lb/>are more
                              durable; and lastly, because in that <lb/>condition the passions of
                              men are incorporated <lb/>with the beautiful and permanent forms of
                              na-<lb/>ture. The language, too, of these men is adopted
                              <lb/>(purified indeed from what appear to be its real <lb/>defects,
                              from all lasting and rational causes of <lb/>dislike or disgust)
                              because such men hourly com-<lb/>municate with the best objects from
                              which the <lb/>best part of language is originally derived ; and
                              <lb/>because, from their rank in society and the same-<lb/>ness and
                              narrow circle of their intercourse, being<pb n="ix"/>
            <milestone n="ix" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>less under the action of social vanity
                              they <lb/>convey their feelings and notions in simple and
                              <lb/>unelaborated expressions. Accordingly, such a <lb/>language,
                              arising out of repeated experience and <lb/>regular feelings, is a
                              more permanent, and a far <lb/>more philosophical language, than that
                              which is <lb/>frequently substituted for it by Poets, who think
                              <lb/>that they are conferring honour upon themselves <lb/>and their
                              art, in proportion as they separate them-<lb/>selves from the
                              sympathies of men, and indulge <lb/>in arbitrary and capricious habits
                              of expression, in <lb/>order to furnish food for fickle tastes, and
                              fickle <lb/>appetites, of their own creation*.</p>
         <p>I cannot, however, be insensible of the present <lb/>
            <note resp="author" place="foot">* It is worth while here to observe that the
                                   affecting parts <lb/>of Chaucer are almost always expressed in
                                   language pure <lb/>and universally intelligible even to this
                                   day.</note>
            <pb n="x"/>
            <milestone n="x" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>outcry against the triviality and meanness both of
                              <lb/>thought and language, which some of my contem-<lb/>poraries have
                              occasionally introduced into their <lb/>metrical compositions; and I
                              acknowledge that <lb/>this defect, where it exists, is more
                              dishonourable <lb/>to the Writer’s own character than false
                              refine-<lb/>ment or arbitrary innovation, though I should
                              con-<lb/>tend at the same time that it is far less pernicious <lb/>in
                              the sum of its consequences. From such verses <lb/>the Poems in these
                              volumes will be found distin-<lb/>guished at least by one mark of
                              difference, that <lb/>each of them has a worthy <emph>purpose</emph>.
                              Not that I <lb/>mean to say, that I always began to write with a
                              <lb/>distinct purpose formally conceived ; but I believe <lb/>that my
                              habits of meditation have so formed my <lb/>feelings, as that my
                              descriptions of such objects <lb/>as strongly excite those feelings,
                              will be found to <lb/>carry along with them a <emph>purpose</emph>. If
                              in this op-<lb/>inion I am mistaken, I can have little right to the
                              <lb/>name of a Poet. For all good poetry is the<pb n="xi"/>
            <milestone n="xi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>spontaneous overflow of powerful
                              feelings : but <lb/>though this be true, Poems to which any value
                              <lb/>can be attached, were never produced on any <lb/>variety of
                              subjects but by a man, who being pos-<lb/>sessed of more than usual
                              organic sensibility, had <lb/>also thought long and deeply. For our
                              continued <lb/>influxes of feeling are modified and directed by
                              <lb/>our thoughts, which are indeed the representatives <lb/>of all
                              our past feelings ; and, as by contemplating <lb/>the relation of
                              these general representatives to <lb/>each other we discover what is
                              really important <lb/>to men, so, by the repetition and continuance of
                              <lb/>this act, our feelings will be connected with im-<lb/>portant
                              subjects, till at length, if we be origi-<lb/>nally possessed of much
                              sensibility, such habits <lb/>of mind will be produced, that, by
                              obeying <lb/>blindly and mechanically the impulses of those
                              <lb/>habits, we shall describe objects, and utter senti-<lb/>ments, of
                              such a nature and in such connection <lb/>with each other, that the
                              understanding of the<pb n="xii"/>
            <milestone n="xii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>being to whom we address ourselves, if he be in <lb/>a
                              healthful state of association, must necessarily <lb/>be in some
                              degree enlightened, and his affections <lb/>ameliorated.</p>
         <p>I have said that each of these poems has a <lb/>purpose. I have also
                              informed my Reader what <lb/>this purpose will be found principally to
                              be : <lb/>namely, to illustrate the manner in which our <lb/>feelings
                              and ideas are associated in a state of <lb/>excitement. But, speaking
                              in language somewhat <lb/>more appropriate, it is to follow the fluxes
                              and <lb/>refluxes of the mind when agitated by the great <lb/>and
                              simple affections of our nature. This object <lb/>I have endeavoured
                              in these short essays to attain <lb/>by various means ; by tracing the
                              maternal pas-<lb/>sion through many of its more subtle windings,
                              <lb/>as in the poems of the I<hi rend="small">diot</hi> B<hi rend="small">oy</hi> and the <lb/>M<hi rend="small">ad</hi>M<hi rend="small">other</hi> ; by accompanying the last
                              strug-<lb/>gles of a human being, at the approach of death, <pb n="xiii"/>
            <milestone n="xiii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>cleaving in
                              solitude to life and society, as in the <lb/>Poem of the F<hi rend="small">orsaken</hi> I<hi rend="small">ndian</hi> ; by
                              showing, <lb/>as in the Stanzas entitled W<hi rend="small">e are
                                   </hi>S<hi rend="small">even</hi>, the <lb/>perplexity and
                              obscurity which in childhood <lb/>attend our notion of death, or
                              rather our utter <lb/>inability to admit that notion ; or by
                              displaying <lb/>the strength of fraternal, or to speak more
                              phi-<lb/>losophically, of moral attachment when early as-<lb/>sociated
                              with the great and beautiful objects of <lb/>nature, as in T<hi rend="small">he</hi> B<hi rend="small">rothers</hi> ; or, as in
                              the <lb/>Incident of S<hi rend="small">imon</hi> L<hi rend="small">ee</hi>, by placing my Reader <lb/>in the way of receiving from
                              ordinary moral <lb/>sensations another and more salutary impression
                              <lb/>than we are accustomed to receive from them. It <lb/>has also
                              been part of my general purpose to at-<lb/>tempt to sketch characters
                              under the influence of <lb/>less impassioned feelings, as in the T<hi rend="small">wo</hi> A<hi rend="small">pril</hi>
            <lb/>M<hi rend="small">ornings</hi>, T<hi rend="small">he</hi> F<hi rend="small">ountain</hi>, T<hi rend="small">he</hi> O<hi rend="small">ld</hi> M<hi rend="small">an <lb/>travelling</hi>,
                                   T<hi rend="small">he two</hi> T<hi rend="small">hieves</hi>,
                              &amp;c. characters <lb/>of which the elements are simple, belonging
                                   <pb n="xiv"/>
            <milestone n="xiv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>rather to
                              nature than to manners, such as exist <lb/>now, and will probably
                              always exist, and which <lb/>from their constitution may be distinctly
                              and pro-<lb/>fitably contemplated. I will not abuse the
                              in-<lb/>dulgence of my Reader by dwelling longer upon <lb/>this
                              subject; but it is proper that I should men-<lb/>tion one other
                              circumstance which distinguishes <lb/>these Poems from the popular
                              Poetry of the day ; <lb/>it is this, that the feeling therein
                              developed gives <lb/>importance to the action and situation, and not
                              <lb/>the action and situation to the feeling. My mean-<lb/>ing will be
                              rendered perfectly intelligible by refer-<lb/>ring my Reader to the
                              Poems entitled P<hi rend="small">oor</hi> S<hi rend="small">usan</hi>
            <lb/>and the C<hi rend="small">hildless</hi> F<hi rend="small">ather</hi>, particularly to the <lb/>last Stanza of the latter
                              Poem.</p>
         <p>I will not suffer a sense of false modesty to prevent <lb/>me from
                              asserting, that I point my Reader’s atten-<lb/>tion to this mark
                              of distinction, far less for the <lb/>sake of these particular Poems
                              than from the<pb n="xv"/>
            <milestone n="xv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>general importance of the subject. The subject <lb/>is
                              indeed important! For the human mind is <lb/>capable of being excited
                              without the application <lb/>of gross and violent stimulants; and he
                              must have <lb/>a very faint perception of its beauty and dignity
                              <lb/>who does not know this, and who does not fur-<lb/>ther know, that
                              one being is elevated above an-<lb/>other, in proportion as he
                              possesses this capa-<lb/>bility. It has therefore appeared to me, that
                              to <lb/>endeavour to produce or enlarge this capability is <lb/>one of
                              the best services in which, at any period, <lb/>a Writer can be
                              engaged ; but this service, excel-<lb/>lent at all times, is
                              especially so at the present day. <lb/>For a multitude of causes,
                              unknown to former <lb/>times, are now acting with a combined force to
                              <lb/>blunt the discriminating powers of the mind, and <lb/>unfitting
                              it for all voluntary exertion to reduce it <lb/>to a state of almost
                              savage torpor. The most <lb/>effective of these causes are the great
                                   national<pb n="xvi"/>
            <milestone n="xvi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>events which are daily taking place, and the
                              in-<lb/>creasing accumulation of men in cities, where the
                              <lb/>uniformity of the occupations produces a craving <lb/>for
                              extraordinary incident, which the rapid com-<lb/>munication of
                              intelligence hourly gratifies. To <lb/>this tendency of life and
                              manners the literature <lb/>and theatrical exhibitions of the country
                              have <lb/>conformed themselves. The invaluable works of <lb/>our elder
                              writers, I had almost said the works of <lb/>Shakespear and Milton,
                              are driven into neglect <lb/>by frantic novels, sickly and stupid
                              German Tra-<lb/>gedies, and deluges of idle and extravagant stories
                              <lb/>in verse.—When I think upon this degrading <lb/>thirst
                              after outrageous stimulation, I am almost <lb/>ashamed to have spoken
                              of the feeble effort with <lb/>which I have endeavoured to counteract
                              it; and, <lb/>reflecting upon the magnitude of the general <lb/>evil,
                              I should be oppressed with no dishonorable <lb/>melancholy, had I not
                              a deep impression of certain <pb n="xvii"/>
            <milestone n="xvii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>inherent and indestructible qualities of
                              the human <lb/>mind, and likewise of certain powers in the great
                              <lb/>and permanent objects that act upon it, which are <lb/>equally
                              inherent and indestructible ; and did I <lb/>not further add to this
                              impression a belief, that the <lb/>time is approaching when the evil
                              will be syste-<lb/>matically opposed, by men of greater powers, and
                              <lb/>with far more distinguished success.</p>
         <p>Having dwelt thus long on the subjects and aim <lb/>of these Poems, I
                              shall request the Reader’s per-<lb/>mission to apprize him of a
                              few circumstances <lb/>relating to their <emph>style</emph>, in order,
                              among other rea-<lb/>sons, that I may not be censured for not having
                              <lb/>performed what I never attempted. The Reader <lb/>will find that
                              personifications of abstract ideas <lb/>rarely occur in these volumes
                              ; and, I hope, are <lb/>utterly rejected as an ordinary device to
                              elevate <lb/>the style, and raise it above prose. I have pro- <pb n="xviii"/>
            <milestone n="xviii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>posed to
                              myself to imitate, and, as far as is pos-<lb/>sible, to adopt the very
                              language of men ; and <lb/>assuredly such personifications do not make
                              any <lb/>natural or regular part of that language. They <lb/>are,
                              indeed, a figure of speech occasionally <lb/>prompted by passion, and
                              I have made use of <lb/>them as such; but I have endeavoured utterly
                              <lb/>to reject them as a mechanical device of style, <lb/>or as a
                              family language which Writers in metre <lb/>seem to lay claim to by
                              prescription. I have <lb/>wished to keep my Reader in the company of
                              <lb/>flesh and blood, persuaded thatby so doing I <lb/>shall interest
                              him. I am, however, well aware <lb/>that others who pursue a different
                              track may <lb/>interest him likewise; I do not interfere with
                              <lb/>their claim, I only wish to prefer a different <lb/>claim of my
                              own. There will also be found in <lb/>these volumes little of what is
                              usually called <lb/>poetic diction ; I have taken as much pains to <pb n="xix"/>
            <milestone n="xix" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>avoid it as
                              others ordinarily take to produce it ; <lb/>this I have done for the
                              reason already alleged, <lb/>to bring my language near to the language
                              of men, <lb/>and further, because the pleasure which I have
                              <lb/>proposed to myself to impart is of a kind very <lb/>different
                              from that which is supposed by many <lb/>persons to be the proper
                              object of poetry. I do <lb/>not know how, without being culpably
                              particular, <lb/>I can give my Reader a more exact notion of <lb/>the
                              style in which I wished these poems to be <lb/>written than by
                              informing him that I have at <lb/>all times endeavoured to look
                              steadily at my sub-<lb/>ject, consequently, I hope that there is in
                              these <lb/>Poems little falsehood of description, and that <lb/>my
                              ideas are expressed in language fitted to their <lb/>respective
                              importance. Something I must have <lb/>gained by this practice, as it
                              is friendly to one <lb/>property of all good poetry, namely good sense
                              ; <lb/>but it has necessarily cut me off from a large por-<lb/>tion of
                              phrases and figures of speech which from<pb n="xx"/>
            <milestone n="xx" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>father to son have long been regarded as
                              the com-<lb/>mon inheritance of Poets. I have also thought it
                              <lb/>expedient to restrict myself still further, having <lb/>abstained
                              from the use of many expressions, in <lb/>themselves proper and
                              beautiful, but which have <lb/>been foolishly repeated by bad Poets,
                              till such <lb/>feelings of disgust are connected with them as it
                              <lb/>is scarcely possible by any art of association to
                              <lb/>overpower.</p>
         <p>If in a poem there should be found a series of lines, <lb/>or even a
                              single line, in which the language, though <lb/>naturally arranged,
                              and according to the <lb/>strict laws of metre, does not differ from
                              that of <lb/>prose, there is a numerous class of critics, who,
                              <lb/>when they stumble upon these prosaisms, as they <lb/>call them,
                              imagine that they have made a notable <lb/>discovery, and exult over
                              the Poet as over a man<lb/>ignorant of his own profession. Now these
                              men <lb/>would establish a canon of criticism which the <pb n="xxi"/>
            <milestone n="xxi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>Reader will conclude
                              he must utterly reject, if he <lb/>wishes to be pleased with these
                              volumes. And it <lb/>would be a most easy task to prove to him, that
                              <lb/>not only the language of a large portion of every <lb/>good poem,
                              even of the most elevated character, <lb/>must necessarily, except
                              with reference to the <lb/>metre, in no respect differ from that of
                              good <lb/>prose, but likewise that some of the most in-<lb/>teresting
                              parts of the best poems will be found <lb/>to be strictly the language
                              of prose, when prose <lb/>is well written. The truth of this assertion
                              <lb/>might be demonstrated by innumerable passages <lb/>from almost
                              all the poetical writings, even of <lb/>Milton himself. I have not
                              space for much quo-<lb/>tation; but, to illustrate the subject in a
                              gene-<lb/>ral manner, I will here adduce a short composi-<lb/>tion of
                              Gray, who was at the head of those who, <lb/>by their reasonings, have
                              attempted to widen the <lb/>space of separation betwixt Prose and
                              Metrical <lb/>composition, and was more than any other man <pb n="xxii"/>
            <milestone n="xxii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>curiously
                              elaborate in the structure of his own <lb/>poetic diction. <lb/>
            <q who="Gray">
               <lg type="sonnet">
                  <l>In vain to me the smiling mornings shine,</l>
                  <l>And reddening Phœbus lifts his golden fire:</l>
                  <l>The birds in vain their amorous descant join,</l>
                  <l>Or cheerful fields resume their green attire.</l>
                  <l>These ears alas ! for other notes repine;</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>A different object do these eyes
                                             require;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>My lonely anguish melts no heart but
                                             mine;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>And in my breast the imperfect joys
                                             expire;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet morning smiles the busy race to cheer,</l>
                  <l>And new-born pleasure brings to happier men;</l>
                  <l>The fields to all their wonted tribute bear;</l>
                  <l>To warm their little loves the birds complain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>I fruitless mourn to him that cannot
                                             hear,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>And weep the more because I weep in
                                             vain.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>It will easily by perceived that the only part of
                              <lb/>this Sonnet which is of any value is the lines <lb/>printed in
                              Italics : it is equally obvious, that, ex-<lb/>cept in the rhyme, and
                              in the use of the single <lb/>word “ fruitless” for
                              fruitlessly, which is so far a <lb/>defect, the language of these
                              lines does in no re-<lb/>spect differ from that of prose.</p>
         <pb n="xxiii"/>
         <milestone n="xxiii" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <p>By the foregoing quotation I have shown that <lb/>the language of Prose
                              may yet be well adapted <lb/>to Poetry; and I have previously asserted
                              that <lb/>a large portion of the language of every good <lb/>poem can
                              in no respect differ from that of good <lb/>Prose. I will go further.
                              I do not doubt that <lb/>it may be safely affirmed, that there neither
                              is, <lb/>nor can be, any essential difference between <lb/>the
                              language of prose and metrical composi-<lb/>tion. We are fond of
                              tracing the resemblance <lb/>between Poetry and Painting, and,
                              accordingly, <lb/>we call them Sisters: but where shall we find
                              <lb/>bonds of connection sufficiently strict to typify <lb/>the
                              affinity betwixt metrical and prose com-<lb/>position? They both speak
                              by and to the same <lb/>organs; the bodies in which both of them are
                              <lb/>clothed may be said to be of the same substance, <lb/>their
                              affections are kindred, and almost iden-<lb/>tical, not necessarily
                              differing even in degree; <pb n="xxiv"/>
            <milestone n="xxiv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>Poetry* sheds no tears “ such as
                              Angels weep,” <lb/>but natural and human tears; she can boast of
                              <lb/>no celestial Ichor that distinguishes her vital <lb/>juices from
                              those of prose; the same human <lb/>blood circulates through the veins
                              of them <lb/>both.</p>
         <p>If it be affirmed that rhyme and metrical arrange-<lb/>ment of
                              themselves constitute a distinction which <lb/>overturns what I have
                              been saying on the strict <note resp="author" place="foot">* I here
                                   use the word “ Poetry” (though against my own
                                   <lb/>judgment) as opposed to the word Prose, and synonymous
                                   <lb/>with metrical composition. But much confusion has been
                                   <lb/>introduced into criticism by this contradistinction of
                                   Po-<lb/>etry and Prose, instead of the more philosophical one of
                                   <lb/>Poetry and Matter of Fact, or Science. The only strict
                                   <lb/>antithesis to Prose is Metre ; nor is this, in truth, a
                                        <emph>strict</emph>
               <lb/>antithesis; because lines and passages of metre so
                                   natu-<lb/>rally occur in writing prose, that it would be scarcely
                                   pos-<lb/>sible to avoidthem, even were it desirable.</note>
            <pb n="xxv"/>
            <milestone n="xxv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>affinity of
                              metrical language with that of prose, <lb/>and paves the way for other
                              artificial distinctions <lb/>which the mind voluntarily admits, I
                              answer that <lb/>the language of such Poetry as I am
                              recommend-<lb/>ing is, as far as is possible, a selection of the
                              lan-<lb/>guage really spoken by men; that this selection,
                              <lb/>wherever it is made with true taste and feeling, <lb/>will of
                              itself form a distinction far greater than <lb/>would at first be
                              imagined, and will entirely sepa-<lb/>rate the composition from the
                              vulgarity and mean-<lb/>ness of ordinary life; and, if metre be
                              superadded <lb/>thereto, I believe that a dissimilitude will be
                              <lb/>produced altogether sufficient for the gratifica-<lb/>tion of a
                              rational mind. What other distinction <lb/>would we have? Whence is it
                              to come? And <lb/>where is it to exist? Not, surely, where the
                              <lb/>Poet speaks through the mouths of his characters : <lb/>it cannot
                              be necessary here, either for elevation <lb/>of style, or any of its
                              supposed ornaments : for, <lb/>if the Poet’s subject be
                              judiciously chosen, it will<pb n="xxvi"/>
            <milestone n="xxvi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>naturally, and upon fit occasion, lead him
                              to <lb/>passions the language of which, if selected truly <lb/>and
                              judiciously, must necessarily be dignified and <lb/>variegated, and
                              alive with metaphors and figures. <lb/>I forbear to speak of an
                              incongruity which would <lb/>shock the intelligent Reader, should the
                              Poet <lb/>interweave any foreign splendour of his own <lb/>with that
                              which the passion naturally suggests: <lb/>it is sufficient to say
                              that such addition is un-<lb/>necessary. And, surely, it is more
                              probable that <lb/>those passages, which with propriety abound with
                              <lb/>metaphors and figures, will have their due effect, <lb/>if, upon
                              other occasions where the passions are of <lb/>a milder character, the
                              style also be subdued and <lb/>temperate.</p>
         <p>But, as the pleasure which I hope to give by the <lb/>Poems I now
                              present to the Reader must depend <lb/>entirely on just notions upon
                              this subject, and, <lb/>as it is in itself of the highest importance
                              to our<pb n="xxvii"/>
            <milestone n="xxvii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>taste
                              and moral feelings, I cannot content myself <lb/>with these detached
                              remarks. And if, in what I <lb/>am about to say, it shall appear to
                              some that my <lb/>labour is unnecessary, and that I am like a man
                              <lb/>fighting a battle without enemies, I would remind <lb/>such
                              persons, that, whatever may be the lan-<lb/>guage outwardly holden by
                              men, a practical faith <lb/>in the opinions which I am wishing to
                              establish <lb/>is almost entirely unknown. If my conclusions are
                              ad-<lb/>mitted, and carried as far as they must be carried <lb/>if
                              admitted at all, our judgments concerning the <lb/>works of the
                              greatest Poets both ancient and <lb/>modern will be far different from
                              what they are <lb/>at present, both when we praise, and when we
                              <lb/>censure: and our moral feelings influencing, and <lb/>influenced
                              by these judgments will, I believe, be <lb/>corrected and
                              purified.</p>
         <p>Taking up the subject, then, upon general <lb/>grounds, I ask what is
                              meant by the word Poet ? <pb n="xxviii"/>
            <milestone n="xxviii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>What is a Poet ? To whom does he address
                              <lb/>himself? And what language is to be expected <lb/>from him ? He
                              is a man speaking to men : <lb/>a man, it is true, endued with more
                              lively sensi-<lb/>bility, more enthusiasm and tenderness, who has
                              <lb/>a greater knowledge of human nature, and a more
                              <lb/>comprehensive soul, than are supposed to be com-<lb/>mon among
                              mankind; a man pleased with his <lb/>own passions and volitions, and
                              who rejoices <lb/>more than other men in the spirit of life that is
                              <lb/>in him ; delighting to contemplate similar voli-<lb/>tions and
                              passions as manifested in the goings-on <lb/>of the Universe, and
                              habitually impelled to create <lb/>them where he does not find them.
                              To these <lb/>qualities he has added a disposition to be
                              affect-<lb/>ed more than other men by absent things as <lb/>if they
                              were present ; an ability of conjuring <lb/>up in himself passions,
                              which are indeed far <lb/>from being the same as those produced by
                              real <lb/>events, yet (especially in those parts of the general<pb n="xxix"/>
            <milestone n="xxix" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>sympathy
                              which are pleasing and delightful) do <lb/>more nearly resemble the
                              passions produced by <lb/>real events, than any thing which, from the
                              mo-<lb/>tions of their own minds merely, other men are <lb/>accustomed
                              to feel in themselves; whence, and <lb/>from practice, he has acquired
                              a greater readiness <lb/>and power in expressing what he thinks and
                              <lb/>feels, and especially those thoughts and feelings <lb/>which, by
                              his own choice, or from the structure <lb/>of his own mind, arise in
                              him without immediate <lb/>external excitement.</p>
         <p>But, whatever portion of this faculty we may <lb/>suppose even the
                              greatest Poet to possess, there <lb/>cannot be a doubt but that the
                              language which <lb/>it will suggest to him, must, in liveliness and
                              <lb/>truth, fall far short of that which is uttered by <lb/>men in
                              real life, under the actual pressure of <lb/>those passions, certain
                              shadows of which the Poet <lb/>thus produces, or feels to be produced,
                              in himself.<pb n="xxx"/>
            <milestone n="xxx" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>However exalted a notion we would wish to <lb/>cherish of
                              the character of a Poet, it is obvious, <lb/>that, while he describes
                              and imitates passions, his <lb/>situation is altogether slavish and
                              mechanical, <lb/>compared with the freedom and power of real <lb/>and
                              substantial action and suffering. So that it <lb/>will be the wish of
                              the Poet to bring his feelings <lb/>near to those of the persons whose
                              feelings he <lb/>describes, nay, for short spaces of time perhaps,
                              <lb/>to let himself slip into an entire delusion, and <lb/>even
                              confound and identify his own feelings with <lb/>theirs; modifying
                              only the language which is thus <lb/>suggested to him, by a
                              consideration that he de-<lb/>scribes for a particular purpose, that
                              of giving <lb/>pleasure. Here, then, he will apply the principle
                              <lb/>on which l have so much insisted, namely, that <lb/>of selection;
                              on this he will depend for removing <lb/>what would otherwise be
                              painful or disgusting in <lb/>the passion; he will feel that there is
                              no necessity <lb/>to trick out or to elevate nature : and, the more
                                   <pb n="xxxi"/>
            <milestone n="xxxi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>industriously he applies this principle, the deeper
                              <lb/>will be his faith that no words, which his fancy <lb/>or
                              imagination can suggest, will be to be com-<lb/>pared with those which
                              are the emanations of <lb/>reality and truth.</p>
         <p>But it may be said by those who do not object <lb/>to the general spirit
                              of these remarks, that, as it <lb/>is impossible for the Poet to
                              produce upon all <lb/>occasions language as exquisitely fitted for the
                              <lb/>passion as that which the real passion itself sug-<lb/>gests, it
                              is proper that he should consider himself <lb/>as in the situation of
                              a translator, who deems <lb/>himself justified when he substitutes
                              excellences <lb/>of another kind for those which are unattainable
                              <lb/>by him; and endeavours occasionally to surpass <lb/>his original,
                              in order to make some amends for <lb/>the general inferiority to which
                              he feels that he <lb/>must submit. But this would be to encourage
                              <lb/>idleness and unmanly despair. Further, it is the<pb n="xxxii"/>
            <milestone n="xxxii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>language of men who
                              speak of what they do not <lb/>understand; who talk of Poetry as of a
                              matter <lb/>of amusement and idle pleasure; who will con-<lb/>verse
                              with us as gravely about a <emph>taste </emph>for Poetry, <lb/>as they
                              express it, as if it were a thing as indiffe-<lb/>rent as a taste for
                              Rope-dancing, or Frontiniac or <lb/>Sherry. Aristotle, I have been
                              told, hath said, <lb/>that Poetry is the most philosophic of all
                              writing : <lb/>it is so : its object is truth, not individual and
                              <lb/>local, but general, and operative ; not standing <lb/>upon
                              external testimony, but carried alive into the <lb/>heart by passion;
                              truth which is its own testi-<lb/>mony, which gives strength and
                              divinity to the <lb/>tribunal to which it appeals, and receives them
                              <lb/>from the same tribunal. Poetry is the image of <lb/>man and
                              nature. The obstacles which stand in <lb/>the way of the fidelity of
                              the Biographer and His-<lb/>torian, and of their consequent utility,
                              are incal-<lb/>culably greater than those which are to be
                              encoun-<lb/>tered by the Poet who has an adequate notion of <pb n="xxxiii"/>
            <milestone n="xxxiii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>the
                              dignity of his art. The Poet writes under <lb/>one restriction only,
                              namely, that of the neces-<lb/>sity of giving immediate pleasure to a
                              human <lb/>Being possessed of that information which may <lb/>be
                              expected from him, not as a lawyer, a phy-<lb/>sician, a mariner, an
                              astronomer or a natural <lb/>philosopher, but as a Man. Except this
                              one re-<lb/>striction, there is no object standing between the
                              <lb/>Poet and the image of things; between this, <lb/>and the
                              Biographer and Historian there are a <lb/>thousand.</p>
         <p>Nor let this necessity of producing immediate <lb/>pleasure be
                              considered as a degradation of the <lb/>Poet’s art. It is far
                              otherwise. It is an acknow-<lb/>ledgment of the beauty of the
                              universe, an ac-<lb/>knowledgment the more sincere, because it is not
                              <lb/>formal, but indirect; it is a task light and easy <lb/>to him who
                              looks at the world in the spirit of <lb/>love: further, it is a homage
                              paid to the native<pb n="xxxiv"/>
            <milestone n="xxxiv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>and naked dignity of man, to the grand elemen-<lb/>tary
                              principle of pleasure, by which he knows, <lb/>and feels, and lives,
                              and moves. We have no <lb/>sympathy but what is propagated by pleasure
                              : <lb/>I would not be misunderstood; but wherever we <lb/>sympathize
                              with pain it will be found that the <lb/>sympathy is produced and
                              carried on by subtle <lb/>combinations with pleasure. We have no
                              know-<lb/>ledge, that is, no general principles drawn from <lb/>the
                              contemplation of particular facts, but what <lb/>has been built up by
                              pleasure, and exists in us by <lb/>pleasure alone. The Man of Science,
                              the Che-<lb/>mist and Mathematician, whatever difficulties and
                              <lb/>disgusts they may have had to struggle with, <lb/>know and feel
                              this. However painful may be the <lb/>objects with which the
                              Anatomist’s knowledge is <lb/>connected, he feels that his
                              knowledge is plea-<lb/>sure ; and where he has no pleasure he has no
                              <lb/>knowledge. What then does the Poet? He <lb/>considers man and the
                              objects that surround him<pb n="xxxv"/>
            <milestone n="xxxv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>as acting and re-acting upon each other, so as to
                              <lb/>produce an infinite complexity of pain and plea-<lb/>sure ; he
                              considers man in his own nature and in <lb/>his ordinary life as
                              contemplating this with a cer-<lb/>tain quantity of immediate
                              knowledge, with <lb/>certain convictions, intuitions, and deductions
                              <lb/>which by habit become of the nature of intuitions; <lb/>he
                              considers him as looking upon this complex <lb/>scene of ideas and
                              sensations, and finding every <lb/>where objects that immediately
                              excite in him <lb/>sympathies which, from the necessities of his
                              <lb/>nature, are accompanied by an overbalance of <lb/>enjoyment.</p>
         <p>To this knowledge which all men carry about <lb/>with them, and to these
                              sympathies in which <lb/>without any other discipline than that of our
                              <lb/>daily life we are fitted to take delight, the Poet
                              <lb/>principally directs his attention. He considers man <lb/>and
                              nature as essentially adapted to each other, <pb n="xxxvi"/>
            <milestone n="xxxvi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>and the mind of man as naturally
                              the mirror of <lb/>the fairest and most interesting qualities of
                              nature. <lb/>And thus the Poet, prompted by this feeling of
                              <lb/>pleasure which accompanies him through the <lb/>whole course of
                              his studies, converses with gene-<lb/>ral nature with affections akin
                              to those, which, <lb/>through labour and length of time, the Man of
                              <lb/>Science has raised up in himself, by conversing <lb/>with those
                              particular parts of nature which are <lb/>the objects of his studies.
                              The knowledge both <lb/>of the Poet and the Man of Science is pleasure
                              ; <lb/>but the knowledge of the one cleaves to us as a <lb/>necessary
                              part of our existence, our natural and <lb/>unalienable inheritance ;
                              the other is a personal <lb/>and individual acquisition, slow to come
                              to us, and <lb/>by no habitual and direct sympathy connecting <lb/>us
                              with our fellow-beings. The Man of Science <lb/>seeks truth as a
                              remote and unknown benefactor ; <lb/>he cherishes and loves it in his
                              solitude : the <lb/>Poet, singing a song in which all human beings<pb n="xxxvii"/>
            <milestone n="xxxvii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>join
                              with him, rejoices in the presence of truth as <lb/>our visible friend
                              and hourly companion. Poetry <lb/>is the breath and finer spirit of
                              all knowledge; it <lb/>is the impassioned expression which is in the
                              coun-<lb/>tenance of all Science. Emphatically may it be <lb/>said of
                              the Poet, as Shakespeare hath said of man, <lb/>“ that he looks
                              before and after.” He is the <lb/>rock of defence of human
                              nature ; an upholder <lb/>and preserver, carrying every where with him
                              <lb/>relationship and love. In spite of difference of <lb/>soil and
                              climate, of language and manners, of laws <lb/>and customs, in spite
                              of things silently gone out <lb/>of mind and things violently
                              destroyed, the Poet <lb/>binds together by passion and knowledge the
                              vast <lb/>empire of human society, as it is spread over the <lb/>whole
                              earth, and over all time. The objects of <lb/>the Poet’s
                              thoughts are every where; though the <lb/>eyes and senses of man are,
                              it is true, his favourite <lb/>guides, yet he will follow wheresoever
                              he can find <lb/>an atmosphere of sensation in which to move his<pb n="xxxviii"/>
            <milestone n="xxxviii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>wings.
                              Poetry is the first and last of all know-<lb/>ledge—it is as
                              immortal as the heart of man. If <lb/>the labours of Men of Science
                              should ever create <lb/>any material revolution, direct or indirect,
                              in our <lb/>condition, and in the impressions which we
                              habi-<lb/>tually receive, the Poet will sleep then no more <lb/>than
                              at present, but he will be ready to follow the <lb/>steps of the Man
                              of Science, not only in those <lb/>general indirect effects, but he
                              will be at his side, <lb/>carrying sensation into the midst of the
                              objects <lb/>of the Science itself. The remotest discoveries <lb/>of
                              the Chemist, the Botanist, or Mineralogist, <lb/>will be as proper
                              objects of the Poet’s art as any <lb/>upon which it can be
                              employed, if the time <lb/>should ever come when these things shall be
                              fami-<lb/>liar to us, and the relations under which they are
                              <lb/>contemplated by the followers of these respective <lb/>Sciences
                              shall be manifestly and palpably material <lb/>to us as enjoying and
                              suffering beings. If the <lb/>time should ever come when what is now
                              called <pb n="xxxix"/>
            <milestone n="xxxix" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>Science, thus familiarized to men, shall be ready <lb/>to
                              put on, as it were, a form of flesh and blood, <lb/>the Poet will lend
                              his divine spirit to aid the <lb/>transfiguration, and will welcome
                              the Being thus <lb/>produced, as a dear and genuine inmate of <lb/>the
                              household of man.—It is not, then, to be supposed <lb/>that any
                              one, who holds that sublime notion of <lb/>Poetry which I have
                              attempted to convey, will <lb/>break in upon the sanctity and truth of
                              his pictures <lb/>by transitory and accidental ornaments, and
                              endea-<lb/>vour to excite admiration of himself by arts, the
                              <lb/>necessity of which must manifestly depend upon <lb/>the assumed
                              meanness of his subject. </p>
         <p>What I have thus far said applies to Poetry in <lb/>general; but
                              especially to those parts of compo-<lb/>sition where the Poet speaks
                              through the mouths <lb/>of his characters; and upon this point it
                              appears <lb/>to have such weight that I will conclude, there <lb/>are
                              few persons of good sense, who would not<pb n="xl"/>
            <milestone n="xl" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>allow that the dramatic parts of
                              composition are <lb/>defective, in proportion as they deviate from the
                              <lb/>real language of nature, and are coloured by a <lb/>diction of
                              the Poet’s own, either peculiar to him <lb/>as an individual
                              Poet, or belonging simply to <lb/>Poets in general, to a body of men
                              who, from <lb/>the circumstance of their compositions being in
                              <lb/>metre, it is expected will employ a particular language.</p>
         <p>It is not, then, in the dramatic parts of compo-<lb/>sition that we look
                              for this distinction of lan-<lb/>guage; but still it may be proper and
                              necessary <lb/>where the Poet speaks to us in his own person <lb/>and
                              character. To this I answer by referring my <lb/>Reader to the
                              description which I have before <lb/>given of a Poet. Among the
                              qualities which I <lb/>have enumerated as principally conducing to
                              form <lb/>a Poet, is implied nothing differing in kind from <lb/>other
                              men, but only in degree. The sum of<pb n="xli"/>
            <milestone n="xli" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>what I have there said is, that the Poet
                              is chiefly <lb/>distinguished from other men by a greater
                              prompt-<lb/>ness to think and feel without immediate external
                              <lb/>excitement, and a greater power in expressing such <lb/>thoughts
                              and feelings as a reproduced in him in <lb/>that manner. But these
                              passions and thoughts <lb/>and feelings are the general passions and
                              thoughts <lb/>and feelings of men. And with what are they
                              <lb/>connected? Undoubtedly with our moral senti-<lb/>ments and animal
                              sensations, and with the causes <lb/>which excite these; with the
                              operations of the <lb/>elements and the appearances of the visible
                              uni-<lb/>verse; with storm and sun-shine, with the revo-<lb/>lutions
                              of the seasons, with cold and heat, with <lb/>loss of friends and
                              kindred, with injuries and re-<lb/>sentments, gratitude and hope, with
                              fear and <lb/>sorrow. These, and the like, are the sensations <lb/>and
                              objects which the Poet describes, as they are <lb/>the sensations of
                              other men, and the objects which <lb/>interest them. The Poet thinks
                              and feels in the<pb n="xlii"/>
            <milestone n="xlii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>spirit of the passions of men. How, then, can <lb/>his
                              language differ in any material degree from that <lb/>of all other men
                              who feel vividly and see clearly ? <lb/>It might be
                                   <emph>proved</emph> that it is impossible. But sup-<lb/>posing
                              that this were not the case, the Poet might <lb/>then be allowed to
                              use a peculiar language when <lb/>expressing his feelings for his own
                              gratification, or <lb/>that of men like himself. But Poets do not
                              write <lb/>for Poets alone, but for men. Unless therefore we <lb/>are
                              advocates for that admiration which depends <lb/>upon ignorance, and
                              that pleasure which arises <lb/>from hearing what we do not
                              understand, the Poet <lb/>must descend from this supposed height, and,
                              in <lb/>order to excite rational sympathy, he must express
                              <lb/>himself as other men express themselves. To this <lb/>it may be
                              added, that while he is only selecting <lb/>from the real language of
                              men, or, which amounts <lb/>to the same thing, composing accurately in
                              the <lb/>spirit of such selection, he is treading upon safe
                              <lb/>ground, and we know what we are to expect from <pb n="xliii"/>
            <milestone n="xliii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>him. Our feelings
                              are the same with respect to <lb/>metre ; for, as it may be proper to
                              remind the <lb/>Reader, the distinction of metre is regular and
                              <lb/>uniform, and not like that which is produced by <lb/>what is
                              usually called poetic diction, arbitrary, and <lb/>subject to infinite
                              caprices upon which no calcula-<lb/>tion whatever can be made. In the
                              one case, the <lb/>Reader is utterly at the mercy of the Poet
                              respect-<lb/>ing what imagery or diction he may choose to <lb/>connect
                              with the passion, whereas, in the other, <lb/>the metre obeys certain
                              laws, to which the Poet <lb/>and Reader both willingly submit because
                              they are <lb/>certain, and because no interference is made by
                              <lb/>them with the passion but such as the concurring <lb/>testimony
                              of ages has shown to heighten and im-<lb/>prove the pleasure which
                              co-exists with it.</p>
         <p>It will now be proper to answer an obvious ques-<lb/>tion, namely, Why,
                              professing these opinions, have <lb/>I written in verse? To this, in
                              addition to such<pb n="xliv"/>
            <milestone n="xliv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>answer as is included in what I have already said, <lb/>I
                              reply in the first place, Because, however I may <lb/>have restricted
                              myself, there is still left open to me <lb/>what confessedly
                              constitutes the most valuable ob-<lb/>ject of all writing, whether in
                              prose or verse, the <lb/>great and universal passions of men, the most
                              gene-<lb/>ral and interesting of their occupations, and the
                              en-<lb/>tire world of nature, from which I am at liberty to
                              <lb/>supply myself with endless combinations of forms <lb/>and
                              imagery. Now, supposing for a moment that <lb/>whatever is interesting
                              in these objects may be as <lb/>vividly described in prose, why am I
                              to be con-<lb/>demned, if to such description I have endeavoured
                              <lb/>to superadd the charm which, by the consent of all <lb/>nations,
                              is acknowledged to exist in metrical lan-<lb/>guage ? To this, by such
                              as are unconvinced by <lb/>what I have already said, it may be
                              answered, that <lb/>a very small part of the pleasure given by Poetry
                              <lb/> depends upon the metre, and that it is injudicious <lb/>to write
                              in metre, unless it be accompanied with<pb n="xlv"/>
            <milestone n="xlv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>the other artificial distinctions of style
                              with which <lb/>metre is usually accompanied, and that by such
                              <lb/>deviation more will be lost from the shock which <lb/>will be
                              thereby given to the Reader’s associations, <lb/>than will be
                              counterbalanced by any pleasure which <lb/>he can derive from the
                              general power of numbers. <lb/>In answer to those who still contend
                              for the neces-<lb/>sity of accompanying metre with certain
                              appropri-<lb/>ate colours of style in order to the accomplishment
                              <lb/>of its appropriate end, and who also, in my opinion, <lb/>greatly
                              under-rate the power of metre in itself, it <lb/>might perhaps, as far
                              as relates to these Poems, <lb/>have been almost sufficient to
                              observe, that poems <lb/>are extant, written upon more humble
                              subjects, <lb/>and in a more naked and simple style than I have
                              <lb/>aimed at, which poems have continued to give <lb/>pleasure from
                              generation to generation. Now, if <lb/>nakedness and simplicity be a
                              defect, the fact here <lb/>mentioned affords a strong presumption that
                              poems <lb/>somewhat less naked and simple are capable of<pb n="xlvi"/>
            <milestone n="xlvi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>affording pleasure
                              at the present day ; and, what <lb/>I wished <emph>chiefly</emph> to
                              attempt, at present, was to jus-<lb/>tify myself for having written
                              under the impression <lb/>of this belief.</p>
         <p>But I might point out various causes why, when <lb/>the style is manly,
                              and the subject of some im-<lb/>portance, words metrically arranged
                              will long con-<lb/>tinue to impart such a pleasure to mankind as he
                              <lb/>who is sensible of the extent of that pleasure will <lb/>be
                              desirous to impart. The end of Poetry is to <lb/>produce excitement in
                              co-existence with an over-<lb/>balance of pleasure. Now, by the
                              supposition, <lb/>excitement is an unusual and irregular state of
                              <lb/>the mind; ideas and feelings do not in that state <lb/>succeed
                              each other in accustomed order. But, if <lb/>the words by which this
                              excitement is produced <lb/>are in themselves powerful, or the images
                              and <lb/>feelings have an undue proportion of pain con-<lb/>nected
                              with them, there is some danger that the <pb n="xlvii"/>
            <milestone n="xlvii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>excitement may be carried beyond
                              its proper <lb/>bounds. Now the co-presence of something
                              regu-<lb/>lar, something to which the mind has been accus-<lb/>tomed
                              in various moods and in a less excited state, <lb/>cannot but have
                              great efficacy in tempering and re-<lb/>straining the passion by an
                              intertexture of ordinary <lb/>feeling, and of feeling not strictly and
                              necessarily <lb/>connected with the passion. This is unquestionably
                              <lb/>true, and hence, though the opinion will at first <lb/>appear
                              paradoxical, from the tendency of metre to <lb/>divest language in a
                              certain degree of its reality, <lb/>and thus to throw a sort of half
                              consciousness of <lb/>unsubstantial existence over the whole
                              composition, <lb/>there can be little doubt but that more pathetic
                              <lb/>situations and sentiments, that is, those which <lb/>have a
                              greater proportion of pain connected with <lb/>them, may be endured in
                              metrical composition, <lb/>especially in rhyme, than in prose. The
                              metre of <lb/>the old ballads is very artless; yet they contain
                              <lb/>many passages which would illustrate this opinion, <pb n="xlviii"/>
            <milestone n="xlviii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>and, I hope, if
                              the following Poems be attentively <lb/>perused, similar instances
                              will be found in them. <lb/>This opinion may be further illustrated by
                              appeal-<lb/>ing to the Reader’s own experience of the reluctance
                              <lb/>with which he comes to the re-perusal of the dis-<lb/>tressful
                              parts of Clarissa Harlowe, or the Gamester. <lb/>While
                              Shakespeare’s writings, in the most pathetic <lb/>scenes, never
                              act upon us as pathetic beyond the <lb/>bounds of pleasure—an
                              effect which, in a much <lb/>greater degree than might at first be
                              imagined, is <lb/>to be ascribed to small, but continual and regular
                              <lb/>impulses of pleasurable surprise from the metrical
                              <lb/>arrangement.—On the other hand (what it must <lb/>be
                              allowed will much more frequently happen) <lb/>if the Poet’s
                              words should be incommensurate <lb/>with the passion, and inadequate
                              to raise the <lb/>Reader to a height of desirable excitement, then,
                              <lb/>(unless the Poet’s choice of his metre has been
                              <lb/>grossly injudicious) in the feelings of pleasure <lb/>which the
                              Reader has been accustomed to con- <pb n="xlix"/>
            <milestone n="xlix" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>nect with metre in general, and in the
                              feeling, <lb/>whether cheerful or melancholy, which he has <lb/>been
                              accustomed to connect with that particular <lb/>movement of metre,
                              there will be found some-<lb/>thing which will greatly contribute to
                              impart pas-<lb/>sion to the words, and to effect the complex end
                              <lb/>which the Poet proposes to himself.</p>
         <p>If I had undertaken a systematic defence of the <lb/>theory upon which
                              these poems are written, it <lb/>would have been my duty to develope
                              the various <lb/>causes upon which the pleasure received from
                              <lb/>metrical language depends. Among the chief of <lb/>these causes
                              is to be reckoned a principle which <lb/>must be well known to those
                              who have made any <lb/>of the Arts the object of accurate reflection ;
                              I <lb/>mean the pleasure which the mind derives from <lb/>the
                              perception of similitude in dissimilitude. This <lb/>principle is the
                              great spring of the activity of our <lb/>minds, and their chief
                              feeder. From this prin- <pb n="l"/>
            <milestone unit="page" n="l"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>ciple the direction of the sexual appetite, and all
                              <lb/>the passions connected with it, take their origin: <lb/>it is the
                              life of our ordinary conversation ; and <lb/>upon the accuracy with
                              which similitude in <lb/>dissimilitude, and dissimilitude in
                              similitude are <lb/>perceived, depend our taste and our moral
                              feel-<lb/>ings. It would not have been a useless employ-<lb/>ment to
                              have applied this principle to the con-<lb/>sideration of metre, and
                              to have shown that metre <lb/>is hence enabled to afford much
                              pleasure, and <lb/>to have pointed out in what manner that pleasure
                              <lb/>is produced. But my limits will not permit me to <lb/>enter upon
                              this subject, and I must content myself <lb/>with a general
                              summary.</p>
         <p>I have said that Poetry is the spontaneous overflow <lb/>of powerful
                              feelings: it takes its origin from emo-<lb/>tion recollected in
                              tranquillity : the emotion is <lb/>contemplated till by a species of
                              reaction the <lb/>tranquillity gradually disappears, and an emotion,
                                   <pb n="li"/>
            <milestone n="li" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>kindred to
                              that which was before the subject of <lb/>contemplation, is gradually
                              produced, and does <lb/>itself actually exist in the mind. In this
                              mood <lb/>successful composition generally begins, and in a <lb/>mood
                              similar to this it is carried on; but the <lb/>emotion, of whatever
                              kind and in whatever degree, <lb/>from various causes is qualified by
                              various plea-<lb/>sures, so that in describing any passions
                              what-<lb/>soever, which are voluntarily described, the mind <lb/>will
                              upon the whole be in a state of enjoyment. <lb/>Now, if Nature be thus
                              cautious in preserving in <lb/>a state of enjoyment a being thus
                              employed, <lb/>the Poet ought to profit by the lesson thus held
                              <lb/>forth to him, and ought especially to take care, <lb/>that
                              whatever passions he communicates to his <lb/>Reader, those passions,
                              if his Reader’s mind be <lb/>sound and vigorous, should always
                              be accompa-<lb/>nied with an overbalance of pleasure. Now the
                              <lb/>music of harmonious metrical language, the sense <lb/>of
                              difficulty overcome, and the blind association of <pb n="lii"/>
            <milestone n="lii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>pleasure which has
                              been previously received from <lb/>works of rhyme or metre of the same
                              or similar <lb/>construction, an indistinct perception perpetually
                              <lb/>renewed of language closely resembling that of <lb/>real life,
                              and yet, in the circumstance of metre, <lb/>differing from it so
                              widely, all these imperceptibly <lb/>make up a complex feeling of
                              delight, which is <lb/>of the most important use in tempering the
                              painful <lb/>feeling which will always be found intermingled <lb/>with
                              powerful descriptions of the deeper passions. <lb/>This effect is
                              always produced in pathetic and im-<lb/>passioned poetry ; while, in
                              lighter compositions, <lb/>the ease and gracefulness with which the
                              Poet <lb/>manages his numbers are themselves confessedly a
                              <lb/>principal source of the gratification of the Reader. <lb/>I might
                              perhaps include all which it is <emph>necessary</emph>
            <lb/>to say upon this subject by affirming, what few <lb/>persons will
                              deny, that of two descriptions, either <lb/>of passions, manners, or
                              characters, each of them <lb/>equally well executed, the one in prose
                              and the <pb n="liii"/>
            <milestone n="liii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>other
                              in verse, the verse will be read a hundred <lb/>times where the prose
                              is read once. We see that <lb/>Pope, by the power of verse alone, has
                              contrived <lb/>to render the plainest common sense interesting,
                              <lb/>and even frequently to invest it with the appear-<lb/>ance of
                              passion. In consequence of these con-<lb/>victions I related in metre
                              the Tale of G<hi rend="small">oody</hi>
            <lb/>B<hi rend="small">lake</hi> and H<hi rend="small">arry</hi> G<hi rend="small">ill</hi>, which is one of the <lb/>rudest of this
                              collection. I wished to draw atten-<lb/>tion to the truth, that the
                              power of the human <lb/>imagination is sufficient to produce such
                              changes <lb/>even in our physical nature as might almost appear
                              <lb/>miraculous. The truth is an important one; the <lb/>fact (for it
                              is a <emph>fact</emph>) is a valuable illustration of it. <lb/>And I
                              have the satisfaction of knowing that it has <lb/>been communicated to
                              many hundreds of people <lb/>who would never have heard of it, had it
                              not <lb/>been narrated as a Ballad, and in a more impres-<lb/>sive
                              metre than is usual in Ballads.</p>
         <pb n="liv"/>
         <milestone n="liv" unit="page"/>
         <p>Having thus explained a few of the reasons why <lb/>I have written in
                              verse, and why I have chosen <lb/>subjects from common life, and
                              endeavoured to <lb/>bring my language near to the real language of
                              <lb/>men, if I have been too minute in pleading my <lb/>own cause, I
                              have at the same time been treat-<lb/>ing a subject of general
                              interest; and it is for this <lb/>reason that I request the
                              Reader’s permission to <lb/>add a few words with reference
                              solely to these <lb/>particular poems, and to some defects which will
                              <lb/>probably be found in them. I am sensible that <lb/>my
                              associations must have sometimes been par-<lb/>ticular instead of
                              general, and that, consequently, <lb/>giving to things a false
                              importance, sometimes <lb/>from diseased impulses I may have written
                              upon <lb/>unworthy subjects; but I am less apprehensive <lb/>on this
                              account, than that my language may fre-<lb/>quently have suffered from
                              those arbitrary con-<lb/>nections of feelings and ideas with
                              particular words<pb n="lv"/>
            <milestone n="lv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>and phrases, from which no man can altogether <lb/>protect
                              himself. Hence I have no doubt, that, in <lb/>some instances, feelings
                              even of the ludicrous may <lb/>be given to my Readers by expressions
                              which ap-<lb/>peared to me tender and pathetic. Such faulty
                              <lb/>expressions, were I convinced they were faulty <lb/>at present,
                              and that they must necessarily con-<lb/>tinue to be so, I would
                              willingly take all rea-<lb/>sonable pains to correct. But it is
                              dangerous to <lb/>make these alterations on the simple authority of a
                              <lb/>few individuals, or even of certain classes of men; <lb/>for
                              where the understanding of an Author is not <lb/>convinced, or his
                              feelings altered, this cannot <lb/>be done without great injury to
                              himself: for his <lb/>own feelings are his stay and support, and, if
                              he <lb/>sets them aside in one instance, he may be indu-<lb/>ced to
                              repeat this act till his mind loses all con-<lb/>fidence in itself,
                              and becomes utterly debilitated. <lb/>To this it may be added, that
                              the Reader ought <pb n="lvi"/>
            <milestone n="lvi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>never to forget that he is himself exposed to the
                              <lb/>same errors as the Poet, and perhaps in a much <lb/>greater
                              degree : for there can be no presumption <lb/>in saying, that it is
                              not probable he will be so well <lb/>acquainted with the various
                              stages of meaning <lb/>through which words have passed, or with the
                              <lb/>fickleness or stability of the relations of particular <lb/>ideas
                              to each other ; and above all, since he is <lb/>so much less
                              interested in the subject, he may <lb/>decide lightly and
                              carelessly.</p>
         <p>Long as I have detained my Reader, I hope he <lb/>will permit me to
                              caution him against a mode of <lb/>false criticism which has been
                              applied to Poetry <lb/>in which the language closely resembles that of
                              <lb/>life and nature. Such verses have been triumphed <lb/>over in
                              parodies of which Dr. Johnson’s stanza <lb/>is a fair specimen.
                                   <pb n="lvii"/>
            <milestone n="lvii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>“ I put my hat upon my head,</l>
                  <l>And walk’d into the Strand,</l>
                  <l>And there I met another man</l>
                  <l>Whose hat was in his hand.”</l>
               </lg>
            </q>Immediately under these lines I will place one <lb/>of
                              the most justly admired stanzas of the “<emph> Babes</emph>
            <lb/>in the Wood.”<lb/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>“ These pretty Babes with hand in hand</l>
                  <l>Went wandering up and down;</l>
                  <l>But never more they saw the Man</l>
                  <l>Approaching from the Town.”</l>
               </lg>
            </q>In both of these stanzas the words, and the order
                              <lb/>of the words, in no respect differ from the most
                              <lb/>unimpassioned conversation. There are words <lb/>in both, for
                              example, “ the Strand,” and “ the <lb/>Town,”
                              connected with none but the most fami-<lb/>liar ideas; yet the one
                              stanza we admit as admi-<lb/>rable, and the other as a fair example of
                                   the<pb n="lviii"/>
            <milestone n="lviii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>superlatively contemptible. Whence arises this
                              <lb/>difference? Not from the metre, not from the <lb/>language, not
                              from the order of the words; but <lb/>the <emph>matter</emph>expressed
                              in Dr. Johnson’s stanza is <lb/>contemptible. The proper method
                              of treating <lb/>trivial and simple verses, to which Dr.
                              Johnson’s <lb/>stanza would be a fair parallelism, is not to
                              say, <lb/>This is a bad kind of poetry, or This is not po-<lb/>etry ;
                              but This wants sense ; it is neither interest-<lb/>ing in itself, nor
                              can <emph>lead</emph> to any thing interesting; <lb/>the images
                              neither originate in that sane state <lb/>of feeling which arises out
                              of thought, nor can <lb/>excite thought or feeling in the Reader. This
                              is <lb/>the only sensible manner of dealing with such <lb/>verses. Why
                              trouble yourself about the species <lb/>till you have previously
                              decided upon the genus ? <lb/>Why take pains to prove that an ape is
                              not <lb/>a Newton when it is self-evident that he is not <lb/>a man
                              ?</p>
         <pb n="lix"/>
         <milestone n="lix" unit="page"/>
         <p>I have one request to make of my Reader, which <lb/>is, that in judging
                              these Poems he would decide <lb/>by his own feelings genuinely, and
                              not by reflec-<lb/>tion upon what will probably be the judgment of
                              <lb/>others. How common is it to hear a person say, <lb/>“I
                              myself do not object to this style of compo-<lb/>sition, or this or
                              that expression, but to such and <lb/>such classes of people it will
                              appear mean or <lb/>ludicrous.” This mode of criticism, so
                              destructive <lb/>of all sound unadulterated judgment, is almost
                              <lb/>universal: I have therefore to request, that the <lb/>Reader
                              would abide independently by his own <lb/>feelings, and that if he
                              finds himself affected he <lb/>would not suffer such conjectures to
                              interfere with <lb/>his pleasure.</p>
         <p>If an Author by any single composition has im-<lb/>pressed us with
                              respect for his talents, it is useful <lb/>to consider this as
                              affording a presumption, that, <pb n="lx"/>
            <milestone n="lx" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>on other occasions where we have been
                              displeased, <lb/>he nevertheless may not have written ill or
                              ab-<lb/>surdly; and, further, to give him so much credit <lb/>for this
                              one composition as may induce us to <lb/>review what has displeased us
                              with more care <lb/>than we should otherwise have bestowed upon it.
                              <lb/>This is not only an act of justice, but, in our de-<lb/>cisions
                              upon poetry especially, may conduce in a <lb/>high degree to the
                              improvement of our own taste : <lb/>for an <emph>accurate</emph> taste
                              in poetry, and in all the other <lb/>arts, as Sir Joshua Reynolds has
                              observed, is an <lb/>
            <emph>acquired</emph> talent, which can only be
                              produced by <lb/>thought, and a long continued intercourse with
                              <lb/>the best models of composition. This is men-<lb/>tioned, not with
                              so ridiculous a purpose as to pre-<lb/>vent the most inexperienced
                              Reader from judging <lb/>for himself, (I have already said that I wish
                              him <lb/>to judge for himself;) but merely to temper the <lb/>rashness
                              of decision, and to suggest, that, if <pb n="lxi"/>
            <milestone n="lxi" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>Poetry be a subject on which much time has
                              <lb/>not been bestowed, the judgment may be er-<lb/>roneous; and that
                              in many cases it necessarily <lb/>will be so.</p>
         <p>I know that nothing would have so effectually <lb/>contributed to
                              further the end which I have in <lb/>view, as to have shown of what
                              kind the pleasure <lb/>is, and how the pleasure is produced, which is
                              <lb/>confessedly produced by metrical composition <lb/>essentially
                              different from that which I have here <lb/>endeavoured to recommend :
                              for the Reader will <lb/>say that he has been pleased by such
                              composition ; <lb/>and what can I do more for him? The power of
                              <lb/>any art is limited; and he will suspect, that, if I <lb/>propose
                              to furnish him with new friends, it is only <lb/>upon condition of his
                              abandoning his old friends. <lb/>Besides, as I have said, the Reader
                              is himself <lb/>conscious of the pleasure which he has received<pb n="lxii"/>
            <milestone n="lxii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>from such
                              composition, composition to which he <lb/>has peculiarly attached the
                              endearing name of <lb/>Poetry; and all men feel an habitual gratitude,
                              <lb/>and something of an honorable bigotry for the <lb/>objects which
                              have long continued to please them ; <lb/>we not only wish to be
                              pleased, but to be pleased <lb/>in that particular way in which we
                              have been <lb/>accustomed to be pleased. There is a host of
                              <lb/>arguments in these feelings ; and I should be the <lb/>less able
                              to combat them successfully, as I am <lb/>willing to allow, that, in
                              order entirely to enjoy <lb/>the Poetry which I am recommending, it
                              would <lb/>be necessary to give up much of what is ordinarily
                              <lb/>enjoyed. But, would my limits have permitted <lb/>me to point out
                              how this pleasure is produced, I <lb/>might have removed many
                              obstacles, and assisted <lb/>my Reader in perceiving that the powers
                              of lan-<lb/>guage are not so limited as he may suppose; and <lb/>that
                              it is possible that poetry may give other<pb n="lxiii"/>
            <milestone n="lxiii" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>enjoyments, of a purer, more
                              lasting, and more <lb/>exquisite nature. This part of my subject I
                              <lb/>have not altogether neglected ; but it has been <lb/>less my
                              present aim to prove, that the interest <lb/>excited by some other
                              kinds of poetry is less <lb/>vivid, and less worthy of the nobler
                              powers of the <lb/>mind, than to offer reasons for presuming, that,
                              <lb/>if the object which I have proposed to myself <lb/>were
                              adequately attained, a species of poetry <lb/>would be produced, which
                              is genuine poetry; <lb/>in its nature well adapted to interest
                              man-<lb/>kind permanently, and likewise important in <lb/>the
                              multiplicity and quality of its moral rela-<lb/>tions.</p>
         <p>From what has been said, and from a perusal of <lb/>the Poems, the
                              Reader will be able clearly to <lb/>perceive the object which I have
                              proposed to <lb/>myself: he will determine how far I have attained <pb n="lxiv"/>
            <milestone n="lxiv" unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>this object
                              ; and, what is a much more important <lb/>question, whether it be
                              worth attaining : and upon <lb/>the decision of these two questions
                              will rest my <lb/>claim to the approbation of the public.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
