<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1805: [Endnotes on The Thorn, Tintern Abbey, and the Ancient Mariner (varies)]</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB05-1_NOTES</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="NOTES">
                  <title>[NOTES]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB05-1">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB05-1.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1805</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">201 to 204</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="201"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <div xml:id="noteThorn">
            <head>
               <emph>NOTES. </emph>
            </head>
            <p rend="note">
               <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="small">ote</hi> to T<hi rend="small">he</hi> T<hi rend="small">horn</hi>, p.
                                        35.</hi>—This Poem ought to have <lb/>been preceded by
                                   an introductory Poem, which I have <lb/>been prevented from
                                   writing by never having felt myself <lb/>in a mood when it was
                                   probable that I should write it well. <lb/>—The character
                                   which I have here introduced speaking <lb/>is sufficiently
                                   common. The Reader will perhaps have <lb/>a general notion of it,
                                   if he has ever known a man, a <lb/>Captain of a small trading
                                   vessel, for example, who, being <lb/>past the middle age of life,
                                   had retired upon an annuity or <lb/>small independent income to
                                   some village or country town <lb/>of which he was not a native,
                                   or in which he had not been <lb/>accustomed to live. Such men,
                                   having little to do, become<lb/>credulous and talkative from
                                   indolence ; and from the <lb/>same cause, and other predisposing
                                   causes by which it is <lb/>probable that such men may have been
                                   affected, they <lb/>are prone to superstition. On which account
                                   it appeared <lb/>to me proper to select a character like this to
                                   exhibit some <lb/>of the general laws by which superstition acts
                                   upon the <lb/>mind. Superstitious men are almost always men of
                                   slow <lb/>faculties and deep feelings : their minds are not loose
                                   <lb/>but adhesive; they have a reasonable share of imagination,
                                   by <lb/>which word I mean the faculty which produces impressive
                                   <pb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>effects out of simple elements ; but they are
                                   utterly desti-<lb/>tute of fancy, the power by which pleasure and
                                   surprise <lb/>are excited by sudden varieties of situation and by
                                   accu-<lb/>mulated imagery.</p>
            <p rend="note">It was my wish in this poem to shew the manner in which
                                   <lb/>such men cleave to the same ideas; and to follow the turns
                                   <lb/>of passion, always different, yet not palpably different, by
                                   <lb/>which their conversation is swayed. I had two objects to
                                   <lb/>attain ; first, to represent a picture which should not be
                                   <lb/>unimpressive, yet consistent with the character that should
                                   <lb/>describe it; secondly, while I adhered to the style in which
                                   <lb/>such persons describe, to take care that words, which in
                                   <lb/>their minds are impregnated with passion, should likewise
                                   <lb/>convey passion to Readers who are not accustomed to
                                   <lb/>sympathize with men feeling in that manner or using such
                                   <lb/>language. It seemed to me that this might be done by
                                   <lb/>calling in the assistance of Lyrical and rapid Metre. It
                                   <lb/>was necessary that the Poem, to be natural, should in
                                   <lb/>reality move slowly ; yet I hoped, that, by the aid of the
                                   <lb/>metre, to those who should at all enter into the spirit of
                                   <lb/>the Poem, it would appear to move quickly. The Reader
                                   <lb/>will have the kindness to excuse this note, as I am sensible
                                   <lb/>that an introductory Poem is necessary to give this Poem
                                   <lb/>its full effect.</p>
            <p rend="note">Upon this occasion I will request permission to add a
                                   few <lb/>words closely connected with T<hi rend="small">he</hi>
                                        T<hi rend="small">horn</hi> and many other
                                   <pb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>Poems in these Volumes. There is a numerous class
                                   of <lb/>readers who imagine that the same words cannot be
                                   re-<lb/>peated without tautology : this is a great error ;
                                   virtual tau-<lb/>tology is much oftener produced by using
                                   different words <lb/>when the meaning is exactly the same. Words,
                                   a Poet’s <lb/>words more particularly, ought to be weighed
                                   in the ba-<lb/>lance of feeling, and not measured by the space
                                   which <lb/>they occupy upon paper. For the Reader cannot be too
                                   <lb/>often reminded that Poetry is passion : it is the history or
                                   <lb/>science of feelings: now every man must know that an
                                   <lb/>attempt is rarely made to communicate impassioned
                                   feel-<lb/>ings without something of an accompanying consciousness
                                   <lb/>of the inadequateness of our own powers, or the deficiencies
                                   <lb/>of language. During such efforts there will be a craving
                                   <lb/>in the mind, and as long as it is unsatisfied the Speaker
                                   <lb/>will cling to the same words, or words of the same
                                   cha-<lb/>racter. There are also various other reasons why
                                   repeti-<lb/>tion and apparent tautology are frequently beauties
                                   of the <lb/>highest kind. Among the chief of these reasons is the
                                   <lb/>interest which the mind attaches to words, not only as
                                   <lb/>symbols of the passion, but as <emph>things</emph>, active
                                   and efficient, <lb/>which are of themselves part of the passion.
                                   And furth-<lb/>er, from a spirit of fondness, exultation, and
                                   gratitude, <lb/>the mind luxuriates in the repetition of words
                                   which ap-<lb/>pear successfully to communicate its feelings. The
                                   truth <lb/>of these remarks might be shown by innumerable
                                   passages <lb/>from the Bible, and from the impassioned Poetry of
                                   every <lb/>nation.</p>
            <pb n="204"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p rend="note">“ Awake, awake, Deborah: awake, awake, utter a
                                   song : <lb/>Arise, Barak, and lead thy captivity captive, thou
                                   Son of <lb/>Abinoam.<lb/>At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay
                                   down : at her feet he <lb/>bowed, he fell ; where he bowed there
                                   he fell down dead. <lb/>Why is his Chariot so long in coming? Why
                                   tarry the <lb/>Wheels of his Chariot?”—Judges, chap.
                                   5th. verses 12th, 27th, and part of 28th.—See also the
                                   whole of that tumul-<lb/>tuous and wonderful Poem.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="noteTintern">
            <p rend="note">
               <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="small">ote</hi> to the Poem
                                             O<hi rend="small">n revisiting the</hi> W<hi rend="small">ye</hi>, p. 191.</hi>—<lb/>I have
                                   not ventured to call this Poem an Ode; but it was <lb/>written
                                   with a hope that in the transitions, and the impas-<lb/>sioned
                                   music of the versification, would be found the prin-<lb/>cipal
                                   requisites of that species of composition.</p>
         </div>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <trailer>
            <hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>END OF VOL. I.</hi>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <emph>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>R. Taylor
                                   and Co. Printers, 38, Shoe-Lane. </emph>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
