<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edition Information and Descriptions</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Romantic Circles</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The 1798 descriptions were revised and so come from an email from Bruce, Tuesday,
               August 26, 2025, at 6:41 pm, with no text written by in it, responding to a query on
               a different topic; email title, "Table of Contents Oddity." The others come from an
               email from Bruce, responding to "Decision Needed," dated July 7, 2025, 3:45pm.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <list type="gloss">
            <label xml:id="LB98-Bbl"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Southey’s copy, Bristol (BL)</label>
            <item>1798: Robert Southey’s copy of Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint. Described sometimes as
               an 'archival' copy, it contains both S. T. Coleridge’s 'Lewti,' from the first state
               of the printing (see Reed, A3) and the 'Advertisement' and S. T. Coleridge’s 'The
               Nightingale' from the second state. British Library.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-BEDDOES"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Beddoes's copy, Bristol, with "Domiciliary
               Verses" (BL)</label>
            <item>1798: Thomas Beddoes's copy of Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, second state. British
               Library (Ashley 2250). As Reed notes, A3, a leaf has been added after p. 62,
               containing 'Domiciliary Verses,' an apparent parody probably written by Beddoes
               himself.</item>
            <label xml:id="lb98-bnypl"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Fricker's copy, Bristol, with "Lewti" (NYPL)</label>
            <item>1798: Martha Fricker’s copy of Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, first state. With
               corrections in S. T. Coleridge’s hand. Berg Collection, New York Public
               Library.</item>
            <label xml:id="lb98-bp"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Bristol, with "Lewti" (Princeton)</label>
            <item>1798: Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, first state, containing S. T. Coleridge’s
               'Lewti.' Robert H. Taylor collection, Firestone Library, Princeton University.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-BY"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Bristol, with "The Nightingale" and
               "Lewti" (Yale)</label>
            <item>1798: Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, second state, containing both 'Lewti' and 'The
               Nightingale.' Beinecke Library, Yale University.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-by1"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Bristol, with "Lewti" (Yale)</label>
            <item>1798: Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, first state. Tinker collection, Beinecke
               Library, Yale University.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-L"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> London, inscription by Wordsworth (Wordsworth Trust)</label>
            <item>1798: Lyrical Ballads, London imprint, third state. Presentation copy from William Wordsworth to his nephew, John Wordsworth, 1844 inscription (Wordsworth Trust)</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-pinney"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Pinney's copy, Bristol, with "The Nightingale" (Harvard)</label>
            <item>1798: J. F. Pinney’s copy of Lyrical Ballads, Bristol imprint, second state. Houghton Library, Harvard University.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB98-STC"><hi rend="bold">1798:</hi> Coleridge's copy, Bristol, with "The Nightingale" (Cambridge)</label>
            <item>1798: S. T. Coleridge's copy, 1798, Bristol impriint, second state. (Wren Library, Trinity College, Cambridge University)</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-1"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 1, 2nd ed., London (SFU).</label>
            <item>1800: Lyrical Ballads, London imprint (Longman, with Bristol printer), volume 1, second edition (Simon Fraser University Library)</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-1a"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 1, 2nd ed., London, with uncancelled leaf a3 (Wordsworth Trust)</label>
            <item>1800: volume 1 of the second edition with uncancelled leaf a3 (Wordsworth Trust): this edition accidentally 
               includes both the original and revised preface, changed when "Christabel" couldn't be included, strangely ordered.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-1b"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 1, 2nd ed., London, with uncancelled leaf a3 (BL)</label>
            <item>1800: volume 1 of the second edition, London imprint, with uncancelled leaf a3 (British Library): includes only one page
               of the cancelland and the cancel, each.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-2"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 2, 2nd ed., London (SFU)</label>
            <item>1800: volume 2 of the second edition, London imprint (Simon 
               Fraser University Library); rushed printing.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-2a"><hi rend="bold">1800</hi> vol. 2, 2nd ed., London (UC Boulder), with "Michael" cancel</label>
            <item>1800: volume 2 of the second edition with 'Michael' cancel and new errata sheet (University of Colorado-Boulder Library): corrections to errors from the rushed printing.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-2S"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 2, 2nd ed., London with "Michael" paste-in  (Swarthmore)</label>
            <item>1800: volume 2 of the second edition, London imprint (Swarthmore College Library), with 'Michael' paste-in.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB00-2y"><hi rend="bold">1800:</hi> vol. 2, 2nd ed., author's revisions for printing 3rd ed., 1802 (Yale)</label>
            <item>1800: proof-sheets from the volume 2 of the second edition with authorial corrections to be made in the third edition of 1802 (Beinecke Library, Yale University)</item>
            <label xml:id="LB02-1"><hi rend="bold">1802:</hi> S. H.'s copy, vol. 1, 3rd ed., London, with inscription (Wordsworth Trust)</label>
            <item>1802: Sarah Hutchinson's copy, volume 1 of the third edition, London imprint, with an inscription by Mary Wordsworth (Wordsworth Trust); 'The Complaint of a forsaken Indian Woman' moved to vol. 2.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB02-2"><hi rend="bold">1802:</hi> S. H.'s copy, vol. 2, 3rd ed., London, with Appendix (Wordsworth Trust)</label>
            <item>1802: Sarah Hutchinson's copy, volume 2 of the third edition, London imprint (Wordsworth Trust); contains 
               the Appendix.</item>
            <label xml:id="LBP1-campbell"><hi rend="bold">1802:</hi> Campbell's copy, vol. 1, unauthorized 3rd ed., Philadelphia (Harvard)</label>
            <item>1802: J. Dykes Campbell's copy, volume 1 of the third edition (unauthorized), Philadelphia imprint, (Houghton Library, Harvard University); 
               contains both the Advertisement and Preface and a disordered table of contents. Notes for vol. 1 moved to the end of vol. 2.</item>
            <label xml:id="lbphil-2"><hi rend="bold">1802:</hi> Campbell's copy, vol. 2, unauthorized 3rd ed., Philadelphia (Harvard)</label>
            <item>1802: J. Dykes Campbell's copy, volume 2 of the third edition (unauthorized), Philadelphia imprint (Houghton Library, Harvard University); contains the 
               notes for both volume 1 and 2.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB05-1"><hi rend="bold">1805:</hi> vol. 1, 4th ed., London (SFU)</label>
            <item>1805: volume 1 of the fourth edition, London imprint (Simon Fraser University Library).</item>
            <label xml:id="LB05-1RS"><hi rend="bold">1805:</hi> Southey's corrections, vol. 1, 4th ed., London (BL)</label>
            <item>1805: volume 1 of the fourth edition, London imprint (British Library), with corrections by Robert 
               Southey.</item>
            <label xml:id="LB05-2"><hi rend="bold">1805:</hi> vol. 2, 4th ed., London (SFU)</label>
            <item>1805: volume 2 of the fourth edition, London imprint (Simon Fraser University Library).</item>
            <label xml:id="LB05-2a"><hi rend="bold">1805:</hi> vol. 2, 4th ed., London (various)</label>
            <item>1805: volume 2 of the fourth edition, London imprint (based on several library copies, including Princeton, Harvard, and Simon Fraser Universities).</item>
            <label xml:id="LB05-2RS"><hi rend="bold">1805:</hi> Southey's corrections, vol. 2, 4th ed., London (BL)</label>
            <item>1805: volume 2 of the fourth edition, London imprint (British Library), with corrections by Robert Southey.</item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
