<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1800: Preface</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">LB00-1a_PREF</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="PREF">
                  <title>Preface</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="LB00-1a">
                  <ptr target="../XML/LB00-1a.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace/>
                     <date>1800</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">vii to xlvi.</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">45</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="a3cancelland">
            <pb/>
            <head>[Original leaf, accidentally printed along with its
                              replacement]<lb/>
               <lb/>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>The first Volume of these Poems has already been <lb/>submitted to
                              general perusal. It was published, <lb/>as an experiment which, I
                              hoped, might be of some <lb/>use to ascertain, how far, by fitting to
                              metrical <lb/>arrangement a selection of the real language of <lb/>men
                              in a state of vivid sensation, that sort of <lb/>pleasure and that
                              quantity of pleasure may be <lb/>imparted, which a Poet may rationally
                              endeavour <lb/>to impart.</p>
            <p>I had formed no very inaccurate estimate of the <lb/>probable effect of
                              those Poems : I flattered myself <lb/>that they who should be pleased
                              with them would <lb/>read them with more than common pleasure : and
                                   <pb n="vi"/>
               <milestone n="vi" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>on the other
                              hand I was well aware that by those <lb/>who should dislike them they
                              would be read with <lb/>more than common dislike. The result has
                              <lb/>differed from my expectation in this only, that I <lb/>have
                              pleased a greater number, than I ventured <lb/>to hope I should
                              please. </p>
            <p xml:id="a3orig">For the sake of variety and from a consciousness <lb/>of
                              my own weakness I have again requested the <lb/>assistance of a Friend
                              who contributed largely to <lb/>the first volume,* and who has now
                              furnished me <lb/>with the Poem of Christabel, without which I
                              <lb/>should not have yet ventured to present a second <lb/>volume to
                              the public. I should not however have <lb/>requested this assistance,
                              had I not believed that <lb/>the poems of my Friend would in a great
                              measure <lb/>have the same tendency as my own, and that,<lb/>
               <note place="foot">* The Poems supplied by my Friend, are the
                                        <hi>Antient <lb/>Mariner</hi>, the <hi>Foster-Mother’s
                                        Tale</hi>, the <hi>Nightin-<lb/>gale</hi>, the
                                        D<hi>ungeon</hi>, and the Poem entitled,
                                   L<hi>ove</hi>.</note>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>[end original leaf]</p>
         </div>
         <pb xml:id="endOrig"/>
         <milestone unit="page" n="vii"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <div>
            <p>though there would be found a difference, there
                              <lb/>would be found no discordance in the colours of <lb/>our style;
                              as our opinions on the subject of poetry <lb/>do almost entirely
                              coincide.</p>
            <p>Several of my Friends are anxious for the success <lb/>of these Poems
                              from a belief, that if the views, <lb/>with which they were composed,
                              were indeed <lb/>realized, a class of Poetry would be produced,
                              <lb/>well adapted to interest mankind permanently, <lb/>and not
                              unimportant in the multiplicity and in the <lb/>quality of its moral
                              relations : and on this account <lb/>they have advised me to prefix a
                              systematic defence <lb/>of the theory, upon which the poems were
                              written. <lb/>But I was unwilling to undertake the task, because
                              <lb/>I knew that on this occasion the Reader would <lb/>look coldly
                              upon my arguments, since I might <lb/>be suspected of having been
                              principally influenced <lb/>by the selfish and foolish hope of
                                   <emph>reasoning</emph> him <lb/>into an approbation of these
                              particular Poems :<pb n="viii"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="viii"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>and I was still more unwilling to undertake the <lb/>task,
                              because adequately to display my opinions <lb/>and fully to enforce my
                              arguments would require <lb/>a space wholly disproportionate to the
                              nature of a <lb/>preface. For to treat the subject with the
                              clear-<lb/>ness and coherence, of which I believe it <orig rend="long s">s</orig>u<orig rend="long s">s</orig>cepti-<lb/>ble, it would be necessary to give a full account
                              <lb/>of the present state of the public taste in this <lb/>country,
                              and to determine how far this taste is <lb/>healthy or depraved ;
                              which again could not be <lb/>determined, without pointing out, in
                              what man-<lb/>ner language and the human mind act and react <lb/>on
                              each other, and without retracing the revolu-<lb/>tions not of
                              literature alone but likewise of society <lb/>itself. I have therefore
                              altogether declined to <lb/>enter regularly upon this defence ; yet I
                              am sensi-<lb/>ble, that there would be some impropriety in
                              <lb/>abruptly obtruding upon the Public, without a <lb/>few words of
                              introduction, Poems so materially <lb/>different from those, upon
                              which general appro-<lb/>bation is at present bestowed.</p>
            <pb n="ix"/>
            <milestone unit="page" n="xi."/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>It is supposed, that by the act of writing in verse <lb/>an Author makes
                              a formal engagement that he <lb/>will gratify certain known habits of
                              association, <lb/>that he not only thus apprizes the Reader that
                              <lb/>certain classes of ideas and expressions will be <lb/>found in
                              his book, but that others will be care-<lb/>fully excluded. This
                              exponent or symbol held <lb/>forth by metrical language must in
                              different æras <lb/>of literature have excited very different
                              expecta-<lb/>tions : for example, in the age of Catullus Terence
                              <lb/>and Lucretia, and that of Statius or Claudian, <lb/>and in our
                              own country, in the age of Shakespeare <lb/>and Beaumont and Fletcher,
                              and that of Donne <lb/>and Cowley, or Dryden, or Pope. I will not
                              <lb/>take upon me to determine the exact import of <lb/>the promise
                              which by the act of writing in verse <lb/>an Author in the present day
                              makes to his Reader; <lb/>but I am certain it will appear to many
                              persons <lb/>that I have not fulfilled the terms of an
                              engage-<lb/>ment thus voluntarily contracted. I hope there- <pb n="x"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="x"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>fore the Reader
                              will not censure me, if I attempt <lb/>to state what I have proposed
                              to myself to perform, <lb/>and also, (as far as the limits of a
                              preface will <lb/>permit) to explain some of the chief reasons which
                              <lb/>have determined me in the choice of my purpose : <lb/>that at
                              least he may be spared any unpleasant <lb/>feeling of disappointment,
                              and that I myself may <lb/>be protected from the most dishonorable
                              accusa-<lb/>tion which can be brought against an Author, <lb/>namely,
                              that of an indolence which prevents him <lb/>from endeavouring to
                              ascertain what is his duty, <lb/>or, when his duty is ascertained
                              prevents him <lb/>from performing it.</p>
            <p>The principal object then which I proposed to <lb/>myself in these Poems
                              was to make the incidents <lb/>of common life interesting by tracing
                              in them, <lb/>truly though not ostentatiously, the primary laws
                              <lb/>of our nature : chiefly as far as regards the man-<lb/>ner in
                              which we associate ideas in a state of <pb n="xi"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="xi"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>excitement. Low and rustic
                              life was generally <lb/>chosen because in that situation the essential
                              <lb/>passions of the heart find a better soil in which <lb/>they can
                              attain their maturity, are less under <lb/>restraint, and speak a
                              plainer and more emphatic <lb/>language ; because in that situation
                              our elementary <lb/>feelings exist in a state of greater simplicity
                              and <lb/>consequently may be more accurately contempla-<lb/>ted and
                              more forcibly communicated ; because <lb/>the manners of rural life
                              germinate from those <lb/>elementary feelings; and from the necessary
                              <lb/>character of rural occupations are more easily <lb/>comprehended
                              ; and are more durable ; and lastly, <lb/>because in that situation
                              the passions of men are <lb/>incorporated with the beautiful and
                              permanent <lb/>forms of nature. The language too of these men <lb/>is
                              adopted (purified indeed from what appear to <lb/>be its real defects,
                              from all lasting and rational <lb/>causes of dislike or disgust)
                              because such men <lb/>hourly communicate with the best objects from
                                   <pb n="xii"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="xii"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>which the best part of language is originally <lb/>derived
                              ; and because, from their rank in society <lb/>and the sameness and
                              narrow circle of their inter-<lb/>course, being less under the action
                              of social vanity <lb/>they convey their feelings and notions in simple
                              <lb/>and unelaborated expressions. Accordingly such <lb/>a language
                              arising out of repeated experience and <lb/>regular feelings is a more
                              permanent and a far <lb/>more philosophical language than that which
                              is <lb/>frequently substituted for it by Poets, who think <lb/>that
                              they are conferring honour upon themselves <lb/>and their art in
                              proportion as they separate them-<lb/>selves from the sympathies of
                              men, and indulge <lb/>in arbitrary and capricious habits of expression
                              in <lb/>order to furnish food for fickle tastes and fickle
                              <lb/>appetites of their own creation.*<note place="foot" resp="auth">*
                                   It is worth while here to observe that the affecting parts
                                   <lb/>of Chaucer are almost always expressed in language pure
                                   <lb/>and universally intelligible even to this day.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="xiii"/>
            <milestone unit="page" n="xiii"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>I cannot be insensible of the present outcry <lb/>against the triviality
                              and meanness both of thought <lb/>and language, which some of my
                              contemporaries <lb/>have occasionally introduced into their metrical
                              <lb/>compositions; and I acknowledge that this defect <lb/>where it
                              exists, is more dishonorable to the Wri-<lb/>ter’s own character than
                              false refinement or arbi-<lb/>trary innovation, though I should
                              contend at the <lb/>same time that it is far less pernicious in the
                              sum <lb/>of its consequences. From such verses the Poems <lb/>in these
                              volumes will be found distinguished at <lb/>least by one mark of
                              difference, that each of them <lb/>has a worthy <emph>purpose</emph>.
                              Not that I mean to say, <lb/>that I always began to write with a
                              distinct pur-<lb/>pose formally conceived ; but I believe that my
                              <lb/>habits of meditation have so formed my feelings, <lb/>as that my
                              descriptions of such objects as strongly <lb/>excite those feelings,
                              will be found to carry along <lb/>with them a <emph>purpose</emph>. If
                              in this opinion I am <lb/>mistaken I can have little right to the name
                              of a<pb n="xiv"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="xiv"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>Poet.
                              For all good poetry is the spontaneous <lb/>overflow of powerful
                              feelings ; but though this be <lb/>true, Poems to which any value can
                              be attached, <lb/>were never produced on any variety of subjects
                              <lb/>but by a man who being possessed of more than <lb/>usual organic
                              sensibility had also thought long <lb/>and deeply. For our continued
                              influxes of feeling <lb/>are modified and directed by our thoughts,
                              which <lb/>are indeed the representatives of all our past
                              feel-<lb/>ings ; and as by contemplating the relation of <lb/>these
                              general representatives to each other, we <lb/>discover what is really
                              important to men, so by <lb/>the repetition and continuance of this
                              act feelings <lb/>connected with important subjects will be
                              nourish-<lb/>ed, till at length, if we be originally possessed of
                              <lb/>much organic sensibility, such habits of mind <lb/>will be
                              produced that by obeying blindly and me-<lb/>chanically the impulses
                              of those habits we shall <lb/>describe objects and utter sentiments of
                              such a <lb/>nature and in such connection with each other, <pb n="xv"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="xv"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>that the
                              understanding of the being to whom we <lb/>address ourselves, if he be
                              in a healthful state of <lb/>association, must necessarily be in some
                              degree <lb/>enlightened, his taste exalted, and his affections
                              <lb/>ameliorated.</p>
            <p>I have said that each of these poems has a <lb/>purpose. I have also
                              informed my Reader what <lb/>this purpose will be found principally to
                              be : <lb/>namely to illustrate the manner in which our <lb/>feelings
                              and ideas are associated in a state of <lb/>excitement. But speaking
                              in less general lan-<lb/>guage, it is to follow the fluxes and
                              refluxes of <lb/>the mind when agitated by the great and simple
                              <lb/>affections of our nature. This object I have endea-<lb/>voured in
                              these short essays to attain by various <lb/>means ; by tracing the
                              maternal passion through <lb/>many of its more subtle windings, as in
                              the poems <lb/>of the I<hi rend="small">diot</hi> B<hi rend="small">oy</hi> and the M<hi rend="small">ad</hi> M<hi rend="small">other </hi>; by <lb/>accompanying the last struggles of a human
                              being <pb n="xvi"/>
               <milestone unit="page" n="xvi"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>at
                              the approach of death, cleaving in solitude to <lb/>life and society,
                              as in the Poem of the F<hi rend="small">orsaken</hi>
               <lb/>I<hi rend="small">ndian </hi>; by shewing, as in the Stanzas entitled
                                   <lb/>W<hi rend="small">e are seven</hi>, the perplexity and
                              obscurity <lb/>which in childhood attend our notion of death, <lb/>or
                              rather our utter inability to admit that notion ; <lb/>or by
                              displaying the strength of fraternal, or to <lb/>speak more
                              philosophically, of moral attachment <lb/>when early associated with
                              the great and beauti-<lb/>ful objects of nature, as in T<hi rend="small">he</hi> B<hi rend="small">rothers </hi>; or, as
                              <lb/>in the Incident of S<hi rend="small">imon</hi> L<hi rend="small">ee</hi>, by placing my <lb/>Reader in the way of receiving from
                              ordinary <lb/>moral sensations another and more salutary
                              im-<lb/>pression than we are accustomed to receive from <lb/>them. It
                              has also been part of my general pur-<lb/>pose to attempt to sketch
                              characters under the <lb/>influence of less impassioned feelings, as
                              in the <lb/>O<hi rend="small">ld</hi> M<hi rend="small">an
                                   travelling</hi>, T<hi rend="small">he two</hi> T<hi rend="small">hieves</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>characters of which the elements are
                              simple, be-<lb/>longing rather to nature than to manners, such </p>
            <p>[<ref target="#xvii">skip</ref> misplaced cancel (replacement leaf, which is in the wrong place) and go to the real page xvii]</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="a3Cancel_xvii"/>
         <div xml:id="a3Cancel">
            <head>[Replacement for leaf <ref target="#a3orig">a3</ref>]<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>The First Volume of these Poems has already <lb/>been submitted to
                                   general perusal. It was <lb/>published, as an experiment which, I
                                   hoped, <lb/>might be of some use to ascertain, how far, <lb/>by
                                   fitting to metrical arrangement a selection <lb/>of the real
                                   language of men in a state of vivid <lb/>sensation, that sort of
                                   pleasure and that quantity <lb/>of pleasure may be imparted,
                                   which a Poet may <lb/>rationally endeavour to impart.</p>
            <p>I had formed no very inaccurate estimate of the <lb/>probable
                                   effect of those Poems : I flattered myself </p>
            <pb n="vi"/>
            <milestone n="vi." unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>that they who should be pleased with them would <lb/>read them with
                                   more than common pleasure : and <lb/>on the other hand I was well
                                   aware that by those <lb/>who should dislike them they would be
                                   read with <lb/>more than common dislike. The result has
                                   <lb/>differed from my expectation in this only, that I <lb/>have
                                   pleased a greater number, than I ventured <lb/>to hope I should
                                   please.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="a3Change">For the sake of variety and from a consciousness
                                   <lb/>of my own weakness I was induced to request <lb/>the
                                   assistance of a Friend, who furnished me <lb/>with the Poems of
                                   the A<hi rend="small caps">ncient</hi> M<hi>ariner</hi>, the
                                        <lb/>F<hi rend="small caps">oster</hi>-M<hi rend="small caps">other’s</hi> T<hi rend="small caps">ale</hi>, the N<hi rend="small caps">ightingale</hi>, the
                                        <lb/>D<hi rend="small caps">ungeon</hi>, and the Poem
                                   entitled L<hi rend="small caps">ove</hi>. I <lb/>should not,
                                   however, have requested this <lb/>assistance, had I not believed
                                   that the poems <lb/>of my Friend would in a great measure
                                   <lb/>have the same tendency as my own, and that,</p>
            <p>[End of
                              replacement leaf; the Preface continues <ref target="#endOrig">here</ref>]</p>
         </div>
         <pb xml:id="xvii"/>
         <milestone n="xvii" unit="page"/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <div>
            <p>as exist now and will probably always exist, and <lb/>which from
                                   their constitution may be distinctly <lb/>and profitably
                                   contemplated. I will not abuse <lb/>the indulgence of my Reader
                                   by dwelling longer <lb/>upon this subject ; but it is proper that
                                   I should <lb/>mention one other circumstance which
                                   distin-<lb/>guishes these Poems from the popular Poetry of
                                   <lb/>the day; it is this, that the feeling therein
                                   deve-<lb/>loped gives importance to the action and situation
                                   <lb/>and not the action and situation to the feeling. <lb/>My
                                   meaning will be rendered perfectly intelligible <lb/>by referring
                                   my Reader to the Poems entitled P<hi rend="small">oor</hi>
               <lb/>S<hi rend="small">usan</hi> and the C<hi rend="small">hildless</hi> F<hi rend="small">ather</hi>,
                                   particularly <lb/>to the last Stanza of the latter Poem. </p>
            <p>I will not suffer a sense of false modesty to prevent <lb/>me from
                                   asserting, that I point my Reader’s atten-<lb/>tion to this mark
                                   of distinction far less for the <lb/>sake of these particular
                                   Poems than from the <lb/>general importance of the subject. The
                                   subject <pb n="xviii"/>
               <milestone n="xviii" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>is indeed important! For the human mind is
                                   <lb/>capable of excitement without the application of <lb/>gross
                                   and violent stimulants ; and he must have <lb/>a very faint
                                   perception of its beauty and dignity <lb/>who does not know this,
                                   and who does not fur-<lb/>ther know that one being is elevated
                                   above <lb/>another in proportion as he possesses this
                                   capa-<lb/>bility. It has therefore appeared to me that to
                                   <lb/>endeavour to produce or enlarge this capability is <lb/>one
                                   of the best services in which, at any period, <lb/>a Writer can
                                   be engaged ; but this service, excel-<lb/>lent at all times, is
                                   especially so at the present day. <lb/>For a multitude of causes
                                   unknown to former <lb/>times are now acting with a combined force
                                   to <lb/>blunt the discriminating powers of the mind, and
                                   <lb/>unfitting it for all voluntary exertion to reduce it <lb/>to
                                   a state of almost savage torpor. The most <lb/>effective of these
                                   causes are the great national <lb/>events which are daily taking
                                   place, and the en-<lb/>creasing accumulation of men in cities,
                                   where the<pb n="xix"/>
               <milestone n="xix" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>uniformity of their occupations produces a craving
                                   <lb/>for extraordinary incident which the rapid
                                   com-<lb/>munication of intelligence hourly gratifies. To
                                   <lb/>this tendency of life and manners the literature <lb/>and
                                   theatrical exhibitions of the country have <lb/>conformed
                                   themselves. The invaluable works of <lb/>our elder writers, I had
                                   almost said the works of <lb/>Shakespear and Milton, are driven
                                   into neglect <lb/>by frantic novels, sickly and stupid German
                                   Tra-<lb/>gedies, and deluges of idle and extravagant stories
                                   <lb/>in verse.—When I think upon this degrading <lb/>thirst after
                                   outrageous stimulation I am almost <lb/>ashamed to have spoken of
                                   the feeble effort with <lb/>which I have endeavoured to
                                   counteract it; and <lb/>reflecting upon the magnitude of the
                                   general <lb/>evil, I should be oppressed with no dishonorable
                                   <lb/>melancholy, had I not a deep impression of certain
                                   <lb/>inherent and indestructible qualities of the human
                                   <lb/>mind, and likewise of certain powers in the great <lb/>and
                                   permanent objects that act upon it which are <pb n="xx"/>
               <milestone n="xx" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>equally inherent
                                   and indestructible; and did I <lb/>not further add to this
                                   impression a belief that the <lb/>time is approaching when the
                                   evil will be syste-<lb/>matically opposed by men of greater
                                   powers and <lb/>with far more distinguished success.</p>
            <p>Having dwelt thus long on the subjects and aim <lb/>of these Poems,
                                   I shall request the Reader’s per-<lb/>mission to apprize him of a
                                   few circum<orig rend="long s">s</orig>tances <lb/>relating to
                                   their <emph>style</emph>, in order, among other rea-<lb/>sons,
                                   that I may not be censured for not having <lb/>performed what I
                                   never attempted. Except in a <lb/>very few instances the Reader
                                   will find no personi-<lb/>fications of abstract ideas in these
                                   volumes, not <lb/>that I mean to censure such personifications :
                                   <lb/>they may be well fitted for certain sorts of
                                   com-<lb/>position, but in these Poems I propose to myself <lb/>to
                                   imitate, and, as far as is possible, to adopt the <lb/>very
                                   language of men, and I do not find that <lb/>such
                                   personifications make any regular or natural <pb n="xxi"/>
               <milestone n="xxi" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>part of that
                                   language. I wish to keep my Reader <lb/>in the company of flesh
                                   and blood, persuaded that <lb/>by so doing I shall interest him.
                                   Not but that I <lb/>believe that others who pursue a different
                                   track <lb/>may interest him likewise : I do not interfere
                                   <lb/>with their claim, I only wish to prefer a different
                                   <lb/>claim of my own. There will also be found in <lb/>these
                                   volumes little of what is usually called <lb/>poetic diction ; I
                                   have taken as much pains to <lb/>avoid it as others ordinarily
                                   take to produce it; <lb/>this I have done for the reason already
                                   alleged, <lb/>to bring my language near to the language of men,
                                   <lb/>and further, because the pleasure which I have <lb/>proposed
                                   to myself to impart is of a kind very <lb/>different from that
                                   which is supposed by many <lb/>persons to be the proper object of
                                   poetry. I do <lb/>not know how without being culpably particular
                                   <lb/>I can give my Reader a more exact notion of the <lb/>style
                                   in which I wished these poems to be writ-<lb/>ten than by
                                   informing him that I have at all times<pb n="xxii"/>
               <milestone n="xxii" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>endeavoured to look steadily
                                   at my subject, con-<lb/>sequently I hope it will be found that
                                   there is in <lb/>these Poems little falsehood of description, and
                                   that <lb/>my ideas are expressed in language fitted to their
                                   <lb/>respective importance. Something I must have <lb/>gained by
                                   this practice, as it is friendly to one <lb/>property of all good
                                   poetry, namely good sense; <lb/>but it has necessarily cut me off
                                   from a large por-<lb/>tion of phrases and figures of speech which
                                   from <lb/>father to son have long been regarded as the
                                   <lb/>common inheritance of Poets. I have also thought <lb/>it
                                   expedient to restrict myself still further, having <lb/>abstained
                                   from the use of many expressions, in <lb/>themselves proper and
                                   beautiful, but which have <lb/>been foolishly repeated by bad
                                   Poets till such <lb/>feelings of disgust are connected with them
                                   as it <lb/>is scarcely possible by any art of association to
                                   <lb/>overpower.</p>
            <p>If in a Poem there should be found a series of lines, <pb n="xxiii"/>
               <milestone n="xxiii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>or even a
                                   single line, in which the language, <lb/>though naturally
                                   arranged and according to the <lb/>strict laws of metre, does not
                                   differ from that of <lb/>prose, there is a numerous class of
                                   critics who, <lb/>when they stumble upon these prosaisms as they
                                   <lb/>call them, imagine that they have made a notable
                                   <lb/>discovery, and exult over the Poet as over a man
                                   <lb/>ignorant of his own profession. Now these men <lb/>would
                                   establish a canon of criticism which the <lb/>Reader will
                                   conclude he must utterly reject if he <lb/>wishes to be pleased
                                   with these volumes. And it <lb/>would be a most easy task to
                                   prove to him that <lb/>not only the language of a large portion
                                   of every <lb/>good poem, even of the most elevated character,
                                   <lb/>must necessarily, except with reference to the <lb/>metre,
                                   in no respect differ from that of good prose, <lb/>but likewise
                                   that some of the most interesting <lb/>parts of the best poems
                                   will be found to be <lb/>strictly the language of prose when
                                   prose is well <lb/>written. The truth of this assertion might
                                        be<pb n="xxiv"/>
               <milestone n="xxiv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>demonstrated by innumerable passages from almost
                                   <lb/>all the poetical writings, even of Milton himself. <lb/>I
                                   have not space for much quotation ; but, to <lb/>illustrate the
                                   subject in a general manner, I will <lb/>here adduce a short
                                   composition of Gray, who <lb/>was at the head of those who by
                                   their reasonings <lb/>have attempted to widen the space of
                                   separation <lb/>betwixt Prose and Metrical composition, and was
                                   <lb/>more than any other man curiously elaborate in <lb/>the
                                   structure of his own poetic diction.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <l>In vain to me the
                                             smiling mornings shine,</l>
                  <l>And reddening Phœbus
                                             lifts his golden fire :</l>
                  <l>The birds in vain their
                                             amorous descant join,</l>
                  <l>Or chearful fields resume
                                             their green attire :</l>
                  <l>These ears alas! for other
                                             notes repine ;</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>A different object do these
                                                  eyes require </emph>;</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>My lonely
                                                  anguish melts no heart but mine
                                                  </emph>;</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>And in my breast the
                                                  imperfect joys expire</emph>;</l>
                  <l>Yet Morning
                                             smiles the busy race to cheer,</l>
                  <l>And new-born
                                             pleasure brings to happier men;</l>
                  <l>The fields to all
                                             their wonted tribute bear ;</l>
                  <l>To warm their little
                                             loves the birds complain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>I fruitless mourn
                                                  to him that cannot hear</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>And
                                                  weep the more because I weep in
                                        vain.</emph>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="xxv"/>
               <milestone n="xxv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>It will easily by perceived that the
                                   only part of <lb/>this Sonnet which is of any value is the lines
                                   <lb/>printed in Italics : it is equally obvious that except
                                   <lb/>in the rhyme, and in the use of the single word
                                   <lb/>“fruitless” for fruitlessly, which is so far a defect,
                                   <lb/>the language of these lines does in no respect <lb/>differ
                                   from that of prose.</p>
            <p>Is there then, it will be asked, no essential dif-<lb/>ference
                                   between the language of prose and met--<lb/>rical composition ? I
                                   answer that there neither is <lb/>nor can be any essential
                                   difference. We are <lb/>fond of tracing the resemblance between
                                   Poetry <lb/>and Painting, and, accordingly, we call them
                                   <lb/>Sisters : but where shall we find bonds of con-<lb/>nection
                                   sufficiently strict to typify the affinity <lb/>betwixt metrical
                                   and prose composition ? They <lb/>both speak by and to the same
                                   organs ; the bodies <lb/>in which both of them are clothed may be
                                   said to <lb/>be of the same substance, their affections are<pb n="xxvi"/>
               <milestone n="xxvi." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>kindred and almost identical, not necessarily
                                   <lb/>differing even in degree; *Poetry sheds no tears <lb/>“such
                                   as Angels weep,” but natural and human <lb/>tears; she can boast
                                   of no celestial Ichor that <lb/>distinguishes her vital juices
                                   from those of prose; <lb/>the same human blood circulates through
                                   the <lb/>veins of them both.</p>
            <p>If it be affirmed that rhyme and metrical arrange-<lb/>ment of
                                   themselves constitute a distinction which <lb/>overturns what I
                                   have been saying on the strict <lb/>affinity of metrical language
                                   with that of prose, <lb/>and paves the way for other distinctions
                                   which <note place="foot" resp="auth">* I here use the word
                                        “Poetry” (though against my own <lb/>judgment) as opposed to
                                        the word Prose, and synonomous <lb/>with metrical
                                        composition. But much confusion has been <lb/>introduced
                                        into criticism by this contradistinction of Poetry <lb/>and
                                        Prose, instead of the more philosophical one of Poetry
                                        <lb/>and Science. The only strict antithesis to Prose is
                                        Metre.</note>
               <pb n="xxvii"/>
               <milestone n="xxvii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>the mind voluntarily admits, I answer
                                   that the <lb/>distinction of rhyme and metre is regular and
                                   uni-<lb/>form, and not, like that which is produced by <lb/>what
                                   is usually called poetic diction, arbitrary and <lb/>subject to
                                   infinite caprices upon which no calcula-<lb/>tion whatever can be
                                   made. In the one case the <lb/>Reader is utterly at the mercy of
                                   the Poet re-<lb/>specting what imagery or diction he may choose
                                   <lb/>to connect with the passion, whereas in the other <lb/>the
                                   metre obeys certain laws, to which the Poet <lb/>and Reader both
                                   willingly submit because they <lb/>are certain, and because no
                                   interference is made <lb/>by them with the passion but such as
                                   the con-<lb/>curring testimony of ages has shewn to heighten
                                   <lb/>and improve the pleasure which co-exists with it.</p>
            <p>It will now be proper to answer an obvious ques-<lb/>tion, namely,
                                   why, professing these opinions have <lb/>I written in verse? To
                                   this in the first place I <lb/>reply, because, however I may have
                                   restricted <pb n="xxviii"/>
               <milestone n="xxviii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>myself, there is still left open to me what
                                   con-<lb/>fessedly constitutes the most valuable object of
                                   <lb/>all writing whether in prose or verse, the great <lb/>and
                                   universal passions of men, the most general <lb/>and interesting
                                   of their occupations, and the entire <lb/>world of nature, from
                                   which I am at liberty to <lb/>supply myself with endless
                                   combinations of forms <lb/>and imagery. Now, granting for a
                                   moment that <lb/>whatever is interesting in these objects may be
                                   as <lb/>vividly described in prose, why am I to be
                                   con-<lb/>demned if to such description I have endeavoured <lb/>to
                                   superadd the charm which by the consent of <lb/>all nations is
                                   acknowledged to exist in metrical <lb/>language? To this it will
                                   be answered, that a <lb/>very small part of the pleasure given by
                                   Poetry <lb/>depends upon the metre, and that it is injudicious
                                   <lb/>to write in metre unless it be accompanied with <lb/>the
                                   other artificial distinctions of style with which <lb/>metre is
                                   usually accompanied, and that by such <lb/>deviation more will be
                                   lost from the shock which <pb n="xxix"/>
               <milestone n="xxix." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>will be thereby given to the Reader’s
                                   associations <lb/>than will be counterbalanced by any pleasure
                                   <lb/>which he can derive from the general power of <lb/>numbers.
                                   In answer to those who thus contend <lb/>for the necessity of
                                   accompanying metre with <lb/>certain appropriate colours of style
                                   in order to the <lb/>accomplishment of its appropriate end, and
                                   who <lb/>also, in my opinion, greatly under-rate the power
                                   <lb/>of metre in itself, it might perhaps be almost
                                   <lb/>sufficient to observe that poems are extant, writ-<lb/>ten
                                   upon more humble subjects, and in a more <lb/>naked and simple
                                   style than what I have aimed at, <lb/>which poems have continued
                                   to give pleasure <lb/>from generation to generation. Now, if
                                   naked-<lb/>ness and simplicity be a defect, the fact here
                                   men-<lb/>tioned affords a strong presumption that poems
                                   <lb/>somewhat less naked and simple are capable of <lb/>affording
                                   pleasure at the present day ; and all <lb/>that I am now
                                   attempting is to justify myself for <lb/>having written under the
                                   impression of this <lb/>belief.</p>
            <pb n="xxx"/>
            <milestone n="xxx." unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>But I might point out various causes why, when <lb/>the style is
                                   manly, and the subject of some im-<lb/>portance, words metrically
                                   arranged will long con-<lb/>tinue to impart such a pleasure to
                                   mankind as he <lb/>who is sensible of the extent of that pleasure
                                   will <lb/>be desirous to impart. The end of Poetry is to
                                   <lb/>produce excitement in coexistence with an over-<lb/>balance
                                   of pleasure. Now, by the supposition, <lb/>excitement is an
                                   unusual and irregular state of <lb/>the mind; ideas and feelings
                                   do not in that state <lb/>succeed each other in accustomed order.
                                   But if <lb/>the words by which this excitement is produced
                                   <lb/>are in themselves powerful, or the images and <lb/>feelings
                                   have an undue proportion of pain con-<lb/>nected with them, there
                                   is some danger that the <lb/>excitement may be carried beyond its
                                   proper <lb/>bounds. Now the co-presence of something
                                   <lb/>regular, something to which the mind has been
                                   <lb/>accustomed when in an unexcited or a less excited
                                   <lb/>state, cannot but have great efficacy in tempering<pb n="xxxi"/>
               <milestone n="xxxi." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>and
                                   restraining the passion by an intertexture of <lb/>ordinary
                                   feeling. This may be illustrated by appeal-<lb/>ing to the
                                   Reader’s own experience of the reluctance <lb/>with which he
                                   comes to the re-perusal of the dis-<lb/>tressful parts of
                                   Clarissa Harlowe, or the Gamester. <lb/>While Shakespeare’s
                                   writings, in the most pathetic <lb/>scenes, never act upon us as
                                   pathetic beyond the <lb/>bounds of pleasure—an effect which is in
                                   a great de-<lb/>gree to be ascribed to small, but continual and
                                   regu-<lb/>lar impulses of pleasurable surprise from the metrical
                                   <lb/>arrangement.—On the other hand (what it must <lb/>be allowed
                                   will much more frequently happen) <lb/>if the Poet’s words should
                                   be incommensurate <lb/>with the passion, and inadequate to raise
                                   the <lb/>Reader to a height of desirable excitement, then,
                                   <lb/>(unless the Poet’s choice of his metre has been <lb/>grossly
                                   injudicious) in the feelings of pleasure <lb/>which the Reader
                                   has been accustomed to con-<lb/>nect with metre in general, and
                                   in the feeling, <lb/>whether chearful or melancholy, which he has
                                        <pb n="xxxii"/>
               <milestone n="xxxii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>been accustomed to connect with that particular
                                   <lb/>movement of metre, there will be found some-<lb/>thing which
                                   will greatly contribute to impart <lb/>passion to the words, and
                                   to effect the complex <lb/>end which the Poet proposes to
                                   himself.</p>
            <p>If I had undertaken a systematic defence of the <lb/>theory upon
                                   which these poems are written, it <lb/>would have been my duty to
                                   develope the various <lb/>causes upon which the pleasure received
                                   from <lb/>metrical language depends. Among the chief of
                                   <lb/>these causes is to be reckoned a principle which <lb/>must
                                   be well known to those who have made any <lb/>of the Arts the
                                   object of accurate reflection ; I <lb/>mean the pleasure which
                                   the mind derives from <lb/>the perception of similitude in
                                   dissimilitude. This <lb/>principle is the great spring of the
                                   activity of our <lb/>minds and their chief feeder. From this
                                   princi-<lb/>ple the direction of the sexual appetite, and all
                                   <lb/>the passions connected with it take their origin :<pb n="xxxiii"/>
               <milestone n="xxxiii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>It
                                   is the life of our ordinary conversation ; and <lb/>upon the
                                   accuracy with which similitude in <lb/>dissimilitude, and
                                   dissimilitude in similitude are <lb/>perceived, depend our taste
                                   and our moral feel-<lb/>ings. It would not have been a useless
                                   employ-<lb/>ment to have applied this principle to the
                                   con-<lb/>sideration of metre, and to have shewn that metre
                                   <lb/>is hence enabled to afford much pleasure, and <lb/>to have
                                   pointed out in what manner that pleasure <lb/>is produced. But my
                                   limits will not permit me to <lb/>enter upon this subject, and I
                                   must content my-<lb/>self with a general summary.</p>
            <p>I have said that Poetry is the spontaneous overflow <lb/>of
                                   powerful feelings : it takes its origin from emo-<lb/>tion
                                   recollected in tranquillity : the emotion is <lb/>contemplated
                                   till by a species of reaction the <lb/>tranquillity gradually
                                   disappears, and an emotion, <lb/>similar to that which was before
                                   the subject of <lb/>contemplation, is gradually produced, and
                                   does <pb n="xxxiv"/>
               <milestone n="xxxiv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>itself actually exist in the mind. In this mood
                                   <lb/>successful composition generally begins, and in a <lb/>mood
                                   similar to this it is carried on ; but the <lb/>emotion, of
                                   whatever kind and in whatever de-<lb/>gree, from various causes
                                   is qualified by various <lb/>pleasures, so that in describing any
                                   passions what-<lb/>soever, which are voluntarily described, the
                                   mind <lb/>will upon the whole be in a state of enjoyment.
                                   <lb/>Now if Nature be thus cautious in preserving in <lb/>a state
                                   of enjoyment a being thus employed, <lb/>the Poet ought to profit
                                   by the lesson thus held <lb/>forth to him, and ought especially
                                   to take care, <lb/>that whatever passions he communicates to his
                                   <lb/>Reader, those passions, if his Reader’s mind be <lb/>sound
                                   and vigorous, should always be accompa-<lb/>nied with an
                                   overbalance of pleasure. Now the <lb/>music of harmonious
                                   metrical language, the sense <lb/>of difficulty overcome, and the
                                   blind association of <lb/>pleasure which has been previously
                                   received from <lb/>works of rhyme or metre of the same or similar
                                        <pb n="xxxv"/>
               <milestone n="xxxv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>construction, all these imperceptibly make up a
                                   <lb/>complex feeling of delight, which is of the most
                                   <lb/>important use in tempering the painful feeling <lb/>which
                                   will always be found intermingled with <lb/>powerful descriptions
                                   of the deeper passions. <lb/>This effect is always produced in
                                   pathetic and <lb/>impassioned poetry ; while in lighter
                                   composi-<lb/>tions the ease and gracefulness with which the
                                   <lb/>Poet manages his numbers are themselves con-<lb/>fessedly a
                                   principal source of the gratification of <lb/>the Reader. I might
                                   perhaps include all which <lb/>it is <emph>necessary</emph> to
                                   say upon this subject by affirming <lb/>what few persons will
                                   deny, that of two descrip-<lb/>tions either of passions, manners,
                                   or characters, <lb/>each of them equally well executed, the one
                                   in <lb/>prose and the other in verse, the verse will be <lb/>read
                                   a hundred times where the prose is read <lb/>once. We see that
                                   Pope by the power of verse <lb/>alone, has contrived to render
                                   the plainest com-<lb/>mon sense interesting, and even frequently
                                   to <pb n="xxxvi"/>
               <milestone n="xxxvi." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>invest it with the appearance of passion. In
                                   con-<lb/>sequence of these convictions I related in metre
                                   <lb/>the Tale of G<hi rend="small">oody</hi> B<hi rend="small">lake</hi> and H<hi rend="small">arry</hi> G<hi rend="small">ill</hi>, <lb/>which is one of the rudest of this
                                   collection. I <lb/>wished to draw attention to the truth that the
                                   <lb/>power of the human imagination is sufficient to <lb/>produce
                                   such changes even in our physical nature <lb/>as might almost
                                   appear miraculous. The truth is <lb/>an important one; the fact
                                   (for it is a <emph>fact</emph>) is a <lb/>valuable illustration
                                   of it. And I have the satis-<lb/>faction of knowing that it has
                                   been communicated <lb/>to many hundreds of people who would never
                                   <lb/>have heard of it, had it not been narrated as a <lb/>Ballad,
                                   and in a more impressive metre than is <lb/>usual in Ballads.</p>
            <p>Having thus adverted to a few of the reasons why <lb/>I have
                                   written in verse, and why I have chosen <lb/>subjects from common
                                   life, and endeavoured to <lb/>bring my language near to the real
                                   language of <pb n="xxxvii"/>
               <milestone n="xxxvii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>men, if I have been too minute in pleading my
                                   <lb/>own cause, I have at the same time been treat-<lb/>ing a
                                   subject of general interest; and it is for this <lb/>reason that
                                   I request the Reader’s permission to <lb/>add a few words with
                                   reference solely to these <lb/>particular poems, and to some
                                   defects which will <lb/>probably be found in them. I am sensible
                                   that <lb/>my associations must have sometimes been
                                   par-<lb/>ticular instead of general, and that, consequently,
                                   <lb/>giving to things a false importance, sometimes <lb/>from
                                   diseased impulses I may have written upon <lb/>unworthy subjects;
                                   but I am less apprehensive <lb/>on this account, than that my
                                   language may fre-<lb/>quently have suffered from those arbitrary
                                   con-<lb/>nections of feelings and ideas with particular
                                   <lb/>words, from which no man can altogether protect
                                   <lb/>himself. Hence I have no doubt that in some <lb/>instances
                                   feelings even of the ludicrous may be <lb/>given to my Readers by
                                   expressions which ap-<lb/>peared to me tender and pathetic. Such
                                   faulty <pb n="xxxviii"/>
               <milestone n="xxxviii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>expressions, were I convinced they were faulty
                                   <lb/>at present, and that they must necessarily con-<lb/>tinue to
                                   be so, I would willingly take all rea-<lb/>sonable pains to
                                   correct. But it is dangerous to <lb/>make these alterations on
                                   the simple authority of <lb/>a few individuals, or even of
                                   certain classes of <lb/>men; for where the understanding of an
                                   Author <lb/>is not convinced, or his feelings altered, this
                                   <lb/>cannot be done without great injury to himself : <lb/>for
                                   his own feelings are his stay and support, and <lb/>if he sets
                                   them aside in one instance, he may be <lb/>induced to repeat this
                                   act till his mind loses all <lb/>confidence in itself and becomes
                                   utterly debilitated. <lb/>To this it may be added, that the
                                   Reader ought <lb/>never to forget that he is himself exposed to
                                   the <lb/>same errors as the Poet, and perhaps in a much
                                   <lb/>greater degree : for there can be no presumption <lb/>in
                                   saying that it is not probable he will be so well <lb/>acquainted
                                   with the various stages of meaning <lb/>through which words have
                                   passed, or with the <pb n="xxxix"/>
               <milestone n="xxxix." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>fickleness or stability of the
                                   relations of particular <lb/>ideas to each other ; and above all,
                                   since he is <lb/>so much less interested in the subject, he may
                                   <lb/>decide lightly and carelessly.</p>
            <p>Long as I have detained my Reader, I hope he <lb/>will permit me to
                                   caution him against a mode of <lb/>false criticism which has been
                                   applied to Poetry <lb/>in which the language closely resembles
                                   that of <lb/>life and nature. Such verses have been triumphed
                                   <lb/>over in parodies of which Dr. Johnson’s Stanza is <lb/>a
                                   fair specimen.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>“ I put my hat upon my head,</l>
                     <l>And walk’d into the Strand,</l>
                     <l>And there I met another man</l>
                     <l>Whose hat was in his hand.”</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lb/>
                              Immediately under these lines I will place one <lb/>of the most
                                   justly admired stanzas of the “<emph>Babes</emph>
               <lb/>in the
                                        Wood.”<lb/>
               <pb n="xl"/>
               <milestone n="xl." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <q>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>“ These pretty Babes with hand in hand</l>
                     <l>Went wandering up and down;</l>
                     <l>But never more they saw the Man</l>
                     <l>Approaching from the Town.”</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lb/>In both of these stanzas the words, and the
                                   order <lb/>of the words, in no respect differ from the most
                                   <lb/>unimpassioned conversation. There are words in <lb/>both,
                                   for example, “the Strand,” and “the Town,” <lb/>connected with
                                   none but the most familiar ideas; <lb/>yet the one stanza we
                                   admit as admirable, and <lb/>the other as a fair example of the
                                   superlatively <lb/>contemptible. Whence arises this difference?
                                   <lb/>Not from the metre, not from the language, not <lb/>from the
                                   order of the words; but the <emph>matter</emph>
               <lb/>expressed in
                                   Dr. Johnson’s stanza is contemptible. <lb/>The proper method of
                                   treating trivial and simple <lb/>verses to which Dr. Johnson’s
                                   stanza would be a <lb/>fair parallelism is not to say this is a
                                   bad kind of <lb/>poetry, or this is not poetry, but this wants
                                   sense ; <lb/>it is neither interesting in itself, nor can
                                        <emph>lead</emph> to <pb n="xli"/>
               <milestone n="xli." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>any thing interesting; the images
                                   neither origi-<lb/>nate in that sane state of feeling which
                                   arises out <lb/>of thought, nor can excite thought or feeling in
                                   <lb/>the Reader. This is the only sensible manner of <lb/>dealing
                                   with such verses : Why trouble yourself <lb/>about the species
                                   till you have previously decided <lb/>upon the genus? Why take
                                   pains to prove that <lb/>an Ape is not a Newton when it is
                                   self-evident <lb/>that he is not a man.</p>
            <p>I have one request to make of my Reader, which <lb/>is, that in
                                   judging these Poems he would decide <lb/>by his own feelings
                                   genuinely, and not by reflec-<lb/>tion upon what will probably be
                                   the judgment of <lb/>others. How common is it to hear a person
                                   say, <lb/>“I myself do not object to this style of
                                   composi-<lb/>tion or this or that expression, but to such and
                                   <lb/>such classes of people it will appear mean or
                                   <lb/>ludicrous.” This mode of criticism so destructive <lb/>of
                                   all sound unadulterated judgment is almost <pb n="xlii"/>
               <milestone n="xlii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>universal: I
                                   have therefore to request that the <lb/>Reader would abide
                                   independently by his own <lb/>feelings, and that if he finds
                                   himself affected he <lb/>would not suffer such conjectures to
                                   interfere <lb/>with his pleasure.</p>
            <p>If an Author by any single composition has im-<lb/>pressed us with
                                   respect for his talents, it is useful <lb/>to consider this as
                                   affording a presumption, that, <lb/>on other occasions where we
                                   have been displeased, <lb/>he nevertheless may not have written
                                   ill or ab-<lb/>surdly ; and, further, to give him so much credit
                                   <lb/>for this one composition as may induce us to <lb/>review
                                   what has displeased us with more care <lb/>than we should
                                   otherwise have bestowed upon it. <lb/>This is not only an act of
                                   justice, but in our deci-<lb/>sions upon poetry especially, may
                                   conduce in a <lb/>high degree to the improvement of our own
                                   taste: <lb/>for an <emph>accurate</emph> taste in Poetry and in
                                   all the other <lb/>arts, as Sir Joshua Reynolds has observed, is
                                   an <pb n="xliii"/>
               <milestone n="xliii." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <emph>acquired</emph> talent, which can only be
                                   produced by <lb/>thought and a long continued intercourse with
                                   <lb/>the best models of composition. This is men-<lb/>tioned not
                                   with so ridiculous a purpose as to pre-<lb/>vent the most
                                   inexperienced Reader from judging <lb/>for himself, (I have
                                   already said that I wish him <lb/>to judge for himself ;) but
                                   merely to temper the <lb/>rashness of decision, and to suggest
                                   that if <lb/>Poetry be a subject on which much time has <lb/>not
                                   been bestowed, the judgment may be <lb/>erroneous, and that in
                                   many cases it necessarily <lb/>will be so.</p>
            <p>I know that nothing would have so effectually <lb/>contributed to
                                   further the end which I have in <lb/>view as to have shewn of
                                   what kind the pleasure <lb/>is, and how the pleasure is produced
                                   which is <lb/>confessedly produced by metrical composition
                                   <lb/>essentially different from what I have here
                                   en-<lb/>deavoured to recommend; for the Reader will <pb n="xliv"/>
               <milestone n="xliv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>say that he
                                   has been pleased by such composition <lb/>and what can I do more
                                   for him? The power of <lb/>any art is limited and he will suspect
                                   that if I pro-<lb/>pose to furnish him with new friends it is
                                   only <lb/>upon condition of his abandoning his old friends.
                                   <lb/>Besides, as I have said, the Reader is himself
                                   <lb/>conscious of the pleasure which he has received <lb/>from
                                   such composition, composition to which he <lb/>has peculiarly
                                   attached the endearing name of <lb/>Poetry ; and all men feel an
                                   habitual gratitude, <lb/>and something of an honorable bigotry
                                   for the <lb/>objects which have long continued to please them:
                                   <lb/>we not only wish to be pleased, but to be pleased <lb/>in
                                   that particular way in which we have been <lb/>accustomed to be
                                   pleased. There is a host of <lb/>arguments in these feelings ;
                                   and I should be the <lb/>less able to combat them successfully,
                                   as I am <lb/>willing to allow, that, in order entirely to enjoy
                                   <lb/>the Poetry which I am recommending, it would <lb/>be
                                   necessary to give up much of what is ordinarily<pb n="xlv"/>
               <milestone n="xlv." unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>enjoyed. But
                                   would my limits have permitted <lb/>me to point out how this
                                   pleasure is produced, I <lb/>might have removed many obstacles,
                                   and assisted <lb/>my Reader in perceiving that the powers of
                                   lan-<lb/>guage are not so limited as he may suppose ; and
                                   <lb/>that it is possible that poetry may give other
                                   <lb/>enjoyments, of a purer, more lasting, and more
                                   <lb/>exquisite nature. But this part of my subject I <lb/>have
                                   been obliged altogether to omit : as it has <lb/>been less my
                                   present aim to prove that the interest <lb/>excited by some other
                                   kinds of poetry is less <lb/>vivid, and less worthy of the nobler
                                   powers of the <lb/>mind, than to offer reasons for presuming,
                                   that, <lb/>if the object which I have proposed to myself
                                   <lb/>were adequately attained, a species of poetry <lb/>would be
                                   produced, which is genuine poetry ; <lb/>in its nature well
                                   adapted to interest man-<lb/>kind permanently, and likewise
                                   important in <lb/>the multiplicity and quality of its moral
                                   rela-<lb/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="xlvi"/>
            <milestone n="xlvi." unit="page"/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>From what has been said, and from a perusal of <lb/>the Poems, the
                                   Reader will be able clearly to <lb/>perceive the object which I
                                   have proposed to <lb/>myself : he will determine how far I have
                                   attained <lb/>this object; and, what is a much more important
                                   <lb/>question, whether it be worth attaining; and <lb/>upon the
                                   decision of these two questions will rest <lb/>my claim to the
                                   approbation of the public.</p>
            <pb/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
