<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyrical Ballads, 1802: [Endnotes on The Thorn, Tintern Abbey, and the Ancient Mariner (varies)]</title>
            <author>
               <name>William Wordsworth</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="BG">Bruce Graver</name>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <name xml:id="RT">Ronald Tetreault</name>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor; Producer</resp>
               <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
            <idno type="local">lbphil-2_NOTES</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic xml:id="NOTES">
                  <title>[Endnotes on The Thorn, Tintern Abbey, and the Ancient Mariner (varies)]</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">William Wordsworth</persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr xml:id="lbphil-2">
                  <ptr target="../XML/lbphil-2.xml"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>T. N. Longman and O. Rees</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <date>1802</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">172 to 172</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="pages">4</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20250731" who="#LM">
               Splurged out main xml into separate xml files for poems and paratexts.
            </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <head>
            <emph>NOTES</emph>.</head>
         <div xml:id="noteThorn">
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="small caps">ote</hi> to the T<hi rend="small caps">horn</hi>
               </hi>, V.I.p. 95.—This Poem
                                   ought to have <lb/>been preceded by an introductory Poem, which I
                                   have been pre-<lb/>vented from writing by never having felt
                                   myself in a mood <lb/>when it was probable that I should write it
                                   well.—The character <lb/>which I have here introduced
                                   speaking is sufficiently common. <lb/>The Reader will perhaps
                                   have a general notion of it, if he has <lb/>ever known a man, a
                                   Captain of a small trading vessel for ex-<lb/>ample, who being
                                   past the middle age of life, had retired upon <lb/>an annuity, or
                                   small independent income, to some village or <lb/>country town of
                                   which he was not a native, or in which he had <lb/>not been
                                   accustomed to live. Such men having little to do become
                                   <lb/>credulous and talkative from indolence ; and from the same
                                   <lb/>cause, and other pre-disposing causes by which it is
                                   probable <lb/>that such men may have been affected, they are
                                   prone to super-<lb/>stition. On which account it appeared to me
                                   proper to select a <lb/>character like this, to exhibit some of
                                   the general laws by which <lb/>superstition acts upon the mind.
                                   Superstitious men are almost <lb/>always men of slow faculties
                                   and deep feelings, their minds are <lb/>not loose but adhesive ;
                                   they have a reasonable share of imagi-<lb/>nation, by which word
                                   I mean the faculty which produces im-<lb/>pressive effects out of
                                   simple elements ; but they are utterly <lb/>destitute of fancy,
                                   the power by which pleasure and surprise <lb/>are excited by
                                   sudden varieties of situation, and by accumulated
                                   <lb/>imagery.</p>
            <p>It was my wish in this Poem to shew the manner in which
                                   <lb/>such men cleave to the same ideas ; and to follow the turns
                                   of <lb/>passion, always different, yet not palpably different, by
                                   which <lb/>their conversation is swayed. I had two objects to
                                   attain ; first, <lb/>to represent a picture which should not be
                                   unimpressive yet con-<lb/>sistent with the character that should
                                   describe it ; secondly, <lb/>while I adhered to the style in
                                   which such persons described, to <lb/>take care that words, which
                                   in their minds are impregnated <lb/>with passion, should likewise
                                   convey passion to Readers who <lb/>
               <pb/>
               <milestone n="170" unit="page"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>are not accustomed to sympathise with
                                   men feeling in that <lb/>manner or using <orig>s</orig>uch
                                   language. It <orig>s</orig>eemed to me that this <lb/>might be
                                   done by calling in the assistance of Lyrical and rapid
                                   <lb/>Metre. It was necessary that the Poem, to be natural, should
                                   <lb/>in reality move slowly ; yet I hoped, that, by the aid of
                                   the <lb/>metre, to those who should at all enter into the spirit
                                   of the <lb/>Poem, it would appear to move quickly. The Reader
                                   will have <lb/>the kindness to excuse this note, as I am sensible
                                   that an intro-<lb/>ductory Poem is necessary to give this Poem
                                   its full effect.</p>
            <p>Upon this occasion I will request permission to add a
                                   few <lb/>words closely connected with the Thorn, and many other
                                   Po-<lb/>ems in these Volumes. There is a numerous class of
                                   readers <lb/>who imagine that the same words cannot be repeated
                                   without <lb/>tautology : This is a great error : Virtual
                                   tautology is much <lb/>oftener produced by using different words
                                   when the meaning is <lb/>exactly the same. Words, a Poet’s
                                   words more particularly, <lb/>ought to be weighed in the balance
                                   of feeling and not measured <lb/>by the space which they occupy
                                   upon paper. For the Reader <lb/>cannot be too often reminded,
                                   that Poetry is Passion; it is the <lb/>History or Science of
                                   Feelings. Now every man must know, <lb/>that an attempt is rarely
                                   made to communicate impassion-<lb/>ed feelings, without something
                                   of an accompanying consci-<lb/>ousness of the inadequateness of
                                   our own powers, or the de-<lb/>ficiencies of language. During
                                   such efforts there will be a craving <lb/>in the mind, and as
                                   long as it is unsatisfied, the Speaker will cling <lb/>to the
                                   same words or words of the same character. There are <lb/>also
                                   various other reasons why repetition and apparent tautology
                                   <lb/>are frequently beauties of the highest kind. Among the chief
                                   of <lb/>these reasons is the interest which the mind attaches to
                                   words, <lb/>not only as symbols of the passion, but as
                                        <emph>things</emph>, active and effi-<lb/>cient, which are
                                   of themselves part of the passion. And further, <lb/>from a
                                   spirit of fondness, exultation, and gratitude, the mind
                                   <lb/>luxuriates in the repetition of words, which appear
                                   successfully <lb/>to communicate its feelings. The truth of these
                                   remarks might <lb/>be shewn by innumerable passages from the
                                   Bible, and from the <lb/>impassioned Poetry of every nation.</p>
            <pb/>
            <milestone n="171" unit="page"/>
            <q>
               <p> “ Awake, awake Deborah : awake, awake, utter
                                        a song :<lb/>Arise Barak, and lead thy captivity captive,
                                        thou Son of Abi-<lb/>noam.<lb/> “ At her feet he
                                        bowed, he fell, he lay down : at her feet, he <lb/>bowed, he
                                        fell; where he bowed, there he fell down dead.<lb/> Why is
                                        his Chariot so long in coming ? Why tarry the <lb/>Wheels of
                                        his Chariot?”—Judges, Chap. 5th. Verses 12th
                                        <lb/>27th, and part of the 28th.—See also the whole of
                                        that tumultu-<lb/>ous and wonderful Poem. </p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="noteNav">
            <p>
               <ref target="LBP1-campbell/LBP1-campbell_THORN.html">Back to Single Poem</ref>
               <hi rend="bold large"> || </hi>
               <ref target="LBP1-campbell.html#LBP1-campbell_THORN">Back to Poem in Volume</ref>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="noteMariner">
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="small caps">ote</hi> to the A<hi rend="small caps">ncient</hi> M<hi rend="small caps">arner</hi>
               </hi>, V.I. p. 13.—I cannot <lb/>refuse myself
                                   the gratification of informing such Readers as may <lb/>have been
                                   pleased with this Poem, or with any part of it, that <lb/>they
                                   owe their pleasure in some sort to me ; as the Author was
                                   <lb/>himself very desirous that it should be suppressed. This
                                   wish <lb/>had arisen from a consciousness of the defects of the
                                   Poem, <lb/>and from a knowledge that many persons had been much
                                   dis-<lb/>pleased with it. The Poem of my friend has indeed great
                                   de-<lb/>fects; first, that the principal person has no distinct
                                   character, <lb/>either in his profession of Mariner, or as a
                                   human being who, <lb/>having been long under the controul of
                                   supernatural impressions, <lb/>might be supposed himself to
                                   partake of something supernatu-<lb/>ral ; secondly, that he does
                                   not act, but is continually acted <lb/>upon ; thirdly, that the
                                   events having no necessary connection, <lb/>do not produce each
                                   other ; and lastly, that the imagery is some-<lb/>what too
                                   laboriously accumulated. Yet the Poem contains ma-<lb/>ny
                                   delicate touches of passion, and indeed, the passion is every
                                   <lb/>where true to Nature; a great number of the stanzas present
                                   <lb/>beautiful images, and are expressed with unusual felicity of
                                   lan-<lb/>guage; and the versification, though the Metre is itself
                                   unfit <lb/>for long poems, is harmonious and artfully varied,
                                   exhibiting <lb/>the utmost powers of that Metre, and every
                                   variety of which it is <lb/>capable. It therefore appeared to me,
                                   that these several merits <lb/>(the first of which, namely that
                                   of the passion, is of the highest <lb/>kind) gave to the Poem a
                                   value which is not often possessed by <lb/>better Poems. On this
                                   account I requested of my friend to <lb/>permit me to republish
                                   it.</p>
         </div>
         <pb/>
         <milestone n="172" unit="page"/>
         <div xml:id="noteTintern">
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="small caps">ote</hi> to the Poem on
                                        R<hi>evisiting the </hi>W<hi rend="small caps">ye</hi>
               </hi>, V.
                                   I. p. <lb/>153.—I have not ventured to call this Poem an
                                   Ode ; but it was <lb/>written with a hope that in the
                                   transitions, and the impassioned <lb/>music of the versification
                                   would be found the principal requisites <lb/>of that species of
                                   composition.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
