<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3486.1" type="letter">
            <head>3486.1 Robert Southey to [Unknown Correspondent], [<date when="1820-05-26">26 May 1820</date>] <note type="headnote" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">Endorsement: R Southey<lb/> MS: Special Collections Research Center, University of Kentucky Libraries. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.<lb/> Dating note: Dating from contents – Southey left London for Cambridge on 27 May 1820.</note></head>

            <opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I have a distinct recollection of you, as you may perceive by this token, that you made enquiry of me concerning the
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">author of Count Julian</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"
                     ><title>Count Julian: a Tragedy</title> (1812), by Walter Savage Landor. The work was published anonymously.</note> &#38; were
               one of the few persons who properly appreciated his merits as a poet.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It would give me great pleasure to renew &#38; improve my acquaintance with you. And I should also have been much
               gratified by an opportunity of becoming known to Sir William Curtis,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Curtis, 1st
                  Baronet (1752–1829; <title>DNB</title>), merchant, banker and prominent figure in the government of the City of London. He was one
                  of the MPs for the City 1790–1818 and 1820–1826. Curtis was a consistent supporter of the government. At a celebration dinner on 6
                  April 1820, following his re-election as an MP for the City after a bitter struggle with his Whig opponents, he had denounced
                  radical agitators and praised the Ministry. Curtis was also a supporter of George IV in his battle with his estranged wife, Queen
                  Caroline (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>).</note> respecting as I do the course &#38; the manliness of his political conduct. But I
               am too deeply engaged to allow of this. I have to go thro much business of many kinds, &#38; do not expect to have any thing like a
               feeling of rest till I seat myself in the mail coach for Penrith, in the last week of June.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Whenever you may visit our part of the country again, remember that you need no introduction.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">&#38; believe me my dear sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">yours faithfully</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>

            <postscript>
               <p>I am going to Cambridge tomorrow for the sake of seeing <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">our friend Neville
                  </ref></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
