<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3493.1" type="letter">
            <head>3493.1 Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#LloydCharlesSnr">Charles Lloyd, Senior</ref>], <date when="1820-06-17"
                  >17 June [1820]</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: R Southey 17/6 1820 –<lb/> MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public
                  Library, Misc 4428. ALS; 2p.<lb/> Unpublished.<lb/> Dating note: Dating from content. For Southey’s plan to meet his aunt Mary at
                  Birmingham see his letter to Edith Southey, 25 June 1820, Letter 3497.</note></head>

            <opener><address>
                  <placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">15. Queen Anne Street</ref>. Cavendish Square.</placeName>
               </address>
               <date when="1820-06-17">17. June.</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Will you allow me to request a favour, for which request the case itself will be the best excuse &#38; apology.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My fathers sister</ref>, almost in her seventieth year, has been at
               length prevailed upon to undertake a journey from <del>Xxxx</del> Taunton to Keswick, to see mine &#38; <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> family. I am to meet her at Birmingham, with my friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               Nash, &#38; we shall proceed from thence by chaises, at such a rate as may not fatigue her. I should feel it as an act of particular
               kindness if you would receive her for one night under your roof,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bingley House, on Broad
                  Street, Birmingham.</note> – because she would not be likely to obtain much rest at an inn in your great &#38; busy city. She will
               arrive in the stage from Bristol on Wednesday the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, &#38; we intend to join her by the London mail on the day
               following.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I write this in great haste, or I would reply to some parts of the last letter with which you favoured me, &#38; for
               which I can now only return my thanks. I am so involved in engagements of various kinds that I have scarcely time either for food or
               sleep. I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles</ref> some days ago, &#38; was delighted at seeing him in all
               respects so well. Sophia also was looking in better health, &#38; happier than I had seen her for many years.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">respectfully &#38; truly yours</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
