<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3657.1" type="letter">
            <head>3657.1 Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1821-03-24">24 March
                  [1821]</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Huntington Library, RS 422. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head>


            <opener><salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I receive amusing accounts of my hexameters.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Vision of
                     Judgement</title> (1821).</note> Women, as I expected, readily perceive, &#38; like the metre. Young poets admire it beyond its
                  deserts.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to John Abraham Heraud, 15 March 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of
                     Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3653 and Southey to Ebenezer Elliott, 25 March 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of
                     Robert Southey, Part Six</title>, Letter 3658.</note> Many persons abstain from an opinion till they see which way the wind will
               set. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> says that certainly he does not dislike it so much as he expected. The
               literatuli I hear express their astonishment that I should have ventured to attack <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord
                  Byron</ref>, &#38; anticipate a tremendous visitation of his wrath on my devoted head.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Southey had attacked ‘the Satanic school’ of poetry in the ‘Preface’ to <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), pp.
                  xvii–xxii.</note> – Among my peers, I may in <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> words of old, call
               for a division &#38; count a majority.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Savage Landor, <title>Gebir; a Poem, in Seven
                     Books</title> (London, 1798), p. ii: ‘If there are, now in England, ten men of taste and genius who will applaud my Poem, I
                  declare myself fully content. I will call for a division; I shall count a majority’. The book was no. 1030 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I expect by every post to hear of an explosion in the Prussian States.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Revolutions in Spain, Portugal and Naples in 1820 led Southey to fear further revolts. In the areas of the Rhineland that were
                  incorporated into Prussia in 1815, local elites were fighting a long battle with the government in Berlin to defend their local
                  government system and legal code. But there was no revolutionary outbreak until 1848.</note> – There scarcely seems a chance of
               escape for France &#38; Belgium.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Revolution was avoided in both France and Belgium, but only
                  until 1830.</note> The only possibility (a poor one it is) is that some speedy &#38; signal success of the Austrians may decide the
               business in Naples by proving that <del>in a maro</del> the people care nothing about a revolution, in which the soldiers are moved by
               speculative lawyers, ambitious nobles, &#38; atheistical priests.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Austrian troops crushed the
                  revolution in Naples easily, entering the capital city on 23 March 1821.</note> Yet in other times how one should have wished to see
               Italy shake off the Austrian yoke!</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Europe never wanted a Master Mind so much as at the Congress of Vienna, when all this evil might have been averted.<note
                  n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Congress of Vienna (1814–1815) had settled the borders of Europe after the Napoleonic wars.
                  Southey disapproved of many of its policies, including the decision to keep Italy divided between a number of small states, most of
                  them under Austrian domination.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">– Have you read Michaelis’s “Commentaries on the Laws of Moses”?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann David
                  Michaelis (1717–1791), <title>Mosaisches Recht</title> (1770–1775), translated as <title>Commentaries on the Laws of Moses</title>
                  (1814).</note> – If you have not, there are very few books which would please you more.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to learn from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gee<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Fanny Gee (c. 1772–1846),
                  wife of Captain George Gee (d. 1827), of Wraxall, Somerset. The Gees were renting Ivy Cottage at Rydal. Captain Gee was the son of
                  Thomas Gee, a Bristol merchant, and had been an old schoolmate of Southey’s in Bristol. He seems to have played an important
                  backstage role in organising the Lowther family’s election contests in Westmorland in 1818, 1820 and 1826.</note> that Miss
                  Emma<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Miss Pigott had accompanied Southey and Rickman and his family on their tour of
                  Scotland in August-September 1819. It is difficult to be sure of her identity, but she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown),
                  younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d. 1822) of Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. If this identification is correct, Miss
                  Pigott survived her illness and married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen Hill, Berkshire.</note> has been seriously
               ill. I do not like to think of her as otherwise than in health &#38; happiness, – as she was <del>in</del> &#60;during&#62; our Scotch
               tour which had no other unpleasant circumstance about it than that like all human pleasures – it came to an end. I request <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.</ref> will make my kindest remembrances to her, when next she writes.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">We are tolerably well here, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> continues to
               thrive &#38; to promise well.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">RS.</salute></closer>
            <postscript>
               <p><date when="1821-03-24">March 24.</date></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
